Preface

Preface

Preface

To the best of my recollection, the idea of cognitive pluralism first occurred

to me during an NEH Summer Institute on Meaning held at Rutgers Univer-

sity in 1993. Some initial explorations of the theory found their way into

two previous books, Beyond Reduction (2007) and Laws, Mind, and Free Will

(2011), where I presented cognitive pluralism as a way of explaining dis-

unities of scientific understanding. Although the main arguments of those

books did not depend on cognitive pluralist speculations, many readers

made it clear that they found cognitive pluralism to be the books’ most

interesting and engaging thesis; and I had intended, even before publish-

ing them, to write a stand-alone work on cognitive pluralism once they

were complete. Between the time it took to produce those books and the

demands of academic life, it has taken quite a while to bring this book to

completion. Looking back, I see that much of the early drafting was done

during a sabbatical supported by an NEH Fellowship in 2006–2007. It was

not until a subsequent sabbatical in the fall of 2014 that I was able to pull

together an enormous amount of draft material written piecemeal over

the years and compose the remaining chapters. The anonymous referees

who read the prospectus confirmed my suspicion that what I had pulled

together was too large for one book, and the volume you now have before

you is the result of separating out the material on cognitive architecture,

epistemology, and semantics found here from further discussions of meta-

physics, which will be reframed into a separate volume.

During the writing process, the book went through a number of differ-

ent visions of its scope and intended audience. Several chapters, particu-

larly ones aimed at introducing material such as the history of globalist

and localist views in neuroscience and the attempts of some historically

important philosophers to deal with questions about unities of mind and

understanding, did not make the final cut. These are not, for the most part,

things that could be published as professional articles, but might be of

4 Chapter 1

language, some of which, in the end, might have important consequences

even for our understanding of statements and their truth values.

My point is in a similar vein. Briefly, it might be put something like this:

Philosophers have placed particular emphasis on a number of topics

about thoughts and language, each of which is in itself quite respectable:

the semantic values of concepts and words, the truth conditions of judg-

ments and sentences, the justification of beliefs, and the forms of inference

that are truth preserving. Comparatively little attention has been given to

a topic of equal importance, one that might in the end have important

implications for theories of semantics, truth, epistemology, and reasoning

as well. One name we might give this topic is understanding, though what I

mean by that will have to emerge from the rest of the book.

The ways we frame our questions in different areas of philosophy—

semantics, truth theory, epistemology, logic—tend to force the theories

designed to answer them into particular molds. Questions about semantics

focus our attention on word-sized units: actual words in a natural language,

predicates in a logically regimented language, and individual concepts.

Questions about truth focus our attention on sentence-sized units: sen-

tences, propositions, judgments, and beliefs. Questions about logic and

justification focus our attention on argument-sized units. Moreover, these

three differently sized units are related compositionally: Arguments are

formed out of sentence-sized units inserted into the slots of logical argu-

ment forms. Sentence-sized units, in turn, are composed of word-sized

units inserted into slots of grammatical or logical forms. Units of each of

these sizes occur in language, thought, and logic. They are clearly there to

be found in both natural languages and logically regimented systems, and I

think it not psychologically unrealistic to say that they are important units

of thought as well.

I do not object to treating word-sized, sentence-sized, and argument-sized

units as being fundamentally important to semantics, truth, epistemology,

and logical reasoning; indeed, I think some of the questions of those dis-

ciplines can be satisfied only by theories framed in terms of such units,

even if those theories present an idealized picture of thought (and even of

language). My concern, rather, is twofold. First, collectively, our philosophi-

cal theories form, perhaps not quite a comprehensive theory of thought

and language, but at least a kind of attractor toward a particular type of

theory, or perhaps a set of constraints on what such a theory would have to

look like to accommodate and unify the insights of accounts of semantics,

truth, justification, and reasoning. The basic assumption, which we might

call the “standard view,” is that accounts of thought, understanding, and

5 Introduction

reasoning need to posit just these three types of units: word-sized concepts,

sentence-sized intentional states, and argument-sized inferences—a three-

tiered picture of the elements of our cognitive architecture whose predomi-

nant features are conspicuously modeled on those of a language.

Second, there are other important mental and linguistic phenomena

that seem to require different types of fundamental units—at least if we

are to give an account of them that is psychologically realistic—and the

entrenchment of the traditional theories about the aforementioned philo-

sophical topics may tend to blind us to these other units. The particular

type of unit I am concerned with is what I shall refer to as a mental model of

a content domain. I shall argue that mental models are fundamental units of

understanding, in the sense that understanding comes in the form of mod-

els and in domain-sized chunks. We believe propositions, but we understand

things such as Newtonian mechanics, the game of chess, and the etiquette

for dining in a restaurant, and we do so through having mental models of

those domains. A great deal of what we think of as the semantic proper-

ties of concepts is derived from properties of models in which they play a

role; many inferences (particularly those involved in intuitive judgment

and in expert performance—what contemporary psychologists call System

1 thinking) are produced by model-based processes; and many of our beliefs

are warranted only indirectly by being among the commitments of good

models. This is a familiar claim in psychology and in AI—indeed, in many

ways, the view I am presenting is very similar to Marvin Minsky’s (1974,

1985) frame-based account of the mind and stands in a complementary

relationship to Philip Johnson-Laird’s (1983) work on a slightly different

notion of a mental model—but it has found surprisingly little uptake even

in philosophy of mind, much less in philosophical accounts of epistemol-

ogy, semantics, or reasoning.

There are thus far the rudiments of two types of claims here. First, any

viable account of cognitive architecture has to posit mental models as fun-

damental features of human cognition. Second, a model-based account

of cognitive architecture ultimately has some revisionary implications for

how we should understand meaning, knowledge, and truth as well. Any

realistic model-based account of cognition, however, must also deal with

the fact that we possess mental models of many different content domains,

which we think and reason about in different ways. Indeed, if we under-

stand the world through models of particular domains, there have to be

a very large number of such models, because the list of things we think

about is very long, and indeed open-ended. Perhaps we could (someday,

at Peirce’s ideal end of inquiry) come up with a single “super model” that

6 Chapter 1

would accommodate everything we understand; but that is not how we

really do think about the world, either in ordinary life or in the sciences. It

is because a psychologically plausible model-based cognitive architecture

must encompass many models that I have dubbed my theory cognitive

pluralism.

There are a number of important questions to ask in connection with

this thesis: Why would human (and animal) minds be built so as to under-

stand the world through many distinct models? How do different models

relate to one another, and how can we use several models in conjunction

with one another to triangulate the world? How does the thesis that under-

standing in general is model based differ from the thesis that some aspects of

the mind are “modular” in a sense that is more narrowly confined to cog-

nitive systems that are fully encapsulated, automatic, nativistic, and per-

haps products of natural selection? And how is model-based understanding

related to the kinds of thinking that philosophers more commonly study—

thinking that is (at least putatively) language-like and can involve explicit

arguments?

One feature of models that I emphasize in this book is that models are

idealized. One way in which they are idealized consists simply in the fact

that each model is a model of some specific domain and brackets every-

thing else about the world. But most models are also idealized in the deeper

sense that they provide good-enough ways of thinking and reasoning about

their domains for some particular set of purposes without these being exact,

unidealized, or context-neutral ways of representing their targets. This is

perfectly understandable when viewed from the standpoint of asking how

an organism that is a product of natural selection and possesses only lim-

ited cognitive resources can nonetheless successfully negotiate its environ-

ment. Nature builds organisms with cognitive abilities that are relevant to

their needs, using whatever types of neural resources are available for a

given species, and generally does so with remarkable efficiency. What is

potentially more surprising is that even our most sophisticated modes of

understanding, such as scientific models, are also domain centered and

idealized in the same basic ways, even though they are far more exacting

and track features of the world that are more “objective” in the sense of

being less tied to idiosyncrasies of the individual or the species. A model is

always a model of some particular phenomenon (and not of everything at

once), represented in some particular way (and not in some other way). As a

result, understanding the world through models of its different features also

requires further abilities to recognize when each model can appropriately

be applied and how to use multiple models to triangulate the world.

7 Introduction

The fact that different models represent the world in different ways also

opens up the possibility that two models may not always play well together:

they may be formally incommensurable or lead to conflicting anticipations

about how things in the world will behave. Two models that are each quite

good individually for particular purposes may conflict with each other, and

this raises important questions about whether the kinds of understanding

they supply jointly can be accommodated by a single “super model” that is

intended to “unify” them. This is the kind of problem that drives both the

reductionist agenda in philosophy of science and the search for a grand

unified theory in physics, and many people have assumed that it is only

a matter of time, discovery, and hard work before such projects yield their

desired results. What cognitive pluralism suggests is that the question of

whether we can achieve such explanatory unification depends not only on

how the world is but also on empirical psychological facts about our cogni-

tive architecture.

1.1 Overview of the Book

The book is divided into three parts.

Part 1, “From the Standard View to Cognitive Pluralism,” presents as

a foil for cognitive pluralism a “standard view” that is assumed in main-

stream epistemology, semantics, truth theory, and theory of reasoning,

which does not accord mental models any special role. Instead the standard

view treats the basic types of units found in thinking as analogous to the

three sizes of units found in language and logic: units that are word sized,

sentence sized, and argument sized. It is sentence-sized judgments or beliefs

(or their propositional contents) that are candidates for truth. Sentence-

sized units have semantic values that are largely functions of the meanings

of their constituent concepts plus their compositional syntax (or, if forms

of judgment are not literally syntactic, some structural feature analogous

to syntax). Semantic atomists and holists differ over whether semantic

value is constructed from the ground up, beginning with atomic concepts,

or determined by the entire network of concepts, beliefs, and inferential

commitments; but they agree on the basic units of analysis, with the sole

exception that holists count the entire network as itself the governing

unit. Sentence-sized units (beliefs or judgments) are standardly regarded

as the basic candidates for warrant as well as truth and hence are treated

as the principal units of epistemology, though foundationalists and coher-

entists differ over whether warrant attaches to some beliefs individually,

and the rest through their being the conclusions of valid arguments from

13 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

of beliefs that are properly basic. There are a variety of proposals for what

might make a belief count as properly basic, such as being self-evident or

being produced by a reliable perceptual mechanism; but the basic units

relevant to the foundationalist account are beliefs and inference patterns

ranging over beliefs. Coherentists hold that a belief is warranted by being a

part of a coherent set of beliefs. Again, there are various proposals for just

what kinds of relations count as “coherence,” though consistency is gener-

ally deemed to be a minimal necessary condition. But the relevant relata

are individual beliefs.

A third and more recent theory of knowledge is reliabilism. Reliabilists

hold that a belief is warranted if it is produced by a reliable mechanism.

(A paradigm case would be the production of beliefs through reliable per-

ceptual mechanisms under standard perceiving conditions.) It is perhaps

less clear whether this introduces other types of cognitive phenomena, in

addition to beliefs, that might need to be included in a cognitive architec-

ture for knowledge. On the one hand, we might take the basic relata of a

reliabilist theory to be beliefs and the states of affairs that produce them.

On the other hand, we might take the mechanisms of belief production to

be among the relata, in which case we are then faced with the question

of whether they should be counted as part of cognitive architecture, or as

something noncognitive or even extramental that is nonetheless relevant

to warrant.

We should note, however, that with some beliefs, both their truth and

their warrant may not depend on relations to extramental states of affairs.

These are beliefs that are true because of the meanings of the concepts and

the relationships between them. Propositions like “dogs are animals” and

“triangles are three angled” seem to be true by definition, and we can know

them to be true simply by analysis, based in our mastery of conceptual

semantics.

Semantics is concerned with meaning, and both concepts and beliefs

have semantic properties. Moreover, concepts are constituents of beliefs,

and the semantic properties of a belief (or the proposition believed) are

generally understood to be a function of those of its constituent concepts

plus the logical (or grammatical, or syntactic) form of the proposition (with

a few important caveats, such as that reference may also depend on con-

text). There are important disputes about the basis of semantic properties

(e.g., that they are based in something internal to the mind, such as sense

data, or they latch onto things in the world by direct reference), and also

about the level of organization at which they appear. Semantic atomists hold

that some concepts (semantic atoms) are the most basic bearers of semantic

15 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

knowledge, meaning, truth, inference, and understanding can adequately

be treated using just the resources of the three-tiered picture I shall call the

standard view.

One obvious observation about the units of the three-tiered picture is

that they clearly correspond to the structural units of language and logic as

well. Words in a natural language and predicate letters in logic correspond

to concepts, sentences and well-formed formulas correspond to intentional

states such as beliefs, and both language and logic have larger units called

“arguments” corresponding to inferences, though of course natural lan-

guages have many other types of structured discursive units as well (stories,

jokes, etc.) that are absent from logic. It seems clearest to characterize the

structural size of the units with terminology drawn from the description of

language: that is, as word-sized, sentence-sized, and argument-sized units.

Moreover, some of the ways theorists have expanded on the three-tiered

picture are modeled on things found in linguistics and logic as well: for

example, the idea that the meanings of judgments are a function of the

meanings of concepts plus compositional syntax, and philosophers’ preoc-

cupation with the particular (deductive) forms of inference that predomi-

nate in standard logics. Of course, this raises a number of questions about

the relationship between thinking, language, and logic that I cannot fully

address here. For example, is our capacity for language simply an ability to

express publicly what was already available mentally in the forms of think-

ing characteristic of human minds, or is the ability to think in these ways

a consequence of learning a public language, or at least being a member

of a species whose brains have capacities that were originally selected to

produce competence in spoken language? Does thinking literally take place

in a “language of thought” (Fodor 1975), or is the relationship between

thought and language more analogical—say, that thinking and language

have structural units with similar sizes and functions? I shall not attempt

to settle these questions here. For now, suffice it to say that the theories

of a number of core areas of philosophy suggest that thought, or at least

a significant portion of thought, is “language-like” in the sense of having

structural units analogous to those found in languages.

2.3 Some Philosophical Issues

But do truth theory, epistemology, semantics, and logic really commit us

to such a thesis about cognitive architecture, or indeed to any theses about

cognitive architecture at all? The assumption that they do so presumes that

such theories require, or at least suggest, a kind of psychological realism about

16 Chapter 2

concepts, beliefs, and inferences. There are some important challenges to

this assumption, which require some attention and clarification.

Belief and Judgment

First, the word ‘belief’ is used in several different ways in philosophy (Horst

1995). Sometimes, when we speak of someone “having a belief,” we mean

that she is having a psychological episode in which she is mentally affirming

something. The detective sorts through the evidence and suddenly con-

cludes, “The butler did it!” and we report this by saying that she formed a

belief that the butler did it. But we also speak of people “believing” things

that they have never thought of at all. Suppose I ask you if you believe that

119 + 6 = 125, or that dogs have kidneys. You easily answer yes; and of

course in the process of thinking about it, you probably actually considered

the proposition in question and mentally endorsed it. But suppose I ask you

whether you believed yesterday that 119 + 6 = 125, or that dogs have kidneys.

When I present this question in a classroom, about half of my students tend

to say yes and the other half no. I deliberately choose questions that no one

is likely to have explicitly thought about before to eliminate the possibility

that those who say yes are reporting a previous explicit endorsement. Those

who say no probably do so because they are restricting the word ‘belief’ to

things we have actually thought about and endorsed. But those who say

yes are also using the word ‘belief’ in a perfectly standard way, to report

things we are implicitly committed to or things we are readily disposed to

assent to when prompted. And by my reckoning more often than not, phi-

losophers tend to use ‘belief’ in this broader way, to include what are some-

times distinguished as “dispositional beliefs.” Dispositional beliefs are often

contrasted with “occurrent beliefs”—those that are supposed to be actual

episodes of mental affirmation. Occurrent beliefs are also referred to as judg-

ments in some areas of philosophy; and as this seems a more elegant way of

referring to mental episodes in which we endorse something, I adopt it here

as my preferred terminology, using the word ‘belief’ in the broader sense

that includes dispositions as well.

I have characterized the three-tiered picture in such a fashion as to

include both those who are concerned with judgments and those who are

concerned with beliefs in the broader sense. To the extent that philosophi-

cal and psychological theories of intentionality and reasoning are about

judgments, they seem to require a realist interpretation. A claim that some-

one formed a judgment makes a claim about a mental event and can only

be deemed true if some event at least roughly corresponding to the charac-

terization actually occurred. But to the extent that such theories are about

19 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

contains language-like mental representations corresponding to each of those

beliefs and desires, while another has no such representations, and a third

has representations corresponding to some apt ascriptions of beliefs and

desires but not to others. For example, some of Dennett’s papers include

examples involving chess-playing computers, and some such computers do

what they do by explicitly representing things such as candidate moves

and their consequences in something like propositional form. Nothing in

Dennett’s account should preclude the notion that sometimes we have men-

tal episodes involving language-like propositional representations, or that

they sometimes play a causal role in reasoning. And this is a good thing, as

it seems clear that we at least sometimes do so, when we engage in explicit

and conscious reasoning.

This actually dovetails nicely with the distinction between belief and

judgment in the previous section. Dennett’s characterization of belief

ascription helps us make sense of ascriptions of beliefs that cannot plausi-

bly be construed as ascriptions of judgments: they are, in effect, ascriptions

of normative commitments. Of course, judgments involve normative com-

mitments as well, even though we often do make judgments that are not

ideally rational. Philosophers have raised good and important questions

about whether epistemology does or should apply to beliefs that are not

judgments and, conversely, whether the question of which beliefs are also

judgments is really salient to the concerns of epistemology. (For example,

do questions of warrant really make sense if beliefs are imputed from an

assumption of ideal rationality?) But I will not address those questions here,

as my principal concern is with cognitive architecture.

Another important issue should be addressed. There seem to be clear

cases of language-like judgments: if nothing else, when someone mentally

endorses a proposition by thinking it to herself in a natural language. Like-

wise, clear cases exist in which we can sensibly ascribe to a person a belief

that P in full knowledge that she has never had any thought with the con-

tent P. For example, I recall one college friend describing another by saying,

“He believes he is entitled to half of the speaking time in any conversa-

tion, regardless of how many people are in the conversation.” It was an

apt characterization, but it is unlikely in the extreme that said friend ever

formed, much less endorsed, a thought with that content. Indeed, had he

been presented with that description of himself, he would doubtless either

have disputed it or tried to modify his behavior thereafter. But a wide range

of cases also fall in between. The phone rings, and I reach to pick it up.

Surely some sequence of mental events is going on that we can aptly char-

acterize as “believing the phone is ringing” and “believing that someone is

22 Chapter 2

I think that it is initially plausible that cases of all four types actually exist.

Indeed, I think that evidence for the reality of the first and fourth cases is

clear and compelling. Whether the two intermediate categories are exem-

plified, and how much of our mental life falls into either of them, are the

sort of questions that the cognitive sciences attempt to address.

Two Levels of Intentional Explanation

Advocates of language-like mental representations often appeal to “the suc-

cess of intentional explanation” to justify their position. But it is impor-

tant to distinguish two very different types of explanation here. The first

kind is the sort of explanation of a person’s words or deeds in terms of her

beliefs, desires, and other intentional states that we find ubiquitously in

ordinary life, like the explanation, earlier in the chapter, of why Jane went

to the refrigerator. Fodor and other representationalists do indeed appeal

to the success of such explanations to justify their position, claiming that

such explanations could work only if there really are such things as beliefs

and desires with propositional content that play causal roles in the pro-

duction of behavior, and that the only viable account of how this could

work involves treating them as occurrent mental representations. Dennett

agrees that this kind of explanation works well, but he denies that it should

be taken as the type of explanation that posits causal mechanisms or the

existence of occurrent states called “beliefs” and “desires.” Both of these

positions strike me as at least coherent accounts of the nature of intentional

explanation, and they involve very different commitments to features of

cognitive architecture.

Cognitive science also offers a second and deeper type of explanation,

involving the postulation of mechanisms that explain not only the result-

ing behavior but also things like the time it takes to perform a cognitive

task, what additional forms of information are sought in the accomplish-

ment of a task, characteristic patterns of error and breakdown, and so on. It

is this sort of explanation, not the commonsense explanation of behavior,

that is the real work of theoretical cognitive science. Cognitive scientists

propose accounts of the types of representations and processes that might

underlie different types of competence and performance. There might be

any number of possible cognitive architectures involving different types of

representations and processes that could, in principle, produce the same

end result; but this does not render them indistinguishable, because how

they produce it can have testable consequences. We can prove, for exam-

ple, that chess masters do not decide on a move through brute force serial

evaluation of the possible moves, because we can calculate how many steps

23 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

such a process would require, we know the approximate time in millisec-

onds that a single cognitive operation takes in the human brain, and the

result of combining these factors is far longer than the chess master’s actual

response time.

It would be simply naive to assume that contemporary cognitive scien-

tists who favor a cognitive architecture involving language-like intentional

representations do so merely because explaining people’s actions in terms

of their beliefs and desires succeeds so frequently in ordinary life. Cogni-

tive science is a highly competitive field, in which researchers are exploring

alternative cognitive architectures, procedures, and implementations. In

fact, it is common to distinguish “cognitive science” from “artificial intel-

ligence” on the basis of whether the research is aimed at an empirically

plausible account of human cognition (cognitive science) or the produc-

tion of intelligent machine behavior through whatever means (artificial

intelligence). Theoretical cognitive science is engaged with experimental

evidence from cognitive psychology and holds itself accountable to explain-

ing such evidence. And researchers in competing labs can be avid in their

attempts to show that their approach can accommodate the full range of

data in ways that their competitors’ cannot. Of course, it is part of any

scientific research project that researchers will doggedly try to find ways

to make their own approach work in the face of apparent obstacles. But

when researchers advocate a cognitive architecture that is committed to

language-like propositional representations, they do so generally because

that approach has demonstrated some success at producing explanations

of a number of psychological phenomena that have been demonstrated

in a laboratory, and in a fashion that warrants some hope of a realistic

interpretation.

2

This, however, cuts both ways. Theoretical cognitive science is also

home to a number of theories of cognitive architecture in which language-

like propositional representations play less of a role or none at all; and a

number of aspects of cognition are arguably better explained by alternative

cognitive architectures, such as connectionist architectures, Bayesian nets,

or models, a form of which I am recommending in this book.

2.4 Alternative Proposals regarding Architecture

Several kinds of potential problems for the three-tiered cognitive architec-

ture of the standard view stem from reasons to favor different views of

cognitive architecture. One threat comes from approaches to the mind

that seem to oppose the idea that there is really such a thing as cognitive

24 Chapter 2

architecture at all. A second type of threat comes from concerns that con-

cepts, intentional states, and inference cannot cleanly be separated from a

broader notion of understanding that includes a great deal that cannot be

explained within the framework of the three-tiered picture.

Eliminativism

Some philosophers and psychologists (a minority within both professions),

called “eliminativists,” completely deny some portion of the three-tiered

picture. For example, some claim that there are actually no concepts (Mach-

ery 2009, e.g., is sometimes characterized in this fashion), and others that

there are no beliefs (Churchland 1981; Stich 1983). Sometimes such claims

turn out on closer inspection to be more modest than they might initially

sound. Machery’s Doing without Concepts, for example, is really claiming

that the various rival theories of concepts describe separate phenomena

that cannot be accommodated within a single theory. It is not really the

eliminativist proposal the title might suggest, but a pluralist proposal.

Churchland’s claim that intentional states are “theoretical posits” of what

he deems to be a failed theory does not argue that we never make judg-

ments with propositional content, but argues that intentional psychology,

viewed as a theory that provides causal explanations of behavior, is a stag-

nant research program that even at its best would explain only a limited

range of behavior. These criticisms are indeed responding to the kind of

characterization given to intentional psychology by Fodor, and they raise

real (if controversial) questions about its explanatory scope and success. But

they leave unaddressed the larger question of whether intentional states are

an important structural feature of cognitive architecture (Horst 1995).

Connectionism

Connectionism, which treats cognition as emerging through dynamic

processes that take place in interconnected layers of neuronlike nodes,

involves a very different proposal about cognitive architecture (Rumelhart

and McClelland 1986; Churchland and Sejnowski 1989; Ramsey, Stich, and

Rumelhart 1991). It is controversial (among friends and foes alike) whether

it should be called a “cognitive architecture,” as some writers reserve the word

‘cognitive’ for states, processes, and architectures that operate on units with

representational content (e.g., Pylyshyn 1991), while others apply it more

broadly to subcognitive implementations of cognitive states and processes,

or even to anything that involves information processing, even early pro-

cessing of perceptual information. (Marr’s [1982] book on vision, after all,

is generally regarded as a seminal work in cognitive science.) Connectionist

25 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

accounts often do have their own characterizations of concepts and inten-

tional states—for example, as activation patterns across nodes in intermedi-

ate hidden layers. This approach actually strikes me as being right headed

as an account of judgments (which are transient mental events) as well as

concepts. (It is only when concepts are activated or applied that we should

expect an occurrent state. The notion of having a concept or dispositional

belief need not require a persistent representation corresponding to the

concept or belief.) One can be a connectionist and disavow concepts and

judgments altogether; but often the real issues are about how intentional

phenomena are implemented and whether the dynamic processes that drive

thinking operate over intentional states or merely sometimes have them as

their inputs and outputs.

Embodied Cognition

Advocates of ecological, embodied, and enactive approaches to cognition

have likewise positioned their views in opposition to those based around

representational intentional states.

3

The core thesis of these views is that

cognition is not simply something that takes place within the mind or

brain but a kind of skilled practical engagement with the world. Among

the sources of this relatively new approach to the mind are the twentieth-

century philosopher Martin Heidegger’s (1927/1996) claim that intentional

states are grounded in and dependent on deeper capacities for skilled bodily

activity, and the ecological psychologist J. J. Gibson’s (1977) claim that

organisms perceive and respond directly to affordances (structures in the

world that provide something to the organism or allow it to do something),

rather than inferring and representing them on the basis of brute sensory

data. Cognition is viewed as a dynamic process that encompasses not only

the mind or brain, or even the whole embodied organism, but a dynami-

cally coupled system of interactions between organism and environment

(Silberstein and Chemero 2011; Thompson 2007).

Beyond the provocative thesis that cognition, and even “the mind,”

is not just “in the head,” writers who embrace ecological, embodied, and

enactive theories of cognition make several additional claims of different

degrees of strength. The mildest of these is that there are a variety of pro-

cesses that do not look much like judgments and inferences that none-

theless play essential roles in intelligent interaction with the world and

indeed in sense making. This does not directly threaten commitments to

a cognitive architecture that includes concepts, judgments, and inferences,

but raises a concern, which I explore further in the next section, that this

is a seriously incomplete description of cognitive architecture, and raises

27 A Standard Philosophical View of Cognitive Architecture

different processes seem to operate in very different ways from one another

as well.

None of this is incompatible with the standard view’s supplying a useful

framework for describing the aspects of our mental life that philosophers

have cared most about, which arguably make up a substantial portion of

what is distinctive of human minds. But it does raise the question of how

“open” an architecture it is: whether it is relatively self-contained or can-

not really be separated from other aspects of the mind. Perhaps the old-

est version of this worry in philosophy concerns the relationship between

intentionality and perception. Any epistemological theory faces the ques-

tion of how sensation and perception provide warrant for beliefs. If we

view perception wholly in nonintentional terms, a problem arises for how

perceptual information can be translated into a form that provides warrant.

Conversely, if it has some element of intentionality within it, the realm of

meanings and reasons extends beyond sentence-like intentional states such

as judgments. There are similarly old problems about semantics, such as

whether intentional states include “nonconceptual content,” and to what

extent concepts are dependent on (perhaps even constructions out of) sen-

sations or perceptions.

A slightly different sort of issue is occasioned by psychological theories

claiming that there are undisputedly intentional phenomena that none-

theless seem to be segregated from the rest of our thinking: for example,

special-purpose systems for detecting danger, contagion, or sexual cues,

and special forms of reasoning that are applied only in social cognition.

Evolutionary psychologists suggest that these are isolated cognitive pheno-

typic traits that may well have their own neural substrates, adaptive histo-

ries, and modes of representation and inference. If this implies that they are

separate parts of the mind that work on independent principles, we would

need to posit a much more complicated kind of cognitive architecture. In

chapter 3, I explore an influential strategy for insulating a domain of “cen-

tral cognition,” characterized by the standard view, from threats stemming

from other mental “modules.”

Understanding

A related concern can be raised that does not depend on the assumption

that different parts of our mental lives are a result of separate neural systems

or independent evolutionary adaptations. This is the concern that under-

standing itself involves more than just beliefs or judgments and the kinds of

inferences found in explicit argumentation. We speak of “understanding”

things such as Newtonian mechanics, consequentialist ethics, the game of

28 Chapter 2

chess, the dynamics of free markets, and the Japanese tea ceremony. Under-

standing of any such domain is clearly not something that can be carved

off from the realm of meaning and reasons. It involves an interrelated set

of concepts, beliefs, and semantic, inferential, and practical capacities con-

cerning a particular domain of experience. But this seems to go beyond

the standard view in two ways. First, understanding also involves abilities

to recognize events and situations in terms of those concepts, and to act

in skilled ways within those domains. Second, it at least initially looks as

though understanding needs to be approached in a different way from con-

cepts, beliefs, and inferences: as something whose basic units are domain

sized, where a “domain” is something like the game of chess or the world as

described by Newtonian mechanics. As Catherine Elgin notes:

We understand rules and reasons, actions and passions, objectives and obstacles,

techniques and tools, forms, functions, and fictions, as well as facts. We also un-

derstand pictures, words, equations, and patterns. Ordinarily these are not isolated

accomplishments; they coalesce into an understanding of a subject, discipline, or

field of study. (Elgin 1996, 123)

The idea that a content domain might itself be a fundamental unit for

understanding was developed most influentially in philosophy of science,

beginning in the 1960s, as the idea that scientific theories are not simply

combinations of statements or beliefs that can be specified independently of

one another; rather, the concepts and law claims that make up a theory are

constitutively interdefined, and it is the entire theory that is confirmed or

disconfirmed as a unit by empirical evidence. Theories are integral seman-

tic and epistemic units and indeed are in some sense more fundamental

semantic and epistemic units than the concepts or claims they employ,

as the concepts gain their meaning and the claims their warrant from the

larger unit of the theory, not the other way around. As a consequence, we

do not fully understand concepts, claims, beliefs, judgments, or the special

forms of reasoning distinctive of theories if we do not take this other type of

unit into account. And if that is the case, theory-sized units turn out to be

eminently relevant to the concerns of epistemology, semantics, and truth

theory as well.

Just how broad an implication we should draw from this depends on

whether such features are unique to scientific theories, or whether they are

a more general characteristic of understanding. In chapter 4, I present a

case for the more general thesis that understanding is organized in mental

models of content domains, and this thesis is further developed, under the

name of cognitive pluralism, in chapter 5.

Chapter 3

Central and Modular Cognition

3 Central and Modular Cognition

In the previous chapter, I claimed that mainstream theories about think-

ing tend to treat the mind as a single language-like medium with units of

three distinctive sizes, related to one another compositionally: word-sized

concepts, sentence-sized intentional states (particularly beliefs or judg-

ments), and larger discourse-sized units (particularly deductive arguments).

Theories in a number of core areas of philosophy—epistemology, seman-

tics, truth theory, and logic—are at least tacitly committed to this three-

tiered picture, though each area has its rival theories about matters such as

what makes beliefs warranted, how concepts obtain their semantic values,

what relationship between thoughts and the world is needed for beliefs

to be true, and what are the most appropriate logical formalization(s) of

reasoning. In ordinary life, we often explain people’s behavior in terms of

their beliefs, desires, and other intentional states and how they reason on

the basis of these. And influential mainstream projects in cognitive science

have attempted to provide more explicit and exacting theories of such pro-

cesses through formal and computational models.

While philosophers have often managed to ignore the fact that there is

also much more going on in mind and brain than intentional states and

processes, this option is hardly available within the cognitive sciences. Even

if we were to stipulate that only mental states involving concepts, inten-

tionality, and reasoning are to be called “cognitive,” these still make up

only a part of what goes on within some larger architecture that is needed

to account for things such as sensation, perception, motor control, proprio-

ception, and other topics studied in the cognitive sciences. And this raises

the question of whether, even in this narrow sense of the cognitive, a cogni-

tive architecture can really be specified in a fashion that is independent of

the rest. Alternatively, if we use the word ‘cognitive’ more broadly, can the

architecture for what we might call “the space of meaning and reasons” be

specified independently of a broader cognitive architecture?

33 Central and Modular Cognition

Perception can produce beliefs and other intentional states. Indeed,

when philosophers speak of “perception,” they are often speaking of things

like perceptual gestalts—seeing a dog or seeing something as a dog—that

are reasonably regarded as being intentional states. At the least, they involve

the application of concepts and the formation of assumptions about per-

ceived states of affairs; and some classifications of intentional states (e.g.,

those of Brentano [1874] and Husserl [1900/1973, 1913/1989]) treat such

states as forming a class of intentional states alongside of beliefs, hopes,

and desires. The bulk of what one finds about perception in a neuroscience

textbook, however, is concerned with “early processing” or “preprocessing”

that takes place in the brain before application of concepts, for example,

the separate visual processing pathways in the brain for color, form, and

motion, and the organization of the visual cortex. Most of this processing

not only is unconscious but cannot be made into an object of conscious

awareness through introspection. Moreover, perceptual mechanisms can

operate adaptively without the formation of conscious intentional states.

(And, depending on one’s views of what species of nonhuman animals

have intentional states, it may be possible for perception to drive adaptive

behavior in animals that lack even the capacity for intentional states, or at

least the kind that can enter into reasoning and produce knowledge.) Even

if the philosophers’ paradigm examples of perceptual states are intentional,

supply the warrant for perceptual beliefs, and can enter into reasoning, the

mechanisms that produce these states operate on different, nonintentional,

nonrational principles, and they can produce adaptive behavior even when

they do not produce intentional states. Moreover, there are separate sys-

tems for each perceptual modality, which operate in different ways, and at

least in the case of vision, there are several distinct subsystems that process

different kinds of visual information.

We find much the same thing with motor control. When philosophers

think about the control of bodily activity, they are primarily concerned

with action, in which motor control is driven by intent, often intent that

involves various beliefs and desires and practical reasoning. But what one

finds in a neuroscience textbook is largely about the unconscious, nonin-

tentional, nonrational, and mechanistic operation of circuits in the motor

and premotor cortices and associated noncortical areas. There is a useful

and suggestive distinction between “motor” and “premotor” areas of the

brain—the latter being involved in motor planning and the organization

of behavior into particular sequences of bodily movements—but even

this seems something of a bridge between the “inner” space of conceptual

thought and reasoning and the more mechanism-like operations of the

34 Chapter 3

motor areas. Motor behavior, moreover, can take place without the experi-

ence of intentional states or reasoning, not only in the case of true reflexes

but also, importantly, in the case of expert performance, such as that of an

athlete “in the zone” or a chess master.

Another topic with a similar profile is the comprehension of language.

Phenomenologically, we simply hear sounds as meaningful speech. But

there are complicated mechanisms underlying the processing of sounds

into phonemic, syntactic, and lexical units, and the integration of these

units into an interpretation as meaningful speech via sentence parsing.

Both the operation of these capacities and their acquisition seem to require

special mechanisms, which operate on nonintentional, nonrational prin-

ciples (Chomsky 1965, 1966). Unlike the mechanisms for perception and

motor control, those for comprehension of language seem likely to be

unique to the human species.

In each of these cases, we seem to have phenomena that have one foot

in the world of concepts, intentionality, and the space of reasons, and the

other in the world of neural mechanisms that operate on different prin-

ciples—principles that are in a broad sense “mechanical.” And the relation

between the intentional states and the mechanistic neural processes in this

case is not between a state at a high level of organization and its “realizing

substrate” but more like different links in a causal chain. When we perceive,

early perceptual processing causes conceptually laden perceptual gestalts

and subsequent intentional states and reasoning. When we act, intentional

states and practical reasoning cause the processes that direct bodily move-

ment to come into play.

This, in turn, suggests a basic way of extending the standard view to

accommodate phenomena such as perception, action, and language pars-

ing. There are, as it were, two importantly different types of cognition. On

the one hand, there is “central” cognition, which is the subject matter of

standard philosophical theories and described by the three-tiered picture,

involving concepts, intentional states, and reasoned inference. On the

other hand, there are a variety of “peripheral” processes, operating on dif-

ferent, nonintentional, nonrational principles, which can either produce

outputs into central cognition (in the cases of perception and language

parsing, which indeed might be seen as a specialized form of perception) or

take inputs from central cognition (in the case of the motor systems) and

produce behavior as a consequence. In the next section, I describe a familiar

approach to this division, which contrasts central and peripheral processes

by treating peripheral processes as “modular.”

37 Central and Modular Cognition

stages of visual processing. At some point, the early visual processors pro-

duce output (say, a perceptual gestalt) that is introspectable and can be

used in thinking; but how it was produced, and whatever operations and

representations were used in producing it, are not passed on for further use

(though they can be reconstructed through neuroscientific research). The

systems that perform such operations are thus “cognitively impenetrable”

in the sense that higher thought cannot “see into” them but has to make

do with their outputs.

The opposite question about the information sharing of such systems is

what kind of information they can use. Some types of mental processes are

quite open-ended in what information they can use. My understanding of

cooking and my understanding of thermodynamics might seem like sepa-

rate things. But if, for example, I am cooking at high altitude, I may have to

adjust my cooking in light of what I know about how water boils at differ-

ent altitudes. That is, my culinary prowess is, in principle, capable of using

knowledge that is not itself culinary in character. Likewise, it can use the

input of the senses, proprioceptive feedback, and so on. By contrast, early

perceptual processing seems largely insulated from almost everything else

I know. Conceptual and contextual knowledge do play a role at some point

in perception—say, in forming beliefs about what I am seeing. But they

do not affect how the visual system detects edges or constitutes figures,

as evidenced by the persistence of the standard visual illusions even after

we know them to be illusions. In this way, the early perceptual processing

systems are “encapsulated” in the sense of being insensitive to information

that might exist elsewhere in mind and brain.

Encapsulation, in turn, is plausibly linked to other features Fodor lists

as characteristics of modules. Encapsulated processes have homologues

across a great deal of the animal kingdom and are likely to be products of

evolution, at least weakly nativistic (in the sense of being species typical,

early appearing, and developmentally canalized), and subserved by stan-

dard neural structures. They are also likely to be fast, both because they are

(plausibly) “hardwired” and because they do not waste time gossiping with

the rest of the brain. Because they operate largely on their own, without

input from higher cognition, they are mandatory. And because they are

subserved by standardized species-typical neural mechanisms, they have

characteristic breakdown patterns.

In short, there is a prima facie case that we have a set of processing

systems in the brain that share a certain set of features that give us rea-

son to group them as a class. Moreover, we can see how at least some of

these features might quite naturally be related to one another. Indeed, it

39 Central and Modular Cognition

everything that the scientist knows is, in principle, relevant to determining what else

he ought to believe. In principle, our botany constrains our astronomy, if only we

could think of ways to make them connect. (105)

By saying that scientific confirmation is Quinean, I mean that the degree of con-

firmation assigned to any given hypothesis is sensitive to properties of the entire

belief system; as it were, the shape of our whole science bears on the epistemic status

of each scientific hypothesis. (108)

These points may perhaps be made more clearly without the neologisms. To

take a previous example, one might be tempted to think of culinary under-

standing as a “knowledge domain.” But my culinary beliefs are, at least

potentially, subject to challenge and revision from an open-ended set of

sources. They are, of course, subject to challenge from the senses. (I thought

this would be enough salt, but upon tasting the results, I decide otherwise.)

But they are also subject to challenge from other domains of knowledge:

for instance, I may have to revise the cooking time for a dish when cooking

at high altitude based on what I know about how altitude affects cooking,

or I may revise a recipe in light of what I have learned about how different

cooking techniques affect nutrient content. Or in science, what we discover

about electromagnetism (say, when it is incorporated into quantum theory)

may eventually pose a problem for a corpuscularian view of matter.

In interpreting the claim that central cognition is “Quinean,” it is help-

ful to distinguish a mild Quineanism from a more radical variety. The more

radical variety says that every change in concepts or beliefs necessarily

affects all my concepts and beliefs. To put it crudely, my understanding of

gravitation undergoes subtle changes when I acquire the concept

ARCHDEA-

CON

or learn that Attila the Hun turned back from his siege of Rome after

a conversation with Leo the Great. I have always found such claims wildly

implausible. But a more prudent Quineanism goes something like this: we

hold our concepts and beliefs only tentatively. They are subject to revision

in light of further evidence and integration with other concepts and beliefs.

And there is no a priori boundary to where the reasons for revision might

potentially come from. This milder Quinean thesis makes an interesting

and important claim and is directly relevant to claims about encapsulation,

for if all beliefs are Quinean, they are all, in principle, subject to influence

from all the rest of our beliefs.

We might do well to distinguish this from another kind of argument

for the nonencapsulation of concepts and beliefs. Isotropy and Quinean-

ism are concerned with how concepts and beliefs (recall that the two are

inseparable for Quine) are constituted and how they may be revised. But

knowledge domains are also porous in another way. We can take concepts

40 Chapter 3

and beliefs from different content domains and combine them through

logical machinery. We can string beliefs about different subjects together

with logical connectives. And we can combine them in syllogisms. In this

sense, both thinking and language are “promiscuous”: they are abilities

that allow us to combine beliefs about different content domains, both

in the simple sense of stringing them together with logical connectives

and in the fuller sense of creating new beliefs as a product of deductive

reasoning.

In short, neural localists like Gall had it right about input systems, but

neural globalists like Flourens had it right about thinking. The mind—at

least the human mind—has modular elements, primarily at the sensory

periphery. But all the things we are accustomed to regard as “think-

ing” are nonmodular. And given Fodor’s roots in the computationalist

tradition, the natural term for such processes is “central.” A computer

may use peripheral units like a keyboard, scanner, mouse, and printer,

and even a separate graphics card, each of which contains its own spe-

cial hardware circuitry; but most of the computation is done by a single

“central processing unit” using programs and data stored in a common

memory space.

The book ends on a note of epistemological pessimism. Fodor points

out that whereas the cognitive sciences have been producing impressive

explanations of processes at the sensory and motor peripheries of the

brain, we understand almost nothing about how thinking takes place.

We do not know of neural localizations for various forms of thought

like concepts or judgments the way we do for, say, detection of color

and form. And computational models of thinking founder on the frame

problem—the problem of setting algorithmic (or even heuristic) bound-

aries around what a program should treat as the relevant information in

performing and monitoring a task. This, Fodor points out, has an eerie

resonance with isotropy and Quineanism, and he suggests (plausibly) that

isotropic and Quinean processes may not be susceptible to modeling by

traditional computational approaches in artificial intelligence, and (a bit

more speculatively) there may be no other way to gain epistemic traction

on thinking, either.

3.3 Motivations, Criticisms, and Alternatives

Fodor’s presentation of the distinction between central and modular cogni-

tion at least appears to have been intended primarily as a thesis about cog-

nitive architecture, beholden to empirical data about the mind. Moreover,

41 Central and Modular Cognition

it seems largely to have been case driven: perceptual systems and language

processing (and one might reasonably add motor control to the list) seem

to have a set of distinctive features that differentiate them from concep-

tual thinking and reasoning. Whatever the initial motivations, however,

the bifurcation between central and modular cognition also seems to carve

out a space for the kinds of mental phenomena (concepts, intentional

states, reasoning) studied in several core areas of philosophy (epistemol-

ogy, semantics, truth theory, logic). Moreover, it presents central cognition

as a single representational medium that has a common set of types of

units (word-sized concepts, sentence-sized intentional states, discourse-

sized forms of inference), where thoughts about any subject matter can

be brought into contact with one another, and where they are potentially

mutually relevant. But if central cognition is architecturally unified in this

way, modular cognition, by contrast, is quite disunified: each module has

its own characteristic domain, representational system, and inference pat-

terns, and plausibly its own distinctive neural realization and natural his-

tory in a process of selection.

While Fodor’s notion of a module is widely used in philosophy and the

cognitive sciences, it has also received a great deal of criticism, much of

which can in some measure be traced to the looseness of his characteriza-

tion. Recall that Fodor does not tell us how his various criteria for modular-

ity are supposed to fit together—for example, whether they are supposed to

jointly supply necessary and sufficient conditions. Some things he says—

such as that some of the features are not all-or-nothing affairs but admit of

degrees—might suggest a weaker interpretation; but his conclusion that the

number of modular systems is quite small, limited more or less to process-

ing of perceptual inputs, motor outputs, and language comprehension, sug-

gests that he intends the criteria to be fairly stringent, and he clearly resists

the tendency of some other writers to speak of “modules” wherever a func-

tional decomposition of cognitive abilities occurs (cf. Fodor 2001, 56–57).

Criticisms have therefore come on a number of fronts. Some critics, such

as Jesse Prinz, claim that Fodor’s criteria are too stringent jointly, and in

some cases even individually, to be applied even to the few things that

Fodor considers to be modular. On the other hand, there are any number of

cognitive abilities that share some but not all of Fodor’s criteria.

Fodor’s criteria for modularity do not carve out interesting divisions in the mind.

Systems that have been alleged to be modular cannot be characterized by the prop-

erties on Fodor’s list. At best, these systems have components that satisfy some of

Fodor’s criteria. There is little reason to think that these criteria hang together, and,

42 Chapter 3

when considered individually, they apply to a scattered and sundry assortment of

subsystems. (Prinz 2006, 33)

In subsequent chapters, I make a case that a subset of these features can be

applied equally well to a great deal of what Fodor would count as central

cognition, and they are quite relevant to the question of what units are

needed for a theory of understanding.

The other main objection to Fodorian modularity has come from advo-

cates of the massive modularity thesis (e.g., Carruthers 2006a, 2006b; Tooby

and Cosmides 2005). Fodor claims that while the mind has modules, their

number is comparatively small, largely limited to input and output proces-

sors and a language parser. Advocates of massive modularity argue that the

number of mental modules is actually much larger—perhaps in the hun-

dreds or thousands—and, perhaps more importantly, they are not limited

to “peripheral” processes of perception and motor control.

The massive modularity thesis is generally developed in tandem with

views from evolutionary psychology. We seem to have little problem think-

ing of animal minds as including a grab bag of useful instincts that are prod-

ucts of millions of years of natural selection—that is, of seeing the cognitive

abilities of nonhuman animals as distinctly biological traits. Indeed, phi-

losophers have often doubted that any nonhuman animals possess reason-

ing and other features of centralized cognition. But when we think about

human minds, we tend to have the opposite bias. In spite of believing that

we too are products of natural selection, and indeed that the genetic dis-

tance between us and other primates is slight, we seem to have a hard time

believing that we too possess many psychological traits that are biological

adaptations, and try to attribute as much as possible about our minds to

reasoning.

From a biological standpoint, these biases seem misguided. It is true that

the tiny genetic differences between humans and chimpanzees support

enormous differences in intellectual capacity: the capacity for language,

a greatly expanded ability to create and use tools, more complex social

cognition, and most of what philosophers have lumped under the head-

ings of “thought” and “reason.” And we are right to be interested in these

things, as they are important components of who we are, both as individu-

als and as a species. But biological mutation does not operate by wiping

clean the slate of millions of years’ accumulation of adaptive traits and

designing a new type of mind from scratch. New traits may be built on the

old and transform them in many ways; but many of the old traits are sure

to still exist, and indeed to still be adaptive in many cases. Moreover, new

43 Central and Modular Cognition

species-typical psychological traits are themselves likely to be products of

selection, and perhaps even adaptations.

Evolutionary psychology thus biases the investigation of divisions of

cognitive labor in a direction different from Fodor’s. Fundamental to the

constitution of units of cognition is their selection history. A capacity is a

trait because it is a product of selection. Moreover, evolutionary psychol-

ogists have often assumed that products of selection will be adaptations

rather than exaptations or evolutionary by-products, and tend to classify

the function of a trait in terms of the adaptive advantage it conferred in an

ancient ancestral environment.

Viewing cognitive capacities as grounded in evolutionary processes also

connects nicely with some of the features attributed to modules. Adapta-

tions are encoded in the genome, and this explains their species typicality.

They can thus be expected to have a characteristic developmental sequence

that is strongly canalized. And because they are thought of in biological

terms, it seems plausible that in many cases they will have standard neural

localizations. Both localization and the ability to perform fitness-enhanc-

ing functions suggest that they will be fast and automatic. If we assume

that selection has operated on various traits individually, it seems likely

that the traits will be domain specific, and at least plausible that many of

them will be functionally autonomous from one another, including being

to some extent encapsulated. And if evolution selects “quick-and-dirty”

ways of solving particular problems, and these ways take the form of spe-

cial-purpose mechanisms in the brain, it seems likely that each will have

a representational system that is tooled toward a specific type of problem

and response.

Evolutionary psychology thus makes sense of why a number of Fodor’s

features of modules might go together. It also provides its own criterion

for what is likely to be a module. For a trait to be a module, not only must

it be species typical, but it must be something that could have been pro-

duced through natural selection sufficiently far back in our lineage that the

population it appeared in included common ancestors of all contemporary

human beings. Anything that has appeared during recorded history could

not be a biological adaptation common to the species and hence could not

be a module, even if it had spread to all human cultures through learning

and cultural transmission. (And, indeed, such an ability would be “species

typical” only in a statistical, not a biological, sense.) There is thus an impor-

tant role for something like Fodor’s “central cognition” as well, though the

principal criterion for it lies not in cognitive architecture but in whether

an ability is a product of evolution or of culture and learning. This way

44 Chapter 3

of looking at modules greatly expands the number of cognitive capacities

that could plausibly count as modular. To name a few: folk physics, folk

psychology, folk biology, facial recognition, social contracts, cheater detec-

tion, “mind reading” (assessing the psychological states of others), story-

telling, contagion avoidance, music, dance, empathy, kindness, practical

reasoning, assessment of kinship, incest avoidance, and navigation by dead

reckoning.

Evolutionary psychology is itself a highly controversial approach to the

mind and has received a number of withering critiques from philosophers

of science (Kitcher 1985; O’Hear 1997; Dupré 2001a). Two criticisms stand

out as having special importance. First, evolutionary psychologists have

been criticized for assuming that products of evolution must be adapta-

tions. Critics point out that many heritable traits are evolutionary by-prod-

ucts and exaptations as well. Second, the treatment of traits as adaptations

is linked to highly speculative “just-so stories” about what adaptive advan-

tage a mutation might have conferred in an imagined ancestral environ-

ment, and this adaptational story is then used as an account of the function

of the presumed module.

These criticisms are no doubt justly applied to some of the publications

of evolutionary psychologists. There is a tendency toward “strict adapta-

tionism” within evolutionary psychology, and any account one might give

of what an ancestral environment was like, or the adaptive advantage a trait

conferred in such an environment, will of necessity be highly speculative.

But to my mind, the force of these criticisms is often overestimated. Many

proponents of evolutionary psychology acknowledge that some traits are

exaptations or by-products (cf. Tooby and Cosmides 2005; Carruthers

2006a, 2006b). And the real damage done by this criticism is to the attempt

to ground an account of the function of a module in its ancient adaptive

role, and not to the broader thesis that many special-purpose traits exist

that are products of selection. Likewise, if we abandon the commitment to

strict adaptationism, the speculative “just-so stories” play a much weaker

role in the justification of the massive modularity hypothesis. We have

additional forms of evidence for species-typical traits, such as cross-species

comparisons, and for separation of traits, such as functional and develop-

mental dissociability. To the extent that we are content to speak of heritable

psychological traits in nonhuman animals, there seems little reason to be

skeptical about them when the species in question happens to be our own.

Indeed, even psychologists not inclined to evolutionary reasoning tend to

recognize the existence of things like mechanisms for contagion avoidance

and detection of the mental states of conspecifics.

45 Central and Modular Cognition

For our purposes, however, it is perhaps more useful to note that the mas-

sive modularity thesis is, in important ways, a fairly conservative revision

of Fodor’s thesis. The criteria for modularity may differ considerably from

Fodor’s (Carruthers [2006b], for example, stresses dissociability, domain

specificity, mandatoriness, neural localizability, and central inaccessibil-

ity), but they are not so broad as to include understanding that is accom-

plished through specialized learning: there are not modules for Newtonian

mechanics or chess, though these are ways of understanding particular

domains that involve highly specific proprietary rules and are largely dis-

sociable from other kinds of understanding. Moreover, in many cases, the

postulation of additional modules does not threaten the modular/central

cognition framework. If a module exists for face recognition, contagion,

or cheater detection, it may be encapsulated and cognitively impenetra-

ble and function largely to provide something like a propositional input

for further centralized cognition and behavioral control. (Indeed, many

such purported modules might easily be viewed as specialized perceptual

processing mechanisms for things like faces, cheating, and sources of con-

tagion.) Likewise, it is perfectly compatible with the modular/central cog-

nition framework that modules, operating individually or in tandem, may

sometimes guide behavior in ways that bypass central cognition entirely.

For many animal species, they would probably have to do so, as we must

draw the line somewhere as to what species possess central cognition at all.

More generally, massive modularity threatens the unity of central cogni-

tion only to the extent that the modules postulated actually operate within

the realm of concepts, intentional states, and reasoning. If they merely

supply inputs to central cognition, or execute motor routines in a fashion

caused by central cognition, or bypass it entirely, it really does not matter

how many modules there are. In the next chapter, I look at a number of

types of mental phenomena that clearly involve intentionality and infer-

ence but seem to display some of the features Fodor attributes to modules,

particularly domain specificity, proprietary representational systems, and a

certain degree of automaticity, impenetrability, and encapsulation.

48 Chapter 4

beliefs about anything we are capable of having concepts of and entertain-

ing beliefs about, and mixing them together in thought and inference. Cen-

tral and modular systems can interact, but only in the limited sense that

modular perceptual systems can provide inputs to central cognition, and

central cognition can drive modular motor outputs. In short, the things

that philosophers have traditionally classified as “thinking,” and perhaps

even as “mental,” fall in the sphere of central cognition.

In this chapter, I present several lines of research from the cognitive

sciences that suggest that this bifurcation between central and modular

cognition is not realistic. A great deal of our thinking and understanding,

ranging from an infant’s earliest ways of understanding the world to scien-

tific theory, with all adult commonsense understanding in between, also

seems to be organized around particular content domains, and this seems to

require that we posit units of thinking of corresponding size—considerably

larger than individual concepts, beliefs, and inferences, but considerably

smaller than the entire web of concepts, beliefs, and inferential disposi-

tions. Moreover, to make sense of this, we would seem to need to conclude

that the cognitive systems that deal in these units—mental models, if you

will—must each have their own internal ways of representing their own

domains (often quite different from model to model) and rules for produc-

ing inferences about them. And because expert performance is expertise

in such domains, and the judgments of experts are often, in contrast with

those of novices, fast, automatic, and not reached through explicit reason-

ing, we must conclude that model-based understanding can have these

other features associated with modules as well, even if they are not species

typical and lack standard neural localizations.

The upshot of this is not that thinking is never explicit reasoning in

a language-like system, or that there are not any systems in the brain

that meet the conditions for a Fodorian module. The implication, rather,

is that the bifurcation of the mind into central and modular systems is

not a good or useful one and obscures a much more general feature of cog-

nition: that both within the sphere of meaning and reasons and outside it,

it seems to be a general principle of our cognitive architecture that we deal

with the world through many special-purpose systems that represent differ-

ent features of the world in distinct ways, and we use them in conjunction

with one another rather than integrating them into a single representational

system.

49 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

4.1 Core Systems

In recent years, a number of developmental and cognitive psychologists,

such as Elizabeth Spelke (2000) and Susan Carey (2011), have argued that

the human mind possesses several cognitive systems called core knowledge

systems, which are species typical, strongly canalized in development, and

already evidenced at the earliest ages at which we have ways of testing for

them. The case for core systems is primarily empirical. It consists in evi-

dence that there are particular ways of understanding the world, retained

in adulthood but different from full adult understanding, that appear

extremely early in development. Indeed, they seem to appear too early to

be products of social learning mediated by language, and in some cases,

they are evidenced so early that it is difficult to regard them as products of

learning at all. These include ways of understanding both the physical and

the social world. In their excellent review article, Spelke and Kinzler (2007)

summarize it thus:

Studies of human infants and non-human animals, focused on the ontogenetic and

phylogenetic origins of knowledge, provide evidence for four core knowledge sys-

tems. … These systems serve to represent inanimate objects and their mechanical

interactions, agents and their goal-directed actions, sets and their numerical rela-

tionships of ordering, addition and subtraction, and places in the spatial layout and

their geometric relationships. Each system centers on a set of principles that serves

to individuate the entities in its domain and to support inferences about the enti-

ties’ behavior. Each system, moreover, is characterized by a set of signature limits

that allow investigators to identify the system across tasks, ages, species, and human

cultures. (Spelke and Kinzler 2007, 89)

This is an elegant and compact summary, but precisely for that reason,

there is much to unpack within it. I continue by examining their descrip-

tion of each system, and the evidence used to argue for its existence.

The Core Object System

The first candidate for a core system involves an understanding of contigu-

ous solid Objects with distinct and enduring boundaries. (I will capitalize

the words ‘Object’ and ‘Agent’ when they are used in the special senses that

are internal to the core systems hypothesis.) Very early on, children show

evidence of expecting such Objects to have a certain set of characteristic

properties: they will preserve their boundaries, move as a unit, interact with

one another only through contact, and be set into motion only when acted

on through direct contact. In addition, children show abilities to track such

Objects visually, even when occluded, well before the age that Piaget had

50 Chapter 4

supposed that children “discover” object constancy. The system seems to

have built-in resources for a very limited form of counting as well, or at

least a sensitivity to low numerosities.

It is important to note that the notion of “Object” here is inextricably

linked with the ways things are constituted as Objects. Philosophers are

used to applying the word ‘object’ much more broadly—say, to abstract

objects, to persons, to Cartesian souls, to sets. The notion of the “Object

System” is used in explicit contrast with systems oriented toward inten-

tional agents or sets. The relevant notion of “Object” is further contrasted

with things to which it is not applied, like liquids and heaps. In other

words, the claim is more precisely that there is a psychological system that

is applied to spatiotemporal stimuli that are perceived as being cohesive

and continuous. Indeed, even this is not completely perspicuous, as it sug-

gests that first there is some independent test for properties like cohesion and

continuity, and then, if these are met, the Object System is applied. But in

fact the applications of principles of cohesion and continuity are supposed

to be themselves part of the Object System—indeed, one might venture to

say that if there is such a core system, this is where our ideas of spatiotemporal

cohesion and continuity, as well as Objecthood, originate from.

The Object System is not supposed to be universal in its application.

Rather, it applies only to a subset of things we experience. Indeed, that

subset is more or less defined by the system itself. The “rules” that govern

which experiences activate this system as an interpretive tool—in Kantian

terms, their “schematism”—must appear as early in development as the sys-

tem itself. In these regards, the Object System is importantly different from

some other ways that we come to understand the world later in childhood,

such as foods, artifacts, piles, and liquids.

There also seem to be signature constraints on the ways in which the sys-

tem can be used.

Infants are able to represent only a small number of objects at a time (about

three …). These findings provide evidence that a single system, with signature limits,

underlies infants’ reasoning about the inanimate world. By focusing on these signa-

ture limits, investigators of animal cognition have discovered the same core system of

object representation in adult non-human primates. … Like human infants, mon-

keys’ object representations obey the continuity and contact constraints … and show

a set size limit (of four …). Investigators of cognitive processes in human adults have

discovered that the same system governs adults’ processes of object directed atten-

tion. … Human adults are able to attend to three or four separately moving objects,

for example, when the objects’ boundaries and motions accord with the cohesion

and continuity constraints. Adults fail to track entities beyond this set size limit, and

51 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

they fail to track entities that do not obey the spatiotemporal constraints on objects.

(Spelke and Kinzler 2007, 90)

These latter studies suggest that the core object system is not simply a devel-

opmental stage, like the succession of schemas hypothesized by Piaget,

which were understood to be temporary constructs to be discarded when

a more adequate schema became available. Rather, they seem to involve

enduring capacities that continue to exist in adulthood alongside more

sophisticated adult modes of cognition. And since some of those more

sophisticated forms of adult cognition—such as particular ways of typifying

Objects into more exact categories, and generalized arithmetic abilities—

are subject to cultural variation and transmission, adult cognition should

include the core abilities even if a person has no understanding of arith-

metic operations like addition and multiplication, or even a generalized

notion of the counting numbers.

The Core Number System

Proponents of core systems claim that there is a second system that is also

concerned with numerosity. Whereas the core object system is supposed to

involve abilities involving exact small numerosities, the core number sys-

tem involves abilities to detect and compare significantly larger numerosi-

ties, such as might be presented by two stimuli, one displaying ten objects

and another thirty. This ability is, additionally, nonmodal, in the sense that

it does not operate only on stimuli presented through one sensory modal-

ity. And, significantly, its application is not limited to contiguous Objects

but includes elements such as sounds and actions in its domain. Again,

such abilities appear very early, endure into adulthood, and are found in

nearby species.

The Core Agency System

From early on, children treat people, animals, and other stimuli that dis-

play signs of agency differently from inanimate objects, liquids, and things

like piles of sand. The behaviors of the former are treated as goal directed,

and infants tend to mirror them in their own behavior. Some such mirror-

ing, such as mimicry of four stereotypical facial gestures, has been observed

very early indeed, perhaps as early as hours after birth.

Spatio-temporal principles do not govern infants’ representations of agents, who

need not be cohesive …, continuous in their paths of motion …, or subject to con-

tact in their interactions with other agents. … Instead, the intentional actions of

agents are directed to goals …, and agents achieve their goals through means that are

52 Chapter 4

efficient. … Agents also interact contingently … and reciprocally. … Agents do not

need to have perceptible faces. … When they do, however, infants use their direction

of gaze to interpret their social and non-social actions …, even as newborns. … In

contrast, infants do not interpret the motions of inanimate objects as goal-directed

…, and they do not attempt to mirror such actions. (Spelke and Kinzler 2007, 90)

Interpreting agents differently from inanimate objects is clearly a feature of

adult cognition as well, and a similar profile of agent-directed cognition has

been evidenced by studies of nonhuman animals.

The core agency system is more controversial than some of the other

core systems. One reason for this is that a module for interpreting Agency

(capitalized to reflect its special usage within the theory) requires encoding

of specialized ways of detecting some highly sophisticated phenomena.

An innate ability to detect contiguous solids requires much less sophis-

tication of design than one to detect purposeful action. But by the same

token, Agency should be a difficult notion for humans (or other animals)

to construct out of a prior inventory of notions confined to spatiotempo-

ral properties of stimuli. (Indeed, one might argue that such notions are

insufficient to the task. Agency-concepts are not a conservative extension

of Object-concepts.) In other words, there is reason to think that this is

exactly the sort of case where one might most strongly expect to find

special-purpose ways of understanding the world, on grounds similar to

Chomsky’s “poverty of the stimulus” argument for an innate grammar

module. People and tree leaves both move, and perhaps even an empiri-

cist mind could detect that they display different patterns of movement.

However, it is less clear that, just on the basis of the objects and their

movements, such a mind could come up with the hypothesis of Agency.

And even if it could do so, there are an open-ended number of ways

of grouping different types of motion that would be hypotheses equally

consistent with the data. But in fact we all employ more or less the same

framework for interpreting Agents, and we show evidence of doing so very

early. Since the stimuli underdetermine this interpretation, we have rea-

son to think that there is at least some innate bias toward it. In addition,

it is not clear that we could function as members of a social species, or

engage in particular types of early social learning, without the very early

introduction of something that allows us to treat conspecifics as having

typical features of Agency, and so it seems likely that any social species

must possess developmentally canalized species-typical cognitive abilities

for the detection of Agency.

The core agency system would seem to be constitutively tied to our

notions of Agency. That is, if the hypothesis is correct, we may be unable to

53 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

get outside our innate understanding of Agency to analyze it or its domain

in nonintentional terms. We can, to be sure, come to understand that some

things that initially seemed to be Agents—say, characters in cartoons—are

not really bona fide Agents at all. But it seems unlikely that we can cash out

the phenomena that are interpreted by this system, or the things that make

up its domain, in anything but an intentional vocabulary. Such notions

as we have in this region of our conceptual space would seem to be tied

to our developmentally canalized endowment of core capacities, even if

they can be expanded on, enriched, and adumbrated. In this respect, Den-

nett’s (1971, 1987) idea of an intentional stance—a special framework for

interpreting things as acting on the basis of their beliefs and goals—seems

well conceived. Likewise, the domain specificity of the core agency system

seems constitutive in nature. That is, one cannot specify the class of things

to which the system is applied except through the system itself, or perhaps

some more sophisticated descendant of it.

The Core Geometric System

The fourth core system is devoted to an understanding of the geometric

properties of the environment, “the distance, angle, and sense relations

among extended surfaces in the surrounding layout” (Spelke and Kinzler

2007, 91). It does not represent nongeometric properties such as color or

odor (91). The evidence for such a system is drawn from studies of how chil-

dren, adults, and nonhuman animals orient themselves spatially. Adults

use at least two orienting systems, one guided by surface geometry and

the other by landmarks. The landmark-based orientation system develops

later, whereas the geometric orientation system is evidenced very early. The

Geometric System, moreover, seems to undergo an important type of gen-

eralization as it becomes dissociated from the need for a fixed origin and

angle of orientation.

The existence of such a system may seem either obvious or unnecessary.

The geometrical character of the physical world seems so patently obvious

that it may seem unclear why we should need a special system to under-

stand it. Yet this very obviousness may simply be a product of how deeply

ingrained our geometric assumptions in fact are. (As Kant suggested, we

may actually be unable to perceive space except as structured by a highly

specific geometry.) We can see this most readily by considering artifacts

that have some features of human perception while lacking others. A cam-

era receives visual information about the environment but does not inter-

pret that information as being a product of a three-dimensional world. To

get a computer to infer such a world of objects from optical input devices

55 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

they allow for anticipations, predictions, inferences, and motor planning.

In this respect, they seem much more like Fodor’s central cognition and in

particular have similarities to the other, more sophisticated, ways that we

acquire of thinking about objects, agents, space, and numerosity through

later development and specialized learning, like the folk theories described

in the next section. Both the core systems and these later-acquired ways of

conceptualizing the world are “domain specific” in that they are ways of

thinking about particular parts of aspects of the world. Yet at the same time,

they do not allow for cross-domain reasoning within themselves, a defining

feature of central cognition.

An important question about the core systems as a group is how they

are related to one another. In particular, the two systems that provide ways

of categorizing types of things—the Object and Agency systems—are func-

tionally dissociable from each other and have contradictory rules, yet one

and the same thing can trigger either or both systems. The psychologist

Paul Bloom (2004), for example, emphasizes that children (and adults) can

think of something as an Agent without thinking of it as an Object, and

argues that this dissociability might be what lends intuitive plausibility to

the idea of a soul that is independent of the body. When the Agency sys-

tem operates without the Object system, one conceives of a thing as an

Agent but not as an Object, and such a thought is not counterintuitive to

the child because only the Agency system is in play, and it has no rules

that require Agents to also be Objects. Indeed, some of the rules of the two

systems are logically incompatible: Agents move on the basis of their own

goals, whereas Objects are incapable of self-initiated motion. Objects must

move from place to place in spatially continuous paths, and infants show

surprise if things that have shown the profile of Objects seem to disappear

from one place and reappear in another, but do not show the same surprise

when things showing the profile of Agents do so. Nothing could really cor-

respond to the rules of both the Agency and the Object systems, because

some of the rules of the two systems contradict one another.

At the same time, a single stimulus might be able to trigger either sys-

tem, perhaps even both at once. A toy that is made with features such as

a face, like Thomas the Tank Engine, might at one time be regarded as an

Object, which the child expects to move only when someone pushes it

down the tracks. But at another time it might be regarded as an Agent,

especially when the child has reached an age when she can watch vid-

eos depicting it as doing agential things or hear stories about its adven-

tures. Indeed, even without the deliberately ambiguous features, a model

train that is first observed inert might be assumed to be an Object and

56 Chapter 4

then, to the child’s surprise, be reconstituted as an Agent when the power

switch is thrown and the train begins to move without any obvious exter-

nal cause.

Of course, as I have described the examples, the identification of the

Agent and the Object as “the same thing” is supplied from the perspective

of the adult observer, and in the examples described, the stimulus is per-

ceived first through one core system and then through the other. It is less

clear whether (a) a single stimulus can simultaneously trigger both systems,

and (b) if it can do so, whether the child can bind the two representa-

tions together as representations of the selfsame object and regard one and

the same thing as being both Agent and Object. Bloom seems to think

not and claims that we naturally think of human beings as consisting of

two things—a body (an Object) and a soul (an Agent). I am skeptical of

Bloom’s conclusion. Adults, at least, seem to be quite capable of triangulat-

ing a single object through multiple cognitive lenses, even if the two ways

of regarding it are logically incompatible. Of course, it is possible that we

do this through some mechanism other than the core systems. And even if

adults can triangulate through the core systems, it is also possible that the

ability is acquired only long after the core systems are in place. While the

specific question about how the core systems can be combined is an empiri-

cal question requiring more research, there is nonetheless an important

point here about some forms of cognition: that we understand the selfsame

object through more than one way of thinking about it, and incompatibili-

ties between the two ways of thinking about it do not seem to present an

obstacle to the psychological possibility of doing so.

4.2 Folk Theories

A second and slightly older hypothesis in cognitive and developmental psy-

chology is the claim that ordinary human understanding involves implicit

theories about the natural, biological, mental, and social world, acquired

over the course of early to middle childhood and persisting through adult-

hood. These implicit theories are commonly referred to by names such as

“folk physics,” “folk biology,” and “folk psychology.” They consist of what-

ever species-typical assumptions there may be about matters such as how

objects move when thrown or dropped, what features we can expect of

any animal species (e.g., that individual animals of a species are offspring

of parents of the same species, have a species-typical physiology and diet,

etc.), and how we interpret people’s actions as consequences of their beliefs

and desires.

57 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

Developmentalists who study folk theories note that they are not com-

pletely mastered until sometime in mid- to late childhood (the time frame

varies with the folk theory) and have some typical developmental sequenc-

ing (cf. Gopnik and Meltzoff 1997; Gopnik 1996). For example, children

attribute beliefs to other people before they understand that other people’s

beliefs are different from their own. This latter capacity is generally gained

at an age of around four or five years in human children, and it is a matter

of some controversy which, if any, other animal species share it. Advo-

cates of the view that commonsense understanding is theoretical—some-

times called “the theory-theory”—tend to characterize this understanding

in terms of general beliefs, like “animals have parents of the same species”

and “people tend to do what they believe will bring about the things they

desire.” The different forms of folk understanding (e.g., folk biology and

folk psychology) also seem to have their own central concepts, like

SPECIES

and

BELIEF, and characteristic inference patterns. Folk-theoretic understand-

ing is thus described in the vocabulary used for what Fodor calls central

cognition, though folk theories themselves have some characteristics of

modules, such as being domain specific, appearing in a characteristic devel-

opmental sequence, being applied automatically, and having their own

special categories, forms of representation, and inference rules.

Some cognitivists also suggest that these somewhat abstract central con-

cepts also form a kind of template for more specific concepts. Pascal Boyer

(2001), for example, calls the concepts

ANIMAL and PERSON “ontological cat-

egories.” When a person learns a new animal concept—say,

ZEBRA—she does

not need to learn that members of the kind will have a characteristic diet,

physiology, and means of reproduction. The

ANIMAL category is used as a

template, with “slots” for certain types of information that are assumed

to be available for all species and can be filled in with more specific infor-

mation about a particular species as one learns more about it. Thus even

children know many of the right questions to ask to learn more about a

new animal kind they have just encountered or been told about: What

do they eat, and how do they get their food? How big do they get? What

kind of environment do they live in? How do they move around? Thus

something about the structure of the folk theory encodes a certain kind of

understanding—often left tacit—that guides the formation of more particu-

lar beliefs.

While the acquisition of folk theories seems to be strongly develop-

mentally canalized—they are species-typical features of how adults and

older children think about physical objects, persons, and animals, and

these appear at characteristic ages and in characteristic developmental

59 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

to see competing (or successor) theories not so much in terms of making

incompatible claims in the same vocabulary as offering alternative ways

of conceptualizing their subject matter. Competing (or successor) theories

came to be regarded not so much as contradictory as incommensurable, and

theory change not as piecemeal change in particular scientific beliefs but

as revolutionary change in paradigms for understanding particular aspects

of the world.

A number of different philosophers played roles in developing a new

consensus understanding of scientific theories—Thomas Kuhn, Imre Laka-

tos, Paul Feyerabend, and David Lewis all certainly deserve special men-

tion—and entire books have been written about their works, individually

and collectively. As my aim here is merely to pick out certain consensus

views, I will not even attempt to do justice to all the contributors to this

important period in the philosophy of science. I will cite Kuhn as a main

contributor, though ultimately my interest is as much in his later views

(around the time of his 2000 APA presidential address) as in his seminal The

Structure of Scientific Revolutions (1962).

Kuhn’s initial approach was as a historian of science, concerned with

the nature of theory change. As an introduction, here is an extended quote

offered retrospectively in a later publication:

A historian reading an out-of-date scientific text characteristically encounters pas-

sages that make no sense. That is an experience I have had repeatedly whether my

subject is an Aristotle, a Newton, a Volta, a Bohr, or a Planck. It has been standard to

ignore such passages or to dismiss them as products of error, ignorance, or supersti-

tion, and that response is occasionally appropriate. More often, however, sympa-

thetic contemplation of the troublesome passages suggests a different diagnosis. The

apparent textual anomalies are artifacts, products of misreading.

For lack of an alternative, the historian has been understanding words and phras-

es in the text as he or she would if they had occurred in contemporary discourse.

Through much of the text that way of reading proceeds without difficulty; most

terms in the historian’s vocabulary are still used as they were by the author of the

text. But some sets of interrelated terms are not, and it is [the] failure to isolate those

terms and to discover how they were used that has permitted the passages in ques-

tion to seem anomalous. Apparent anomaly is thus ordinarily evidence of the need

for local adjustment of the lexicon, and it often provides clues to the nature of that

adjustment as well. An important clue to problems in reading Aristotle’s physics

is provided by the discovery that the term translated ‘motion’ in his text refers not

simply to change of position but to all changes characterized by two end points.

Similar difficulties in reading Planck’s early papers begin to dissolve with the dis-

covery that, for Planck before 1907, ‘the energy element hv’ referred, not to a physi-

cally indivisible atom of energy (later to be called ‘the energy quantum’) but to a

60 Chapter 4

mental subdivision of the energy continuum, any point on which could be physically

occupied.

These examples all turn out to involve more than mere changes in the use of

terms, thus illustrating what I had in mind years ago when speaking of the “in-

commensurability” of successive scientific theories. In its original mathematical use

‘incommensurability’ meant “no common measure,” for example of the hypotenuse

and side of an isosceles right triangle. Applied to a pair of theories in the same his-

torical line, the term meant that there was no common language into which both

could be fully translated. (Kuhn 1989/2000, 9–10)

While scientific theories employ terms used more generally in ordinary

language, and the same term may appear in multiple theories, key theo-

retical terminology is proprietary to the theory and cannot be understood

apart from it. To learn a new theory, one must master the terminology as

a whole: “Many of the referring terms of at least scientific languages can-

not be acquired or defined one at a time but must instead be learned in

clusters” (Kuhn 1983/2000, 211). And as the meanings of the terms and

the connections between them differ from theory to theory, a statement

from one theory may literally be nonsensical in the framework of another.

The Newtonian notions of absolute space and of mass that is independent

of velocity, for example, are nonsensical within the context of relativistic

mechanics. The different theoretical vocabularies are also tied to different

theoretical taxonomies of objects. Ptolemy’s theory classified the sun as a

planet, defined as something that orbits the Earth, whereas Copernicus’s

theory classified the sun as a star and planets as things that orbit stars,

hence making the Earth a planet. Moreover, not only does the classificatory

vocabulary of a theory come as an ensemble—with different elements in

nonoverlapping contrast classes—but it is also interdefined with the laws of

the theory. The tight constitutive interconnections within scientific theo-

ries between terms and other terms, and between terms and laws, have

the important consequence that any change in terms or laws ramifies to

constitute changes in meanings of terms and the law or laws involved with

the theory (though, in significant contrast with Quinean holism, it need

not ramify to constitute changes in meaning, belief, or inferential commit-

ments outside the boundaries of the theory).

While Kuhn’s initial interest was in revolutionary changes in theories

about what is in a broader sense a single phenomenon (e.g., changes in

theories of gravitation, thermodynamics, or astronomy), he later came to

realize that similar considerations could be applied to differences in uses

of theoretical terms between contemporary subdisciplines in a science

(1983/2000, 238). And while he continued to favor a linguistic analogy

61 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

for talking about conceptual change and incommensurability, he moved

from speaking about moving between theories as “translation” to a “bilin-

gualism” that afforded multiple resources for understanding the world—a

change that is particularly important when considering differences in terms

as used in different subdisciplines.

Scientific theories are thus like modules in having specific domains,

which are represented in a proprietary fashion. There are as many scientific

theories as there are well-understood phenomena, and each theory is con-

stitutively intertwined with the ways phenomena are understood through

it. Theories likewise employ proprietary taxonomies of object kinds, prop-

erties, relations, and transformations and use proprietary representational

systems with their own inference rules. But theories are unlike Fodorian

modules in that they are products of learning, and subject to scrutiny

and revision. Indeed, scientific theories are a case par excellence of intel-

lectual products that require explicit representation. Moreover, they are

like Fodorian central cognition in that they can be combined with other

forms of thought in reasoning: they can be combined with other theoreti-

cal claims and with commonsense observation and thinking in reasoning

to a conclusion, their appropriate use can be monitored through ways of

evaluating context, and their content can be challenged through observa-

tion and dialectic.

4.4 Intuitive Reasoning, Semantic Reasoning, and Knowledge

Representation

We have thus far looked at several kinds of cognition that do not fit com-

fortably into the bifurcated framework of central and modular cognition.

Core systems, folk theories, and scientific theories are domain specific,

and the understanding they underwrite comes in units larger than the

size of individual concepts and beliefs, but smaller than the entire web

of concepts, beliefs, and inference patterns. Core systems, like modules,

are unlearned and cannot be altered; folk theories and scientific theories

are products of learning, and the learning and alteration of them involve

wholesale alterations in units the size of a domain-centered theory because

the concepts and inference patterns distinctive of them are constitutively

interdefined. They involve implicit divisions of their domains into what we

might call implicit ontologies, with proprietary categories for kinds of things,

properties, relations, and transformations. And once learned to the level of

expertise, they can operate more or less automatically, quickly producing

thoughts and inferences that are “intuitive” in the sense that they are not

62 Chapter 4

based on explicit conscious reasoning. In these ways, they have much in

common with Fodorian modules.

With respect to some of Fodor’s other criteria, they differ from one

another: core systems are highly developmentally canalized, folk theories

are canalized as well but require a great deal of training and bootstrap-

ping, while scientific theories are products of specialized learning, usually

requiring invention or instruction. Core and folk systems, but not scientific

theories, are plausibly products of evolution and may have species-typical

neural realizations. It would seem that the mind has some uses for domain-

specific understanding that is not modular in Fodor’s sense. But perhaps it

is too early to draw general conclusions from this, as core systems, folk the-

ories, and scientific theories, while clearly “mental” in ways that perceptual

input processors are not, are each rather special forms of cognition, in the

first two cases distinguished by their early appearance and developmental

canalization, and in the latter by the specialized learning required.

But in fact we have good reason to think that domain-sized units of

understanding, with proprietary ways of representing domains and tight

connections between concepts and inference patterns within the domain

but much looser connections across domain boundaries, are found broadly

within what Fodor would classify as central cognition. They would seem to

be, among other things, the basis for semantically based reasoning and intu-

itive inference. One reason for thinking this might be so is that researchers

in artificial intelligence, who started out trying to simulate human cogni-

tive abilities on the model of explicit reasoning in something like central

cognition, ended up having to turn to theories positing domain-specific

understanding to explain everyday intuitive reasoning abilities.

Artificial intelligence emerged as a discipline fast on the heels of Turing’s

seminal discussion of digital computation. The first projects in AI were still

closely tied to computation’s mathematical heritage. They were automated

theorem provers like Newell and Simon’s (1956) Logic Theory Machine.

The viability of theorem-proving computers was already assured in prin-

ciple by Turing’s theoretical work. A computer can execute any formalized

algorithm, and so any proof that can be carried out by formal means can in

principle be proved by a computing machine. Researchers then attempted

to model human formal reasoning more generally, in systems like General

Problem Solver (Newell, Shaw, and Simon 1959). Such work is often viewed

as the first generation of AI.

In attempting to model human reasoning more generally, however, AI

researchers quickly hit an important roadblock. Precisely because formal rea-

soning techniques abstract away from the semantic values of the symbols,

63 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

they are unsuited to underwriting the many semantically based inferences

human beings routinely perform. Formal techniques treat predicates like

‘dog’ as lexical primitives. They underwrite valid syllogisms involving such

lexical units, but not the knowledge that is present in human semantic

competence. For example, we all know that if Lassie is a dog, then Lassie

is an animal, she has a weight, she has bones and kidneys, and so on. But

to get a computer to simulate this type of understanding, we must equip it

with more than the ability to perform valid inference techniques on sym-

bolic structures like “Lassie is a dog.” In short, we must encode human-level

semantic understanding of the concept

DOG.

One way to do this is to supply the computer with a set of explicit propo-

sitional representations, like “all dogs are animals,” “dogs have bones,” and

so on. If this could be done with everything we know about dogs, it might

allow formal inference techniques to generate a set of inferences equivalent

to those a human being would make. And if our only concern were to get

a computer to reach the same conclusions humans would reach, regardless

of how they reach them, this might be enough. But if we are also concerned

to get the computer to make such inferences in a fashion that resembles the

way human beings make them, encoding semantic understanding in the

form of explicit propositional representations seems psychologically unre-

alistic. We understand things we have never put into explicit propositional

form. You may never have considered the proposition “dogs have kidneys”

before, but in some sense you understood it to be true. You may never have

entertained the proposition “119 + 7 = 126” before, but it was in some sense

implicit in your mathematical understanding. And indeed we are inclined

to say that we knew those things yesterday, even though we had never

thought of them. That is, we didn’t just learn them overnight, and had we

been asked, we would have given the right answer without any difficulty.

A second way of approaching the problem is to model semantic under-

standing, not in the form of explicit propositions but in terms of a data

structure—say, like that of a relational database. The second generation of AI

was largely devoted to exploring the way semantic understanding is struc-

tured as data. The appeal of this strategy lay not only in its greater ability

to produce simulations that could not be achieved through propositional

representation, but also because it seems the more psychologically realistic,

natural way to model semantic relations that are couched at the concep-

tual, rather than the propositional, level. The work of the models is done,

however, not at the level of the semantics of individual conceptual or lexi-

cal units, but in explicating the systematic relations between them. Treat-

ing semantic relations as data structures also has the advantage that many

64 Chapter 4

such relations are not well captured by standard logical machinery. Our

understanding, say, that dogs are four-legged is not accurately captured by

the proposition “All dogs have four legs,” as we understand that some dogs

have lost one or more legs, and indeed a few dogs have extra legs. Some sort

of semantic link clearly exists between the concepts

DOG and FOUR-LEGGED,

and perhaps one could devise a logical operator that would track this link

extensionally. But as it is not clear from the outset how to do this, we are

well served to find a way to model such links, if we can, in a fashion that

avoids the problem of how to model their precise relation to extensional

logic.

Information Chunking in Knowledge Representation

The second generation of AI, in the 1970s, was marked by efforts to explore

such an approach. Marvin Minsky, writing in 1974, sums up the general

concerns as follows:

It seems to me that the ingredients of most theories both in Artificial Intelligence

and in Psychology have been on the whole too minute, local, and unstructured to

account—either practically or phenomenologically—for the effectiveness of com-

mon-sense thought. The “chunks” of reasoning, language, memory, and “percep-

tion” ought to be larger and more structured; their factual and procedural contents

must be more intimately connected in order to explain the apparent power and

speed of mental activities.

Similar feelings seem to be emerging in several centers working on theories of

intelligence. They take one form in the proposal of Papert and myself … to sub-

structure knowledge into “micro-worlds”; another form in the “Problem-spaces” of

Newell and Simon …; and yet another in new, large structures that theorists like

Schank …, Abelson …, and Norman … assign to linguistic objects. I see all these as

moving away from the traditional attempts both by behavioristic psychologists and

by logic-oriented students of Artificial Intelligence in trying to represent knowledge

as collections of separate, simple fragments. (Minsky 1974)

It is useful to look at a few examples of such proposed structures for model-

ing understanding and knowledge deriving from these projects.

Semantic Networks

Semantic networks are data structures for encoding the semantic relations

between lexical or conceptual units. The structure of semantic networks is

best conveyed in diagrammatic form. Conceptual or lexical units are rep-

resented by nodes (diagrammatically, by words or by boxes or other closed

figures), and semantic relations between them by links between nodes (dia-

grammatically, by lines and arrows) (fig. 4.1). One important relationship

66 Chapter 4

might be structured in human beings (the “structure” in question being a

kind of abstract formal/functional structure, not an anatomical structure).

It is an approach that seems more psychologically realistic than treating

our semantic understanding as a matter of having an enormous number

of explicit propositional beliefs like “dogs are animals.” Our understanding

of dogs seems to involve a vast network of things that we seldom if ever

explicitly think about, but which are in some sense “there” for us should

we ever need to access them. It is tempting, in trying to characterize what

we do when we employ semantically based understanding, to turn to meta-

phors like tracing down the strands of a web until we find what we need.

Of course, neither introspection nor the formalism of semantic networks

can tell us how—through what mechanisms—this is accomplished in the

human brain. But it seems, at some level of abstraction, to get something

right about our psychology that is not captured by treating semantic under-

standing in terms of formal inference: there is a great deal of our under-

standing that is packed into semantic relations, and our way of accessing

this understanding is different from the retrieval of stored propositional

representations.

Another advantage of the semantic network approach is that it leaves

the question of what types of links there might be as one that can be guided

by empirical research, rather than forcing it into the mold of whatever logic

a theorist happens to be most familiar with. Indeed, research in knowledge

representation has led to an expansion of our understanding of the types of

logics that might be relevant to modeling human thought.

Semantic networks in AI bear important resemblances to network theo-

ries of meaning in philosophy of language and provide a machinery for

testing and refining such theories. But they also raise an important question

that philosophers often overlook. Given that our semantic understanding is

characterized, at least in part, by links between conceptual or lexical units,

are all such units connected into a single network, or are there perhaps a

variety of disjoint networks whose units can be connected nonsemantically

through language and syntactically based inference techniques? In philoso-

phy, advocates of network views tend also to be holists. But semantic net-

work modeling does not require holism, though it is compatible with it.

The topology of semantic connections is ultimately an empirical question,

and one that bears heavily on the topics of unities and disunities of mind

and understanding.

67 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

Frames

Semantic networks are structures for representing and encoding semantic

understanding at the level of semantic relations between conceptual or lexi-

cal units. Semantic understanding and logical deduction, however, do not

exhaust the types of cognitive skills that are needed for understanding and

interacting with the everyday world. When we interact with a new object

of a familiar type, or walk into a situation of a type we have encountered

before, we do not have to start from the ground up in assessing the situation

or knowing what to expect. In interpreting an object as a ball or a cube, or

a room as the dining room of a restaurant, we automatically have a whole

set of expectations about what we will encounter, what sorts of actions we

might perform that are relevant to that situation (and perhaps even stereo-

typical of it), and what sequence of events we would expect to ensue if we

were to perform one or another of those actions. We automatically assume

a great deal about the object or situation that is not directly perceived: that

the cube will look a certain way if we were to go around to the other side,

that the hostess will seat us, that there is an unseen kitchen where food is

being prepared, that we will be expected to pay for our meal, and so on.

In short, we seem to have mental models of various familiar types of

objects and situations. Such models allow for a great deal of variety of detail

to be filled in and actively explored, but they will also often involve default

expectations. For example, unless one sees a cafeteria line or a sign saying

“Please Seat Yourself,” we assume that someone who works for the restau-

rant will come and take us to a table. Marvin Minsky (1974) writes of this:

When we enter a room we seem to see the entire scene at a glance. But seeing is really

an extended process. It takes time to fill in details, collect evidence, make conjec-

tures, test, deduce, and interpret in ways that depend on our knowledge, expecta-

tions and goals. Wrong first impressions have to be revised. Nevertheless, all this

proceeds so quickly and smoothly that it seems to demand a special explanation.

The “special explanation” he offers is that such abilities are underwritten by

a particular type of knowledge structure that he calls a “frame.”

A frame is a data-structure for representing a stereotyped situation, like being in a

certain kind of living room, or going to a child’s birthday party. Attached to each

frame are several kinds of information. Some of this information is about how to use

the frame. Some is about what one can expect to happen next. Some is about what

to do if these expectations are not confirmed.

We can think of a frame as a network of nodes and relations. The “top levels” of

a frame are fixed, and represent things that are always true about the supposed situ-

ation. The lower levels have many terminals—“slots” that must be filled by specific

68 Chapter 4

instances or data. Each terminal can specify conditions its assignments must meet.

(The assignments themselves are usually smaller “sub-frames.”) Simple conditions

are specified by markers that might require a terminal assignment to be a person, an

object of sufficient value, or a pointer to a sub-frame of a certain type. More complex

conditions can specify relations among the things assigned to several terminals.

Collections of related frames are linked together into frame-systems. The effects

of important actions are mirrored by transformations between the frames of a sys-

tem. These are used to make certain kinds of calculations economical, to represent

changes of emphasis and attention, and to account for the effectiveness of “imag-

ery.” (Minsky 1974)

Frames, like semantic networks, are thus data structures involving a node-

and-link architecture. But whereas semantic networks are cast at the level

of semantic relations between lexical or conceptual units, frames represent

the space of possible objects, events, and actions stereotypically associated

with a particular type of context or situation.

Minsky (1974) explores a diverse set of examples of how the frame con-

cept can be applied, ranging from visual perception of an object and spatial

imagery to meaning structure of a discourse and understandings of social

interactions; late in the article, he assimilates frames to Kuhnian paradigms,

though without elaborating on the nature of the relationship (e.g., whether

he thinks that scientific understanding is frame based). He also cites the

work of several other researchers whose work, although employing other

labels, like “model” or “script,” is proceeding essentially along similar lines.

Relating all of these, not to mention other applications of frame-based

knowledge representation subsequent to Minsky’s article, would unduly

extend this chapter. But it is difficult to get the idea across adequately

without attending to at least a few examples that give some sense of what

a frame is, and how flexibly this way of representing knowledge can be

applied.

Vision and Perspective

Consider the common experience of becoming acquainted with an object

visually. At any one time, one sees the object from a single viewing angle,

from which only a portion of its surface is visible. One knows, however,

that there will be views from additional angles as well, and may anticipate

some of the visual changes that will occur as one moves, say, around the

object to the right (or, in the case of a small object, as one moves it around

in one’s hands). As one does so, new information becomes available: the

shape of the formerly unseen parts of the object may meet our expecta-

tions or surprise us, and the colors, textures, and patterns on the additional

69 Beyond Modularity and Central Cognition

surfaces come into view. At the same time, we do not forget the sides we saw

before, which have now passed out of view. Rather, as we move around,

we are building an ever-more-comprehensive understanding of the spatial

and visual properties of the object. To think about features that were visible

before, we may not need to go back and look again but may be able simply

to call them to mind. Moreover, when we encounter the object again or

encounter a similar object, we can imagine features of the unseen sides

(perhaps incorrectly, of course) without directly reacquainting ourselves

with them by moving ourselves or the object so that they are in view.

The implication of this seems to be that, in seeing an object, we are not

simply experiencing something like a photograph (or a binocular interpola-

tion of photographs) of the object from a given angle, or even seeing a suc-

cession of photographs taken from different vantages. We do indeed always

see an object from an angle; but we also have some kind of mental model of

the object that either consists in, or is generative of, understanding of what

it looks like from multiple perspectives. And this is not simply a feature of

how we see individual objects. We gain templates for the understanding of

new objects of familiar kinds: if you are handed a new pair of dice at the

casino, you do not need to examine them to see what is on the sides (unless

you have reasons for suspicion), because your mind already fills in default

information that each side will have one to six pips. On the other hand,

some aspects of what one will find are specified only at a generic level: pick-

ing up a book, you expect to see text, but the content of the text requires

empirical examination, as does the question of whether there will also be

pictures.

The question Minsky essentially poses is, What kind of information

structure could have these features? His answer is that it is a particular type

of frame structure. In his own example, an observer is looking at a cube

from multiple angles. Minsky develops the data structure diagrammatically,

using a system of nodes and links ( fig. 4.3 ).

To the left is a representation for the reader of how the cube looks from

an angle, with sides labeled with letters. To the right is a diagram intended

to represent the data structure used to encode such a view as a view of a

cube. The circular node at the top of the diagram represents the type of the

object, in this case a cube. This node has three arrows going down that are

labeled “region-of”—that is, the three nodes to which they connect are rep-

resented as being regions of (the surface of) the cube. These are labeled in

the diagram with arbitrary letter designations of faces of the cube, A, B and

E. The region-nodes have internal links that are labeled for the spatial rela-

tions between regions. Each region-node also has an additional outbound

Chapter 5

Cognitive Pluralism

5 Cognitive Pluralism

In chapter 4, we saw evidence that understanding is organized into units

that are domain specific, relatively self-contained, and possess distinctive

representational systems and inference patterns. This characterization has

much in common with the way cognitive “modules” are typically described,

but is intended to describe a much more general feature of cognition. The

organization of understanding into domain-centered units that can operate

semiautonomously on their own principles is found in nativistic and highly

encapsulated perceptual Fodorian modules, in nonperceptual cognitive sys-

tems (such as core knowledge systems) that are canalized early in develop-

ment and might be products of natural selection, in the organization of

acquired understanding in semantic networks and frames, and in scientific

models, our most exacting and regimented form of understanding. This

would seem to be a feature of the architecture of understanding that is

independent of whether a particular mode of understanding is “nativistic”

or learned, neutrally localized or distributed, species typical or dependent

on individual learning history or acculturation. Indeed, I will claim that it

is a basic design principle for the architecture of understanding.

We need a nomenclature both for this view of cognitive architecture

and for the domain-specific units of understanding that it posits. I will

refer to the view I am espousing here as cognitive pluralism and will use the

expression ‘mental model’ as a generic term for the domain-sized units of

understanding we have observed in modules, core knowledge systems, folk

theories, scientific theories, and Minskian frames. Settling on this terminol-

ogy for domain-sized units of understanding was in some measure a matter

of choice, as there were several obvious candidates, none of them perfect,

and each having preexisting usages: ‘model’, ‘schema’, ‘frame’, ‘framework’,

‘theory’. Short of inventing entirely new terminology, there was really no

way of finding a term that would not risk some degree of confusion with

other writers’ uses of familiar words. In the end, I settled on ‘model’ largely

82 Chapter 5

because it seemed to cause fewer problems and misunderstandings than the

others. Psychologists balked at ‘schema’ because of confusions with a well-

known “schema theory” in their discipline (Bartlett 1932). Minsky’s notion

of a frame is very close to what I mean by a mental model, but is likewise

associated with a particular theory, one whose associations with strong AI

(the assumption that the mind is literally a computer and that mental pro-

cesses are computational) I do not wish to endorse. (I do not actually think

that Minsky’s frame theory requires an endorsement of strong AI; however,

given that it originated in this context, in the end I decided not to use

his terminology to avoid potential misunderstandings.) The term ‘theory’ I

prefer to reserve for a specialized form of cognition found paradigmatically

in the sciences. And so I was left with ‘model’ by a process of elimination.

Of course, the term ‘model’ also has a number of existing uses, including an

importantly different use in cognitive science explored by Philip Johnson-

Laird (1983) and a philosophical use in logic, and I will attempt to situate

my notion of a model in relation to these and other existing uses in chapter

9, and to develop at greater length what I mean by a “mental model” in

chapters 6 and 7.

The claim that mental models are fundamental units of understanding

does not require us to deny that we also possess a more ecumenical form

of language-like thinking, in which concepts and beliefs related to differ-

ent domains can be brought together through syntactic construction and

formal inference. Indeed, this would be a strange thing to deny. Even if you

are skeptical about how much of our thinking takes the form of occurrent

sentence-like thoughts, there is no way around the fact that we think in

this fashion, at the least, when we think in a natural language such as Eng-

lish. Language-like thinking and model-based thinking are good for differ-

ent things and are complementary to each other. Models provide a basis for

semantic understanding and intuitive inference, but each model provides

insight only into its own domain. In my view, semantic understanding and

semantic inference are not really a part of language (or language-like think-

ing) at all. Our concepts and the things they allow us to represent and

reason about are primarily a product of the models we possess. Language

allows us to take these and combine them regardless of their models of

origin and to perform types of inference that are content neutral. Language

also allows us to make our thoughts explicit, and thereby to examine, test,

and refine them, both individually and in interpersonal dialectic. Much of

what is distinctive about human cognition would be impossible without

language or language-like thought. But language would be largely devoid

of content without models. (I develop these themes further in chap. 11.)

83 Cognitive Pluralism

5.1 What Is Cognitive Pluralism?

The basic thesis of cognitive pluralism is that the mind employs multiple

special-purpose models of parts, aspects, and features of the world, rather

than (1) a single, consistent, and integrated model of everything or (2) a

long inventory of more specific and independent individual beliefs. If a

“worldview” is construed as a comprehensive and consistent model of the

world, then we possess nothing that answers to the description of a world-

view. But our understanding is at the same time far more systematic than

simply a list of beliefs, even beliefs that happen to cohere into a consistent

set.

This is, first and foremost, a claim about cognitive architecture: that

domain-centered mental models are fundamental units of understanding,

distinct from, and irreducible to, beliefs or judgments. In fact, I argue that

models provide much of the basis for the semantic properties of concepts

and judgments, and for a psychologically realistic account of dispositional

beliefs. This, and other implications for semantics and epistemology, is the

focus of part 3. One of the main questions I address there concerns whether

the representational disunity that comes with a multitude of different men-

tal models presents principled problems for various concepts of the unifica-

tion of knowledge and understanding.

The type of “plurality” at the heart of cognitive pluralism is primar-

ily a representational plurality, and the type of “unity” that is denied is a

representational unity. Cognitive pluralism is the thesis that our ways of

understanding the world are all partial, idealized, and cast in individual

representational systems and perhaps cannot be reconstructed into a sin-

gle representational system that is at once comprehensive and consistent.

These different representational systems are attuned to particular phenom-

ena in the world and weakly optimized for pragmatic goals in interacting

with them. Some of these representational systems are weakly nativistic

and take species-typical forms. Others are acquired through trial and error,

social learning, and the special processes involved in learning technical

theories like those found in mathematics and the sciences. Which models

are acquired may vary widely between individuals and over the course of

a lifetime in a single individual. Through them, we “triangulate” a com-

mon reality without the construction of a comprehensive and consistent

worldview.

Cognitive pluralism need not be committed to denying other, nonrepre-

sentational types of cognitive unity, such as personal identity, the transcen-

dental unity of apperception, the unity of individual intentional states or

84 Chapter 5

perceptual gestalts, or the ability to combine insights originating in sepa-

rate models through logic and language. Nor need the cognitive pluralist

be hostile to the project of unification as a regulative ideal. Moreover, while

cognitive pluralism holds that mental models are a fundamental unit of

understanding distinct from, and arguably prior to, language-like think-

ing in concepts, judgments, and inferences, it does not deny that there is

such language-like thought. Indeed, the addition of capacities for language-

like thinking to a model-based architecture confers distinct and substantial

cognitive advances that make up a great deal of what is distinctive about

human minds.

5.2 Modules and Models

I propose that a pluralistic cognitive architecture can be found at a num-

ber of biological, evolutionary, and cognitive levels. It is found as a design

principle in many animal species in the form of developmentally canalized

modules. This modular architecture arguably becomes more weakly nativ-

istic (i.e., is increasingly open to developmental variables and learning)

in animals with more complex neural structures but is conserved even in

human beings. In humans and numerous other species, pluralistic architec-

ture takes a new turn in the ability to acquire knowledge of the world and

of how to interact with it in the form of domain-specific learned models.

Scientific models are a special case of learned models, whose special features

lie in their regimentation and minimization (though not elimination) of

features peculiar to the cognizer. In humans, this pluralistic architecture

is supplemented by special capacities for logical and linguistic thought,

which permit concepts and insights originating in modular and model-

based understanding to be combined in a domain-general representational

medium. However, this domain-general medium does not thereby become

a universal and domain-general super model. In humans, moreover, a great

number of learned models are socially shared or even socially distributed

and are transmitted through language and social learning.

I will treat the notions of “module” and “model” as overlapping cat-

egories, typified on different grounds. If a cognitive system is a module,

then it must have a strongly or weakly nativistic (i.e., canalized) etiology

and a species-typical relation between functionality and neural localiza-

tion (broadly understood to include distributed localization [M. Anderson

2014]). By contrast, I will speak of a “model” as a unit of understanding

that encodes systematic relational information about a domain and thereby

affords the possibility of representations of particular states of affairs within

86 Chapter 5

possible for each piece, captures, and the overall game state. A model of

space under gravitation must contain resources for representing objects

(bodies), their relevant properties (mass, position, momentum), and laws

governing their gravitational dynamics.

A model is apt to the extent that its representational system tracks the

salient properties of the phenomena that it is its function to model. Apt-

ness need not be an all-or-nothing matter. Classical gravitational models

are quite apt for modeling the influence of gravity in most of the cases

human beings encounter, but not for relativistic cases. Indeed, aptness may

have multiple components. It may involve both fit with a range of data and

suitability for things like computation. Classical models approach relativistic

models asymptotically with respect to aptness of fit in low-mass, low-veloc-

ity situations and exceed them with respect to computational simplicity.

Aptness is a pragmatic matter, and there are multiple dimensions of prag-

matic virtue.

5.4 Representation

The notion of representation has a checkered history in philosophy.

Indeed, in my first book (Horst 1996), I took computationalists’ theories

of the mind to task for their use of a notion of representation. Readers of

that book may thus find it surprising that I should use a notion of repre-

sentation here. My concern there, however, was that a particular familiar

notion of representation was being put to an illegitimate use. Computa-

tionalists rely on a notion of representation grounded in the paradigm of

symbols. Paradigm examples of symbols, like those in written or spoken

language, have both syntactic and semantic properties. Computationalists

posit that “meaning” may be attributed univocally to symbols in a natu-

ral language, mental states, and the hypothetical symbols of a language

of thought. They then suggest that the meanings of mental states can

be explained by the supposed meanings of symbols in the language of

thought, on the grounds that we already know (on the basis of symbols

in a public language) that symbols are the sorts of things that can have

meanings.

But the sense in which mental states are meaningful cannot be explained

by appeal to the type of meaning attributable to public-language symbols,

as the latter needs to be cashed out in terms of (1) the conventions of a

public language and/or (2) the intentions of their authors and/or (3) the

actual interpretations of hearers. To say that an utterance or inscription

“means-X” is just to say something about its conventional interpretation,

88 Chapter 5

be applied only to beings that think and to the representational tokens and

types that they employ as aids in thinking and communication.

But how broad a category “representation” turns out to be will then

depend on how broadly we construe “thinking” and “intentionality.”

Should we count the cognitive states of nonlinguistic animals as thinking,

and hence potentially as representational? And if so, which nonlinguistic

animals? Chimps? Cats? Lizards? Flatworms? As I have argued elsewhere,

I think there are significant issues here (Horst 1996). We conceive of “the

mental” through the lens of our own mental life, drawing on paradigm

examples that are conscious, available for scrutiny and reasoning, and

articulable in language. A kind of terminological choice is involved when

we decide either (a) to apply terms like ‘mental’ and ‘representational’ to

creatures without consciousness, reasoning, or language or (b) to restrict

those terms to cases closely resembling our own. I think we have good

reason to treat the primary uses of words like ‘mental’ and ‘intentional’ as

closely and perhaps constitutively linked with consciousness, reasoning,

and language. In the present enterprise, however, our concern is not with

consciousness, nor is it immediately with reasoning or language as special

features of human minds. Rather, it is with cognition. And we have good

reason both to use the word ‘cognition’ so that it covers processes that take

place in nonhuman animals, and to stress the continuities between human

and animal cognition.

I thus propose to use ‘representation’ in a stipulative and technical

way, in which representing-things-as-being-thus is something that is

situated in the internal economy of a cognizing system, paradigmatically

a living organism. It may be that the cognitive capacities of some species

are so simple that we cannot plausibly apply this notion to them. Like-

wise, it may be that this usage is naturally applied to certain nonbiological

homeostatic or autopoietic systems as well. But it is applied only analogously

to things like computer simulations of cognition that are not embedded

in homeostatic devices where the “representing” plays an adaptive

function in those devices maintaining their characteristic form of

being. I stress that this is a technical and stipulative usage of the word

‘representation’.

To represent things as being thus-and-so, an organism requires two

types of things. The first is a representational system; the second, a particular

representation, in the sense of a representational vehicle through which the

organism counts as representing things as being A rather than as being B.

The space of possible representational-vehicle types is generated by the rep-

resentational system. A representational system consists of elements that

90 Chapter 5

Models in perceptual modules: Modules used in perception, such as layers

of V4 involved in color perception, may also be viewed as representa-

tional systems. A system for color, for example, produces arrays of color

representations in a retinotopic map, tracking arrangements of chro-

matic properties within the visual field. Such a model involves a spatial

arrangement of units, with an internal geometry and topology, and each

unit is capable of a range of states modeled by the color solid. Areas later

in the perceptual stream used to represent spatial geometry provide a

model describable in terms of geometric rules that is used for represent-

ing objects in space.

A representational system defines a possibility space for possible token

representations. A particular gravitational model rigorously defines a way

of thinking or speaking about the locations, motions, and dynamic interac-

tions of bodies in space over time. This, in turn, provides the resources for

describing a particular set of bodies (e.g., the sun and the earth) in terms of

position, mass, and inertia, and for calculating the resultant gravitational

component of their dynamics. A restaurant script defines a set of possible

events and actions (and thoughts and utterances about them) that are on

script. This provides the resources for describing, understanding, and act-

ing appropriately in a variety of particular occasions of dining in which

different specific things happen within the constraints of the script. The

architecture of a layer of V4 defines a possible set of visual representations

of colored environments, and perhaps of chromatic experiences. Particular

chromatic experiences can then be located with respect to this space. A par-

ticular utterance or judgment about a gravitational situation picks out one

possibility from such a possibility space, and likewise a judgment, utter-

ance, or perception about events in a restaurant or a chromatic experience.

In some cases, a representational token will pick out a possibility at the

most fine-grained level: for example, at any one time, a person’s subjective

color array has fully determinate values. In other cases, a representational

token will narrow the possibility space while leaving some things indeter-

minate: for example, a description of the sun and the earth within a par-

ticular gravitational model need not affirm or deny the existence of other

bodies with mass, and the description of position and mass may be given to

a finite approximation, although the model theoretically allows for indefi-

nitely more exact descriptions.

Some neurally realized representational systems, such as those involved

in regulating autonomic processes and the proprioceptive systems, have

the function of tracking things going on within the organism. Others, like

91 Cognitive Pluralism

physical models, have the function of tracking things in the world, though

the organism may itself be represented as an object in the world. Still others

may have the function of tracking affordances—that is, organism-salient

features of the environment to which it is related. (The cognitive systems

of simpler organisms like flies seem mostly to be of this type, and likewise

human systems for things like tracking the position of head, eyes, and torso

used in orienting to things in the world and modulating perception.)

While each representational system has its internal ontology, these vary

in their degree of “objectivity.” By this I mean that there are varying degrees

to which the internal ontology is an artifact of things about the organ-

ism itself. The human color space, for example, does not neatly map onto

electromagnetic frequencies. It is heavily conditioned by the properties of

human cone and ganglion cells in the retina and is presumably a prod-

uct of selection that has been shaped over evolutionary history to track a

particular set of visual invariants that have been relevant to the adaptive

performance of the species in an ancestral environment or a succession

of such environments. At the opposite extreme, the ontology of objects

and properties in contemporary physics has been carefully developed to

exclude, so far as it is possible, artifacts of human perception and cognition,

and to track properties that objects have independently of how we perceive

or think about them. Such “objectification” is never entirely complete, as

we must always think about objects in some particular way, and the avail-

able ways are constrained by our cognitive architecture. (For example, our

tendency to think of the world in terms of discrete objects with properties

is probably due to a deep bias of human cognition, one that proves prob-

lematic when we turn to quantum phenomena. But even our representa-

tions of quantum phenomena reflect human concepts imported from other

domains by metaphorical transposition (e.g., “wave”), and a stock of math-

ematical concepts that the human mind is suited to dealing with. And,

indeed, many people seem to be unable to comprehend a system without

classical objects at all.)

Each representational system has its own formal shape. In some cases,

such as theories in physics, the formal shape is made explicit, and the

system is partly defined by mathematical equations. In other cases, it is

implicit and is made explicit only by formal modeling, such as is under-

taken in computational psychology and computational neuroscience.

Some representational systems can be modified or replaced, while others

cannot. We can progress from folk to classical to relativistic and quantum

physics or make adjustments to the gravitational constant within a relativ-

istic model. We can learn new rules of restaurant etiquette. But we probably

94 Chapter 5

woman who wished to become the legal mother, our erstwhile understand-

ing of maternity relations is inadequate to the problem. Likewise, if one

asks where an electron is within an orbital, the question can no longer be

answered without qualification, given contemporary physics.

Often (and perhaps always) the truth of a claim can be assessed only

once one has fixed what model is in play. Suppose that Smith witnesses a

traffic accident and testifies that the sedan was standing still and the bus

ran into it. In court, it will not count as a refutation of Smith’s testimony if

the opposing counsel points out that, according to our best physical mod-

els, there is no such thing as absolute rest, and hence the sedan could not

have been standing still. What “standing still” means depends on whether

we are adopting a commonsense model in which motion is judged relative

to the face of the earth or a model suited to physics and cosmology. It is the

former that the judge is likely to count as relevant to matters of traffic law,

and likely this was the type of model that Smith had in mind when giving

his testimony.

5.7 Types of Error

Corresponding to the two levels of alethetic assessment (aptness and truth),

there are two ways that representation may go awry. One of these involves

the tokening of a representation that is not the best match available within

the limits of the operative model for tracking whatever it is its function to

track. Asked to give the value of π, I say that it is 17. Or I know about both

cows and horses and misidentify a cow as a horse, perhaps because of bad

lighting. Or I say that the two lines in an illusory figure are of different

lengths when their lengths are equal. In such cases, the representation is

false.

But there is another sort of case, in which a given model does not pos-

sess adequate resources to produce an apt representation at all, and perhaps

I lack (and may not be capable of grasping) a model that can do so. For

example, I can produce only a finite approximation of the value of π, but a

fully accurate representation requires an infinite decimal sequence. Or my

subjective zoological ontology differentiates cows from horses but does not

extend to differentiating different breeds of cattle, so I cannot identify this

cow as a jersey or a Black Angus. Or I find myself unable to represent the

world except in terms of classical objects and thus find the problems and

models of quantum mechanics unfathomable.

Both of these types of errors can be forced errors—that is, errors that one

cannot avoid. If I do not possess a representational system that affords an

100 Chapter 6

computer models. These will be used to illustrate what I take to be impor-

tant features of models and modeling, and will serve as intuition pumps

for what it would mean to call something a mental model. I explore the

relationship between my notion of a mental model and other uses of the

word ‘model’ in chapter 8.

6.1 Scale Models (Target Domains, Idealization, and Aptness)

We have all interacted at one time or another with scale models, ranging

from children’s toys to models of molecules used in a chemistry class. Scale

models are typified, first and foremost, by their structural similarity to what

they are models of, which we may refer to as the target of the model. A

model of a 1964 Mustang has approximately the same shape and propor-

tions as a genuine 1964 Mustang, only much smaller. In some such models,

the similarity is limited to the surface contours and perhaps the colors.

Other models may reproduce other features in miniature—the doors, trunk,

and hood may open realistically, the steering wheel may spin and turn

the wheels, and so on. A very fine model may even be composed of parts

matching those of the real car: little pieces shaped like the engine, the cata-

lytic converter, the struts and beams, and so on. Some may be powered, so

that the model can move on its own power.

But, of course, many other features will not be modeled. Even a powered

model car will likely run on batteries (of a shape and relative size unlike

those of an automobile battery) and not on a tiny internal combustion

engine. The parts will generally not be made of the same materials, and

hence the balance and the ratio of size to weight will be different, and so

on. In models designed for different purposes, some of these features may

in fact be modeled as well. Engineers designing a car or an airplane may

build a scale model first and use it to test properties like wind drag and

stability. If a model is to be used for such purposes, it will need to model

more properties of the target than will a child’s toy. Design models are also

different from models of production-model cars or airplanes in that they

are typically built before their targets.

Scale models are also used in the sciences and in science classrooms.

There are, for example, kits for building models of molecules, using balls

of different sizes and colors for the atoms and tubes for the bonds. These

are used to roughly approximate the geometric configurations of mole-

cules, and as such, they allow both students and researchers to understand

structural properties of the molecules modeled and to explore what kinds

of molecular configurations are structurally possible. They serve as easily

Models 101

perceived and readily understood surrogates for the real thing, fulfilling

heuristic, explanatory, and predictive functions. Of course, some of the

relationships between elements of the model and their targets are purely

conventional. The balls that represent carbon atoms may be black, those

that represent hydrogen atoms red, and so on, but the atoms themselves

do not possess color at all. The size ratios between the balls may not match

those between atoms, the atoms themselves are not homogeneous spheres

with holes for connectors, and the bonds are not physical solids. The mod-

eling kit affords modeling only of one set of properties of the molecules it

is used to model—the physical, structural, and geometric properties, and

those only roughly.

Idealization

However realistic the model, it is made in such a way that it models only a

subset of the features of the target system. (If it is exactly like a ’64 Mustang,

it is the real thing, or a working prototype, or a reproduction, not a model.

If we build something isomorphic to methanol using atoms of carbon,

hydrogen, and oxygen, we are building an actual molecule of methanol,

not a model.) We may say that in this sense the models are idealized. They

have elements corresponding to some elements of the system modeled and

permit relations and transformations corresponding to some of those char-

acteristic of the target system while differing in other properties. We can use

such models as a kind of stand-in for the real thing for various purposes.

But just what set of purposes they can effectively be used for depends on

what features are modeled. And hence, to use the model effectively, one

must understand how it is idealized and what it reproduces faithfully. A

good scale model of a train may provide information about the relative

size of the engine and caboose but cannot be used to accurately predict the

real train’s structural integrity in a crash. A classroom model of an organic

molecule may provide information about its shape and what it can bond

with, but not about how the bonds of real molecules are formed or broken.

Aptness

We need a term for the suitability of a model to serve as a stand-in for the

real thing with respect to a given task. As noted in chapter 5, I will speak

of this as the aptness of a model. Aptness is always relative to a purpose. A

model train is apt for modeling features like appearance and dimensions,

but not for features like structural integrity. A classroom model of a mol-

ecule is apt for modeling features such as the rough geometry of molecules,

and for determining what molecular configurations are possible, but not for

102 Chapter 6

other features, like the nature or strength of the bonds. Indeed, the model

may itself permit configurations or transformations that are impossible in

the target system, or prohibit ones that are really possible. For example, it

may be possible to connect two balls with tubes representing a particular

type of bond when the molecules they are used to model cannot actually

be bonded in that way. This, too, is a limit on the aptness of the model,

a limitation on the purposes for which it may aptly be employed. Insofar

as the user understands these limitations, this amounts to a further way

the model is idealized. But insofar as the user is unaware of the potential

problems, the model may be capable of misrepresenting what is modeled.

Indeed, if the model is badly constructed, it may even be forced to misrep-

resent what is modeled.

Multiple Models and Incommensurability

There can, of course, be multiple scale models of the same type of object.

For example, model trains come in different gauge sizes defined by different

scales. The engineer’s model of a car or airplane will model different features

than will a toy model. Two kits for modeling molecules may be in different

scales, use different materials, employ different coloring conventions, and

use different types of connectors. The kinds of information available from

two models of the same type (say, two HO-gauge train models or two mod-

els of organic molecules using the same kit) will afford information about

comparisons (one engine is longer than another) or combinations (the

two molecules can or cannot be combined into a larger molecule). But the

use of models of different types is more complicated. One cannot directly

compare the length of two train engines using an HO-scale model of one

and an O-scale model of another, though if one knows the scale of each,

one can calculate and compare the sizes of the originals by using the mod-

els, measuring, and applying algebraic calculations. Model molecules built

from different kits may allow some types of comparisons (the geometry, the

number of carbon atoms) but not allow the models to be used for other pur-

poses: the two models’ failure to fit together into a larger molecular model

may be due to different scales or connectors that do not match and tell us

nothing about what chemical combinations are possible; or if the connec-

tors do fit together by chance, the ways they do so may not correspond to

actual physical possibilities, and the geometry of the resulting model will

be incorrect if the components are of different scales. A mismatch between

the types of models combined can thus result in artifacts, and two models

may even be incommensurable in the sense that they cannot actually be

combined.

106 Chapter 6

The third map (fig. 6.3), an updated version of one I recall seeing on

trains when I lived in Boston, does not preserve the spatial relationships

between stations. Train lines are represented (in the original) by distinctive

colors as before, and stops with labeled dots. But the lines do not preserve

the geometric properties of the routes—the north–south and east–west

directions or the comparative distances between stops. The map represents

the rail system topologically rather than geometrically. This is actually an

elegant way of presenting the information needed to quickly determine

how to get from one rail station to another. In navigating by rail, one in fact

needs to think topologically.

The fourth map (fig. 6.4), of a more limited portion of Boston, is topo-

graphic. It represents isotopic elevations with specially colored lines and

marked with elevations, types of landform with colors, and landmarks with

labels. Topographic maps are particularly useful for reconstructing three-

dimensional features of a landscape from a two-dimensional map. While

their use is something of an acquired skill, they are useful for orienting

oneself to one’s environment, and for calculating elevation-dependent

affordances, like the steepness of a route, optimal locations for radio and

microwave towers, and patterns of water runoff.

Each of these four maps represents certain features of the area it models

and abstracts away from others. Just what is modeled differs from map to

map, and the choice of what to include and what to leave out has con-

sequences for the purposes for which each map may aptly be employed.

Indeed, it is safe to assume that each map was carefully designed with a

particular set of practical purposes in mind, and the mapmakers sought to

optimize each for use in a particular set of tasks. The kinds of information

needed by the driver, the rail passenger, the cross-country hiker, and the city

planner are not the same. And a given type of information is made most

readily available by excluding from the map all unnecessary information.

Consider now a second set of maps (figs. 6.5 and 6.6). These are both

maps of the surface of the globe. Their most obvious difference is in how

they project the surface of a sphere onto a flat surface. The skin of a spheri-

cal surface cannot simply be flattened onto a plane without distortion. One

must either stretch it, or make cuts in it, or both. The first map, a Mercator

projection (fig. 6.5), is a result of something like stretching the surface. It

results in a rectangular map (or, more precisely, the surface of a curved por-

tion of a cylinder flattened onto a rectangular plane), in which each latitude

line is equally long, stretching from left to right. Since different latitude

lines are in fact of different lengths on the surface of a sphere, this results in

a geometric distortion. The map does not preserve the comparative areas of

Models 111

say, a geometric street map and a topological rail map. Indeed, a street map

without indications of railway or station locations and a topological rail

map without indications of street locations cannot be combined to plan a

journey without additional information, such as an independent knowl-

edge of where rail stations are located. Likewise, maps with different scales

or projection schemes require additional knowledge of those variables and

how to translate between them if one is to combine information from the

maps successfully. Failure to observe such strictures can result in errors.

6.3 Blueprints

Architectural blueprints have a great deal in common with maps. They are

two-dimensional representations of three-dimensional physical phenom-

ena and are usually drawn at least roughly to scale. Geometric relations in

the blueprint thus usually reflect similar relations in the building, at least

along the horizontal axes. Of course, blueprints are normally constructed

before the building is built, while maps are usually drawn to depict exist-

ing geographical features. But this need not be the case: one can construct

a blueprint of an existing building, and planners create maps of cities and

road systems that are not yet built.

Also like maps, architectural blueprints employ special conventional

symbols to note standard elements of their domain: doors, windows, elec-

trical wiring, lighting, plumbing, and the like (fig. 6.7). They may also indi-

cate the locations of appliances and furnishings. Unlike the lines used for

walls, these conventional symbols do not always mirror the geometry of

the features they represent. A symbol for an electrical outlet, for example,

is proportionally larger in comparison to the representation of the wall it is

housed in than is the actual outlet to the wall, and the arc used in the sym-

bol for a door indicates the direction in which it opens and not a curved

object. Likewise, the different shading patterns used to indicate materials

(wood, metal) are not spatially accurate representations of objects but con-

ventions that indicate the materials used.

Blueprints, like maps, employ labels. But they also employ a special sort

of label not always found in maps: labels indicating dimensions. Indeed,

while blueprints are often scale drawings that preserve geometric propor-

tions, they need not be drawn in this way. A hand sketch noting dimen-

sions and features contains the information needed by the architect and

the builder.

Much architectural design is now done using computer-aided design

(CAD) software (figs. 6.8 and 6.9). The “deep” representational system used

116 Chapter 6

to the processor chip by an interpreter or compiler. The programmer may

be quite ignorant of the machine language of the hardware she is program-

ming for.)

6.5 Computer Models

Computer programs can also be used as models of noncomputational pro-

cesses. The evening weather report, for example, might display weather

maps for the next day or the next week. These are generated by programs

that model meteorological phenomena and generate predictive simulations

of how they might evolve: for example, how a storm will track, or how

colliding fronts will produce high winds and precipitation. Researchers in

computational neuroscience, artificial intelligence, and cognitive psychol-

ogy use programs to test hypotheses about the mechanisms underlying

neural and cognitive phenomena. And economists use computers to model

the economic consequences of possibilities such as lowering the prime

lending rate or a change in the oil supply.

To build such a program, one must begin with a set of hypotheses about

what objects, properties, relations, and processes are relevant to the dynam-

ics of the real-world phenomenon to be modeled. One then creates com-

putational stand-ins for these variables, in the form of data structures and

algorithms that are designed to mirror the relevant properties of the content

domain. A model of billiard ball collisions, for example, would need to have

some representation of the dimensions of the table, as well as the locations,

dimensions, and momenta of the balls; and a sophisticated model might

represent further factors such as the coefficients of elasticity for the balls

and the sides of the table, and the coefficient of friction for the table surface.

It would also require algorithms for computing trajectories over some quan-

tized representation of time, for the effects of friction, and laws of collision.

Such a model would be idealized in a number of ways. Real pool tables have

surfaces that are not perfectly regular. A gust of wind might affect the real-

world kinematics of a shot, or someone might interfere with a ball in play.

The program may not have a way of modeling the effects of spin (“Eng-

lish”) or the chaotic effects of many-body gravitational variables (which, I

have heard it claimed, can produce macroscopic effects with a fairly small

number of collisions). It may also not be prepared to handle the differences

in high-impact collisions, where structural features of the balls become

important, as they may significantly deform under impact or indeed lose

structural integrity. These features are also relevant to the scientific models

themselves on which such a computer model is ultimately based.

Models 117

6.6 Features of Models

Models are cognitive tools that allow ready understanding of some set of

features of the objects or systems they are models of. Models can be ana-

lyzed into parts or aspects that correspond to various features of the target

system: objects, properties, relations, processes, and transformations. They

thus provide a means of representing these features and reasoning about

them. A model does not simply represent one fact about an object or sys-

tem but provides a framework for representing various sorts of facts about

them, and reasoning about these. A model is thus not itself simply a rep-

resentation of an object or system but a kind of system for representation of

things about them.

It is particularly important to note that the kind of understanding

afforded by models is tied to the ways they are systems. And in this way

models are unlike lists of propositions. If you have a list of propositions and

delete one of them, you may lose some ability to infer things that depend

on that proposition, but all the others are retained. But if you delete a road

or rail connection from a map or remove the labels, the ability to use the

map as a way of navigating from one point to another is more globally

impaired. If you lose information about what kind of projection it is, or

what the various sorts of symbols and lines stand for, the map cannot be

used for all the same purposes and may become utterly useless as a map. If

you delete a section of code from a program, it may cease to operate at all or

result in vastly different behavior. If you alter the meaning of one theoreti-

cal term in a scientific theory or alter one of the laws, you generally must

make a host of other alterations as well, or else the resulting theory will

cease to have the same fit with the phenomena it is a theory of.

Models are useful for understanding in part because they provide a

stand-in for the target object or system in which a certain set of its features

is made available for inspection, reasoning, simulation, and manipulation

in a fashion that is readily grasped. This almost invariably involves ideal-

izing away from other features of the real-world system being modeled

to reduce complexity and hence cognitive load. Of course, there will be

problems for which the things that have been idealized away from will

matter, and this will affect the aptness of the model for thinking and

reasoning about such cases. The way features or aspects of a real-world

system are modeled may also diverge from their real nature, and this can

affect the aptness of a model as well. Often, such distorting idealizations

make the system easier to grasp, and there can be a trade-off between

ease of understanding, reasoning, and calculation on the one hand and

122 Chapter 7

relational properties. You can “build” different structures in your imagina-

tion, conforming to the principles learned from the modeling kit.

Again, there is a good deal of individual difference in how well different

people can perform such an exercise. One person can do it successfully only

if there is a single carbon atom, another can do it with chains of two or

three, and so on. What the upper bounds might be is an empirical question.

There are probably savants who can imagine much larger molecular struc-

tures than you or I, and each of us would likely be able to expand our upper

bound through practice; but it might be that a DNA molecule would prove

too large and complex for anyone to imagine in detail. But this is an obser-

vation about performance limits rather than competence, similar to the fact

that there is some limit to the size of sentences you are able to parse, even

though you have the necessary grammatical competence required. You can

understand the sentences “Noah was the son of Lamech” and “Noah was

the son of the son of Methuselah,” and you understand the iterative nature

of the “son of …” construction, but at some point you lose track of the gen-

erations because you have exceeded some kind of limit on storage or pars-

ing ability. Similarly, you might be able to concretely imagine one or two

carbon atoms and what they are bonded with, but there is some upper limit

to how many you can imagine concretely, though you are perfectly capable

of imagining and thinking about the properties of any suitably small por-

tion of a very large molecule.

How should we describe what you are doing when you perform a task

such as imagining a chain of two carbon atoms with hydrogen atoms occu-

pying the remaining positions? It seems natural to speak of this as “build-

ing (or using) a mental model” of such a molecule. You substitute an oxygen

molecule or an OH group in one of the slots, and you have produced a men-

tal model of a different type of molecule. But something deeper is going

on as well. Your ability to imagine particular types of molecules and per-

form specific transformations on them—structural possibilities and trans-

formations that correspond to those afforded by the modeling kit (and,

assuming it has been well designed, to the ways molecules can actually be

configured)—suggests that you have internalized the structural principles

and possibilities that were engineered into the external model, and you

now have a general and flexible capacity that you previously lacked: to

model molecular configurations in your mind. With the external model, the

mechanical properties of the pieces—the number and locations of the slots

in the balls into which struts can be inserted, the lengths of the struts—

enforce the “rules” for their combination and generate a possibility space

of possible model molecules. If your purely mental modeling matches the

125 Mental Models

learn the ways the pieces fit together. And, having done so, she can inter-

nalize what she has learned so as to be able to think about the same sorts

of structures “off-line”—say, when the kit has been put away for the night

and her busy mind is resisting bedtime. In fact, the process of learning to

use the kit very likely involved the formation of a mental model of it as a

system of balls and struts that can fit together in various ways as well, even

though that model subsequently is little used or perhaps is used uncon-

sciously to guide our hands as we construct models we think of in terms of

the target system of molecules.

We learn about systematic regularities we find in a wide range of things

we experience, use these regularities to organize our subsequent interac-

tions with them, and think about them off-line in ways faithful to their

actual behavior when they are not present. The formation of mental mod-

els on the basis of perception and interaction is actually a ubiquitous form

of human learning. The sole difference in the internalization of an external

model is that the property of being a model of something else (say, mole-

cules)—perhaps something we have never directly perceived and interacted

with—is transferred from the external model to the mental model. Starting

with external models that are then internalized helps us to get a basic grasp

of the idea of a mental model by analogy with the more familiar examples

of external models; but not all mental models are formed in this way, and

the relationship probably really works in the opposite direction: the ability

to work with external models likely depends on the ability to form and use

mental models. Indeed, many advocates of mental models believe that the

capacity to form mental models originally arose as a way of internalizing

regularities encountered in bodily engagement with the world.

Mental models can also be formed in other ways. As I have already sug-

gested, some are formed through experience without an external model.

Some are developmentally canalized. Some are formed through processes

of verbal learning, social interaction, or explicit theory formation. In the

ensuing sections, I describe examples of each.

7.3 A Mental Model of My House

Try the following exercise. Think of a physical environment you are inti-

mately familiar with. For purposes of comparison, I will use the house I

grew up in—a place I have not been inside for perhaps thirty years, though

I lived there from ages two to seventeen. It has often struck me how vividly

I can imagine that house. And when I say “imagine,” I do not mean some-

thing like experiencing mental snapshots. What I have in mind is more like

126 Chapter 7

a kind of situated spatial imagination: I can vividly imagine myself being in

the house, in a given location, and have visual, proprioceptive, and some-

times tactile and olfactory imagery of the environment around me. I can,

in my imagination, turn and move, and things come into view. I can, as it

were, explore the house I once lived in. I don’t mean anything spooky here;

I am not talking about some kind of astral projection. I am talking about an

exploration of things that are somehow stored in memory, in a form that

needs to be explored and exploited, often in a fashion not unlike what I

would do if I were physically present, only by interacting not with the house

itself but with something in my own mind and brain. So let us try to make the

case for this in a way that, I hope, at least the readers with forms of imagin-

ing somewhat like mine can replicate.

Ask yourself: what color are (were) the living room curtains? For me,

both a verbal answer (“red”) and a visual image occur so quickly that I sus-

pect I have more than one way in which I have committed this information

to memory. But if I ask myself about their texture, or how they were hung,

or how many panels there were, I find that the process of “recollection” def-

initely requires a good deal more imagination, and very likely some deal of

reconstruction. For example, in thinking about the texture, I imagine myself

feeling the curtains as well as looking at them. Perhaps some of this is based

on stored episodic memories of times I touched them as a child. (Indeed, in

some sense it must be based on that.) But I can also make myself imagine

handling them in any fashion I can handle curtains—drawing them open

or shut, pulling them outward, lifting them off their hooks (ah—in think-

ing about this, I recall that they were on those hooks that get pulled by

drawcords!), and so on. To some extent, the parameters within which I can

imagine those curtains reflect the actual ways I did interact, or could have

interacted, with them.

Now, in one sense, this seems quite in line with the idea that cognition

is based in capacities for bodily engagement with the world. But it is also in

tension with the most extreme form of that view: that cognition takes place

only through actual bodily engagement with the world, without features of

the world being stored in the mind. Indeed, for me to be able to imagine

interactions that supply some of the same sorts of information as analogous

interactions through the body, there would seem to have to be something

stored in my mind that echoes the affordances I once found in the things

I am remembering.

I can also do other things in imagining my childhood home. Try this:

ask yourself how many electrical outlets there were in your home (or envi-

ronment of choice). What happens in your mind when you try to answer

127 Mental Models

this question? For me it involves a kind of visual or spatial imagining in

which I feel myself present at each moment in some particular position

and orientation within the familiar room and move around it, as though

focusing my gaze from place to place and noting the features I am looking

for. What I am, in effect, imagining is walking around the living room, the

dining room, the bedrooms, looking for outlets, and noting and counting

as I go. Phenomenologically, it has a great deal in common with what I

would do if I were really exploring a room I was present in. But there is, of

course, a crucial difference: I am not bodily present in that room while I am

doing it. I can do the same thing with any of a variety of other features of

the room—the number and configurations of windows or radiators, the size

of the doorways, the types of stones in the mantel, the flooring, and so on.

I should note that I fully expect the results of such an exercise to be quite

fallible. Some might be fallible in the ways one would expect specifically

for episodic memories. I might reconstruct the room as being larger than

it actually was because many of my memories might have been from the

perspective of the much smaller body I had as a child. But others might

be fallible in ways that we expect more of a reconstruction of details from

something more abstract. But a reconstruction from what? The answer that

seems to suggest itself here is something like an abstract, schematic model,

perhaps analogous to the information in the data used by an architectural

design program. This answer particularly suggests itself when the imagina-

tive task results in thoughts that are vague or blurry. My mind imposes

some kind of casing around the windows; but if I am to be truly honest, I

have little idea what the contours of that casing were. I remember a few of

the details of the masonry around the fireplace in detail, the rough width

of the grouting between stones, and some vague textures; but beyond that,

my memory of the hearth is something like a blank template waiting to

be filled in. I remember that several of the stairs to the second floor were

visible from the living room, and the rest disappeared behind the wall and

ceiling, but I could not tell you how many without reconstruction that goes

beyond remembering or exploring what is implicit in memory.

Yet all of this still suggests that the basis of my knowledge of my child-

hood home comes not in the form of episodic or propositional memories

alone but in the form of some kind of mental model (or models) of it, and

of such a sort that I can explore them—and perhaps explore them most

aptly—through an imaginary recapitulation of the operations I would have

performed to collect the same information if I were bodily present in the

actual room. And, as I assume that in so doing I am not interacting with

anything outside mind, brain, and body, it would seem to follow that there

128 Chapter 7

is something within mind, brain, and body that somehow stores some of

the relevant features and relations of the room itself. The accuracy and

detail with which it does so are no doubt limited. But it is hard to see how,

without this supposition, I can explain what happens when I think about

my childhood home.

I can, additionally, do other things in imagination. I can imagine things

that never happened taking place there. What would it have been like

if Martin Luther King had visited us? I can certainly picture him there,

imagine how many steps it would take to rise from the sofa to meet him

at the entrance, and so on. What would the room have looked like had

the walls been painted black? How would things have looked different if

a window had been walled off, or if the porch that adjoined the room had

been enclosed and the doorway to it been made into a doorless arch? What

would the room have looked like from the perspective of a camera in a cor-

ner on the ceiling, or from above, if the ceiling were transparent? Imagin-

ing these things is almost as easy as imagining things from perspectives that

I probably actually did occupy, which suggests that there are capacities at

work that are quite different from episodic memory.

Now try a slightly different exercise: imagine a blueprint of the first floor

of your house. For me, this takes a second or two to coalesce, but it hap-

pens quite readily. This is interesting, as what is present in a blueprint is a

view we seldom if ever actually have of an actual physical house. We do not

learn to understand blueprints by actually exploring houses bodily from

above. But it is a form of understanding that comes easily to many of us.

And, at least for some of us, it feels easy and natural to go from a blueprint

perspective to the perspective of being situated in a room and vice versa.

The information that is directly afforded in one is different from that of

the other, but the mind seems quite adept at translating from one to the

other. Give me a blueprint of a house, and I can fairly quickly form a rough

image of what the view would look like from a given position and angle.

The ability to transition back and forth is surely a form of know-how and

is closely connected with ways of being embedded bodily in the world. But

the “blueprint view” is not something we learn by flying above roofless

buildings. Rather, we have some kind of competence for moving back and

forth between an abstract schematic understanding of a physical layout

and a sort of situated geometrical thinking that allows perspective taking.

I think the best explanation for this is something like the following.

We encounter the world through situated, embodied, embedded cognition.

But this cognition must have some mental form—one or more representa-

tional systems. The use of these systems is not limited to cognition through

129 Mental Models

online perception but can take the form of various kinds of imagining as

well. These are certainly not limited to perspectives that one has actually

occupied in the world; for example, I can always ask, “What would that

look like if I moved over there?” (And, perhaps more surprisingly, I can

often quite routinely envision it.) Even more plainly, they are not limited to

perspectives I am presently in. But they are also not limited to perspectives

that I really could be in. Perhaps I can now be in a position to look down

(say, from a crane or a hot air balloon) on a house under construction in

ways most generations of my ancestors could not. But I cannot really be in

a position to “see” what the organelles of a cell look like from a position in

between them—though I can certainly imagine it and use that imagining

to explore things about it.

Let us now try to be a bit more careful and precise. I am suggesting that

I have mental models of things such as my childhood home. (Perhaps there

is a single integrated model of it in my mind, perhaps a constellation of

models of parts and aspects of it that I can move between and coordinate.)

But by this I do not mean that “having a mental model” means that there

“is something” in my mind that has the same geometric features as my

house. That, indeed, would strike me as a category error. What, then, do I

mean by “having a model” of my house in my mind?

One thing I mean is that there is something in my mind that allows me

to store and explore features of the house itself. And in these examples, I

am particularly concerned with forms of “exploring features” that bear a

good deal of phenomenological resemblance to what I might do to extract

information about the house by interacting with it if I were physically situ-

ated within it. Phenomenologically, I am imagining standing in a point in

the room and looking in a direction, attending to the way the curtains are

hung. This allows me to extract some of the same information about the

room (assuming the imagining is accurate) that I would be able to extract

were I actually situated in that fashion within the room. Phenomenologi-

cally, I imagine turning 45 degrees to the right, and other features of the

room become available to my mind’s eye. These correspond to some of

the features that would become available for perceptual inspection were I

really thus situated. Of course, the information extracted is accurate (and

hence only “information” in the normative sense) only to the extent that

my mental model of the room is accurate. It is surely finite in detail, and

likely inaccurate in some respects. Mental models are abstract and can be

erroneous. But for such things to take place at all there must be some kind

of correspondence between something present in my mind that I use in

imagination (a mental model) and the real-world system I might explore

130 Chapter 7

through bodily interaction. And the correspondence must be in some sense

systematic: when I imagine turning to the left and walking into the dining

room, the things I imagine encountering correspond to what I would actu-

ally see if I were walking through the house along a similar path. Something

in my mind must still be keeping track of the information I am not imag-

ining or attending to at the moment in order for it to be immediately and

often seamlessly available to me when I call for it. The simplest explanation

for this is that my mental model shares, at an abstract level, various fea-

tures of what it is a model of, the house. Having already discussed external

architectural models such as blueprints and CAD software, it is tempting

to suppose that this must include something analogous to blueprints and

three-dimensional structural models representing layout and features inde-

pendent of perspective.

Let us now take it a step farther. Suppose I am looking into some ques-

tion about my house by looking through the house itself—say, I want to

know how many outlets there are in the bedrooms. Consider how different

this task is if I am asking it with respect to my own house as compared with

being deposited in the doorway of an unknown building. In the case of my

own house, I know the layout, I know where I am situated with respect to

that layout, and I know which rooms are the bedrooms—and hence, implic-

itly, the efficient routes to get there. In the case of an unknown house, there

is a lot I have to explore and figure out to know how to carry out the task.

Having a mental model that supplies this needed background information

radically simplifies the task. Indeed, it seems to me that forming a mental

model that includes information such as what rooms are bedrooms is a nec-

essary part of the task of counting the number of outlets in the bedrooms of

a previously unfamiliar house.

Let us now turn to another form of imagination: creative imagination.

Suppose I am an architect, and my task is to build a house that answers to a

particular set of parameters. I do not do this by first slapping together walls

randomly and then exploring. Rather, I conceive the house imaginatively,

imagine the consequences of my design, amend the design in light of these,

draw up blueprints, and then turn it over to the builders. The architect may

understand a house quite well and imagine it quite concretely before the

foundation has been laid. Blueprints, cardboard models, and CAD models

may indeed assist in this process. But an architect with a detailed imagina-

tion may well be able to conceive and design a home without these aids.

The whole design process may take place with little or no bodily engage-

ment with the thing being designed. Nor is this something confined to

architecture: anything that is a product of design is imagined—and not just

132 Chapter 7

of “chess-shaped understanding”—that is, one in which various types of

mental representations and operations have the same abstract form as the

principles of the game.

Understanding chess seems to require a mental model of the game,

which in turn involves a number of kinds of abilities. At the least, these

would include a way of representing the board as a geometrically and topo-

logically describable space of possible piece positions, along with an under-

standing that at most one piece may occupy a square at any one time,

representational types for kinds of pieces and permissive rules for their

movement, definition of an initial state, and rules for turn taking, capture,

and ending states (checkmate, draw, resignation). Together, these gener-

ate a rich (yet also tightly constrained) possibility space, including possible

game evolutions and possible states of play. (Note that the possible legal

states of play are generated by game evolutions. Not all permutations of

pieces in spaces are legal—something that the expert recognizes but the

novice does not. A chess game cannot, for example, result in a configura-

tion in which a player’s pawns occupy the row closest to him.)

The different components of understanding chess are tightly, even con-

stituently, interwoven. My understanding of the piece type

KNIGHT cannot

be separated from my understanding of the rules of movement. Change

the rules for how a knight moves, and you have redefined the type

KNIGHT

as well, and vice versa. Change the size or configuration of the board, and

the move type

CASTLING must either be altered or lost entirely. You can, to be

sure, generate alternative games by starting with chess and changing things

about the board, the pieces, or the rules. But what you have then is a new

game, one that requires a distinct mental model, albeit one that might be

produced by starting with a model of chess and making alterations.

As I move beyond the baseline understanding of chess—being able to

play the game in accordance with the rules—I gradually begin to under-

stand things about tactics and strategy as well. These are normative rather

than permissive or constitutive in character, but they involve a subset of

sequences of moves permitted by the rules and ultimately guided by the

definition of the end state of having the opposing player in checkmate

(or, if that becomes impossible, forcing a draw). Both the baseline compe-

tence and the increasing mastery of competitive play may start out guided

by explicit rules and heuristics; but the more expert I become, the more

automatically they occur to me, and the more intuitive and less calculated

they seem.

While the typical way of learning chess probably still involves sitting

across a physical chessboard from another player, understanding chess also

133 Mental Models

involves a significant abstraction from this context. I may learn the game

with a certain set of pieces, but I can recognize it as the same game if the

pieces look much different. Just about anything can be used as a chess piece,

so long as the players can remember what tokens are being used for which

types of pieces. The typology of chess pieces as chess pieces is completely

independent from their physical characteristics. Indeed, the pieces and the

board need not even be physical particulars: there are many computer pro-

grams for playing chess, and good players can play mental chess, in which

there is neither a real board nor real pieces, the players each keeping track

of the moves and state of play in their minds.

7.5 Social Contexts

One of the better-known projects in AI knowledge representation was Roger

Schank’s script-based simulation of an understanding of dining in a res-

taurant (Schank and Abelson 1977). Like other frame-type models, this

involved special types of representations for types of objects (menus, uten-

sils, servingware, food and drink, checks, tables, chairs) and activities (arriv-

ing at the host or hostess station, seating the customer, taking the order,

bringing the order, bringing the check, paying the check, tipping), as well

as special social roles (customer, host or hostess, waiter or waitress, chef).

The “script” part of the program consisted in a stereotyped sequence (or

flowchart) of events in their typical order (see fig. 4.7 in chap. 4).

Schank’s program modeled a particular type of social context (albeit one

that allows further variations for different types of restaurants), but its gen-

eral features seem to be required for understanding any type of social con-

text. In our understanding of social contexts, people are characteristically

understood through roles, often roles particular to that context. Knowing

that someone is acting as a waiter, a judge, a coach, or a babysitter sets

up expectations about the things he or she is likely to do. Some of these

expectations may be mere associations or prejudices—I might expect wait-

ers to have stage ambitions as a result of living in an area where out-of-work

actors commonly take work waiting tables—but the more important type

are expectations tied to the role. The expectation that a waiter will bring

what I ordered is not a mere association or prejudice but part of my under-

standing of the role of being a waiter. These expectations are generally inde-

pendent of who is serving in that role: any waiter should bring the check at

the end of the meal. And our understanding of what that person will likely

do within the role will generally offer little guidance in predicting how he

might behave outside it. Indeed, within a particular context, it might be

134 Chapter 7

less confusing to have robots perform the roles “on script” than to have,

say, one’s waiter act like a judge or a babysitter instead.

The typology of objects within one context might likewise be orthogo-

nal to typologies from other contexts. The judge’s robe might be a piece

of clothing also sold as an academic gown or a preacher’s robe. The same

production model of fork might be used as a salad fork for one course and a

dessert fork for another, and my dessert fork might be made by Mikasa and

my dining partner’s by Lenox. In a pinch, I can use various chess pieces to

play checkers; and if I do so, their different shapes and the ways they could

legally be moved as chess pieces are irrelevant to their typing as checkers

pieces. The same can be said for activities performed. A quarterback and a

wide receiver might go through the same motions during a game that they

go through just tossing the ball around at a barbeque, but only in the game

do those motions count as a forward pass.

We understand many social contexts with special roles, local ontologies,

and activities. Each requires a separate mental model, though some models

may be related to, and variants on or special cases of, others. There are dif-

ferent types of dining contexts and different types of restaurants; and the

experienced diner knows, say, that at this restaurant there is a special person

called the sommelier who attends to the wine, and the check is not brought

until requested. Social contexts vary greatly from culture to culture, and a

great deal of cultural literacy involves understanding the particular social

contexts of that culture. Moreover, cultures can vary greatly in how strictly

ritualized their practices are, and in how much of their daily life is defined

by roles and contexts. In medieval Europe or Confucian China, it would

seem that a very great deal of how a person was expected to behave—and

probably much of how people really did behave—was defined by roles of

family relationship, guild, and social hierarchy.

Sometimes a person’s roles can conflict and present contrary expecta-

tions. In the play Antigone, the title character is caught between the con-

flicting expectations of her role as a pious sister (who should see that her

brothers’ bodies are properly buried) and as a citizen (who should obey the

Archon’s decree that they should be left where they fell in their rebellion

against the state), and this kind of situation forms the basis for much classi-

cal tragedy. To understand it as tragedy, one must understand the conflict-

ing roles, which can make a story from one culture difficult for someone

from another culture with different roles to understand. Sometimes such

conflicts are themselves the material for further rules: a judge should recuse

herself from a case in which she is an interested party, such as a trial involv-

ing a member of her family.

135 Mental Models

Like most models, social models provide a space for possible alternative

events and sequences of events. People don’t always order the same thing

at restaurants. Sometimes they may just go for dessert or drinks. Differ-

ent things happen at different trials, and with a different attorney, a given

case might have resulted in a different outcome. Even a tightly constrained

event like a play allows latitude. Lear must be played mad when he carries

in Cordelia’s body in act 5, scene 3 (though note that it is a dramatic sense

of “must,” not one suggesting physical or logical necessity), and the actors

must say the lines that Shakespeare composed; but one actor might play

Lear weeping, and another might play his madness as having taken him

into a completely dissociative state, thinking that Cordelia merely sleeps

and watching her happily for a time. Like other models, social models pro-

vide a framework for interpreting a particular type of situation, but there are

various ways things might go within that framework. Some of these may

be built into the model itself; others may be like improvisations on it. And,

of course, in any real-world situation there will be many other things going

on as well, some of which might ultimately impact on the aptness of the

model. I might, for example, discover after several minutes in a restaurant

that the seated people are not really diners but actors in a drama. Or I might

walk in on an impromptu rehearsal of King Lear and mistakenly think I am

really witnessing an old man mourning the death of his daughter.

Social models are unlike many other models, however, in the ways they

shape not only our interpretation of the world but also the social world

itself. The behavior of chemical bonds does not change when our models

of it change. But conduct in a courtroom changes when trial law changes

and those changes are appropriated by judges and attorneys; and people in

cultures that lack any understanding of the Japanese tea ceremony do not

engage in that ceremony, however much tea they might consume.

7.6 Moral Models

One case in which the ability of models to influence behavior is particularly

evident is in prescriptive models, such as moral models. The line between

ritualized behavior (or even custom) and ethics is blurry from a sociological

standpoint. Indeed, the Greek word ethoi means “customs,” and it is only in

the hands of philosophers that it came to mean what we mean by “ethics”

or “morals” today. Professional philosophers generally distinguish between

three broad approaches to ethical evaluation: consequentialist, deontologi-

cal, and virtue theoretic. Each of these provides a general framework for

evaluating persons or their actions. Consequentialism evaluates an action

136 Chapter 7

on the basis of its effects: the overall balance of good and evil, help and

harm, pleasure and pain, it results in, compared to the alternative actions

that were available. Deontology (from the Greek word for duty, deon) eval-

uates actions with respect to whether they are in accordance with one’s

duties. Virtue theory evaluates persons in terms of their virtues (beneficial

character traits) and actions in terms of whether they were done out of a

virtuous character trait. (And, of course, there are various cultural and theo-

retical models of what duties different classes of people have and of what

character traits count as virtuous.)

While philosophers are concerned primarily with these accounts as

frameworks for evaluation, they can also be used to guide conduct. A per-

son can try to foresee the consequences of various alternative actions and

evaluate their likely costs and benefits. She can take stock of what duties

she believes herself to be under and reason out what they require of her.

A person can practice the things needed to acquire a particular virtue like

patience and can inspect her motives and veto prospective action plans

that would be done out of vices like impatience.

The philosophical subdiscipline called metaethics contains a great deal

of literature that attempts to adjudicate which of these frameworks is a bet-

ter account of what is morally good. For our purposes, however, the more

important point is that each framework provides unique tools for evaluating

and shaping action and character. Each framework picks out different fac-

tors that are relevant for such evaluations—consequences, relation to duty,

and character—and each idealizes away from certain things that another

brings into focus. It seems almost certain to me that the ordinary person is

better off having multiple models of human goodness than having just one

of them. And I am inclined to suspect that even careful theoretical formula-

tions are not enough to build all the insights of all three types of model into

a single framework, unless perhaps it is a metaframework that uses each by

moving back and forth between them. There are some things for which

we have concepts—like goodness—that we need to approach from various

angles, through a number of distinct (and sometimes conflicting) models.

7.7 Mental Models and Scientific Understanding

I have tried to explore several familiar examples of everyday understanding

to make the basic idea that they are underwritten by mental models intui-

tively clear and plausible. I have chosen examples that readers would likely

be familiar with and could think about “from the inside.” Hopefully, the

time taken to walk through these examples will help readers form a basic

137 Mental Models

and nontheoretical idea of what a mental model is supposed to be, and to

assess the intuitive plausibility of the idea for themselves.

These examples, however, share two features that might lead to some

unnecessarily narrow assumptions about mental models. The first is that

they are all taken from the middle ground of understanding—types of cog-

nition that are acquired in mid- to late childhood or adulthood, as opposed

to those found in infants and young children, yet not among the more

rarefied forms of thinking that require very specialized theoretical learning,

like higher mathematics or scientific theories. The second, related to the

first, is that they are all cases in which the acquisition of a mental model is

achieved through some invisible learning process on the basis of bodily and

social engagement with the domain modeled, or with an external model of

it, or with existing social and linguistic ways of thinking and talking about

it. The types of models we have discussed may indeed be acquired in differ-

ent ways from one another—for example, some may be formed largely as

a result of individual bodily and perceptual engagement, and others from

supervised learning—but none of the examples was taken from the forms of

thinking found in very young children that seem to be present too early to

be a result of learning at all, and none from the higher reaches of abstract

theoretical understanding.

This might have suggested to the reader that mental modeling is some-

thing found in the broad swath of everyday commonsense understanding,

but absent from infant cognition and higher theory. If so, this would be a

misleading suggestion. Indeed, the reader may recall that a number of the

main examples of domain-centered understanding described in chapter 4

included several forms of thinking that arise in early development and also

scientific theories. In that context, the point of the examples was to show

that domain specificity was by no means unique to Fodorian modules, and

we would need to move beyond the bifurcation between “modular” and

“central” cognition to find an appropriate way to characterize understand-

ing. While it was this line of thinking that led up to an alternative model-

based view, we have not yet talked about the natural conclusion: that these

forms of understanding are based in mental models as well.

The idea that understanding comes in model-sized units clearly bears a

strong resemblance to the idea, which became influential in philosophy of

science beginning in the 1960s, that a scientific theory is an integral unit,

which provides its own interconnected ways of conceiving and reasoning

about a particular range of phenomena. Instead of thinking of a scientific

theory as a set of propositions built out of a theory-neutral language, phi-

losophers of this period began to think of the theoretical vocabulary of a

138 Chapter 7

theory as constitutively interdefined with its laws and other commitments.

Scientific theories have their own proprietary ways of representing and rea-

soning about phenomena, tightly interconnected internally, but only more

loosely connected to everything else. This is precisely what I have been

saying about mental models more generally. I do not claim credit for this as

a completely novel insight. A number of writers before me have suggested

that we view understanding generally, even the infant’s understanding

(Gopnik 1996), on the model of scientific theory. I simply prefer to put it

the other way around: scientific theories are a special case of how we rou-

tinely come to understand the world through mental models. Model-based

views have become increasingly popular in philosophy of science over the

past thirty years, and I will discuss the relation of some of these to my own

view in chapter 9. Here, however, I will try to develop the idea that scien-

tific understanding is based in mental models in the same sort of intuitive

fashion I have employed with other mental models.

In most of the types of models we have already explored, a model is

something that contains elements that are analogous to the objects, fea-

tures, relations, and processes found in their target systems. A modeling

system must have features that mirror key features of the target domain to

be apt. This is also the case with scientific theories and laws. These postulate

entities and their characteristic properties and relations, as well as invari-

ants expressed by laws and physical constants. Like other types of models,

theories and laws are a kind of surrogate that allow us to deal, in an ideal-

ized way, with features of the world in a fashion that affords both under-

standing and prediction. A theory of gravitation or a law like the inverse

square law is in this sense a model of the dynamics of gravitational influ-

ence. Theories and laws about collision are models of how objects behave

when they collide.

Like other models, scientific theories and laws are idealized in several

ways. First, they employ bracketing idealizations in what they exclude from

their scope. A gravitational model is concerned only with gravitational

interactions, not with collisions or electromagnetism. This affords insight

into one invariant in nature, but at the cost of resulting in a model that

is increasingly inadequate for kinematic predictions (i.e., predictions of

how objects will actually move) in cases where nongravitational forces

play larger roles. Second, they employ distorting idealizations. A particular

model of particle collisions, for example, may treat them as ideally elas-

tic. We know this assumption to be false, but such a model may still be

apt for low-energy collisions among some types of particles. Third, scien-

tific laws often employ constants for the values of forces in a fashion that

139 Mental Models

only approximates their real values. When the laws are considered in the

abstract, this can be avoided by simply using a letter for the constant. But

to put the law to work in a computation, some finite approximation of the

value must be used. This is often innocuous but will cause inaccuracies of

prediction in chaotic systems in particular.

As with other types of models, scientific theories can be thought of as

models of real-world processes at two levels. First, the theory itself—say, the

theory of special relativity—can be thought of as a model of very general

invariants found in nature, and of space-time as a whole. But it can also

be used as a framework for modeling more specific problems, such as how

several bodies will behave with respect to one another.

But there are also several ways in which scientific models differ from

some of the other types of models we have explored. Contrary to what

some previous generations of philosophers supposed, scientific under-

standing is not simply a result of inductive associations from naive percep-

tion. Scientific concepts and principles often differ significantly from those

of common sense and have to be constructed through difficult processes

of experiment design and theory building. While the resulting models are

ultimately the outcome of a long process of bootstrapping up from com-

monplace modes of conceiving and interacting with the world, the boot-

strapping process requires the development of some highly specialized and

regimented forms of thinking, including new forms of mathematics and

regimens for experiment and confirmation. Many scientific models thus

employ rarefied mathematical forms of representation that confer a form

of exactitude not found in most other models, and scientific reasoning and

experimentation are regimented in ways designed to minimize error far

beyond those employed in everyday life.

We also frequently speak of science being “objective.” This is a tricky

word, one that upon examination has many different meanings. But one

thing that it can mean, which really does seem to apply to scientific under-

standing, involves the minimization of individual and collective idiosyn-

cracies and biases. If we assume that cognition arose first and foremost as a

way of allowing organisms to interact more adaptively with their environ-

ments, it is natural to conclude that the baseline “default settings” for any

mind are optimized for things that are biologically salient to the organ-

ism: paradigmatically, things relevant to survival, nutrition, maturation,

and reproduction. From a biological standpoint, it is actually good that an

organism’s mind is attuned to things like what is dangerous, what is edible,

and, in the case of social organisms, who is aggressive or cooperative. But

features like these—what Gibson called affordances

1

—are not simply facts

140 Chapter 7

about the object but facts about its potential relation to the interests of

the organism, and such facts vary from individual to individual and from

species to species. What is food for the butterfly is not food for the lion,

and what is dangerous for me may not be dangerous for you. Such facts

are “subjective,” not in the sense that they depend on opinion or taste,

but in the sense that they are really relational facts that depend crucially

on who and what type of organism you are and what your interests are.

Animal minds (including those of human animals) have evolved so that

certain interest-relative properties of the world stand out, and this extends

even to how we conceptualize objects and the world itself. For example,

we “naturally” understand up and down to be privileged directions—a use-

ful and efficient way of framing spatial geometry for organisms that dwell

on the surface of a planet, but one that long proved an impediment to a

satisfactory cosmology. The privileged place of cohesive solids in our matu-

rationally normal ways of thinking about a world of objects is likewise a

useful framing, though one that makes contemporary physics counterintui-

tive. The color vision systems of various species no doubt attune them to

affordances that are important to their mode of life, but color is not a good

framework for understanding scientific optics.

One thing we mean in calling science “objective” is that, to achieve sci-

entific understanding, we often have to peel away layers of “subjectivity”

that involve understanding things in interest-relevant ways that are pecu-

liar to us as individuals or as a species. This, however, does not mean that

there is an end point of “complete objectivity.” The explanatory interests

of the sciences are still interests, and ones that occur to members of one

particular species, and even so only within particular historical and cultural

contexts. Our ways of conceiving things scientifically, even our mathemati-

cal understanding, are still drawn from the repertoire of ways that minds

like ours are capable of thinking, and are also conditioned by the ways we

have of investigating and acting on the world, even if these are greatly

extended and transformed through technology.

The “objectivity” of science also does not imply a single theoretical per-

spective. Scientists use a number of distinct models: relativistic and quan-

tum models, wave and particle models, evolutionary and molecular-genetic

models. Like different types of maps, scientific models can be incommen-

surable with one another, have incompatible representational systems and

background assumptions, and license contradictory predictions. This is one

of the principal phenomena described as “disunity of science,” and we will

examine in later chapters what cognitive pluralism might have to say about

the causes of such disunity and the prospects for unification.

141 Mental Models

7.8 Core and Folk Systems

At the other end of the spectrum of cognitive sophistication from scien-

tific models, we find early appearing, developmentally canalized forms of

thinking such as the core and folk systems described in chapter 4. These are

each centered on domains that are constituted by their respective internal

ontologies, which are represented and reasoned about in distinctive ways.

2

The core object system, for example, has an internal ontology with a single

generic class of things (“Objects”), properties (location, shape, motion),

relations (being in contact, colliding), and processes (causal launching,

moving in a continuous path) and is characterized by constitutive “rules”

that guide anticipations—for example, that Objects are cohesive and con-

tiguous, move in continuous paths, and go into motion only when acted

on. It seems natural to view at least the core object and agency systems

(and perhaps the core geometric system) as models of broad and generic

domains. They involve both bracketing and distorting idealizations and

employ representational systems with different representational types and

rules of inference.

There are several core systems and several folk systems. They latch onto

different systemic features of the physical, mental, social, and biological

world and provide systematic frameworks for representing facts involving

those features. Two systems can often be applied to the selfsame object:

Socrates can be constituted as an Object, an Agent, a thinker, an organism.

But in spite of this, different systems can constitute their common referent

in incompatible ways. A child’s toy or doll might at one time be constituted

as an Object and at another as an Agent, but nothing could really answer

perfectly to the rules of both the Object and Agency systems, as they have

incompatible rules about how motion is initiated.

Given the extended developmental sequence of the folk theories, it

seems overwhelmingly likely that their acquisition, like those of several

other types of mental models we have discussed, depends on extended

engagement with the physical, biological, and social world, albeit with the

important caveat that their species-typical features suggest that there may

be strong developmental biases. Core systems would seem to need to be

even more strongly developmentally canalized, as there is evidence that

they are present so early in infancy that it seems unlikely that the child

could have inferred principles like cohesion and local causal dynamics (for

Objects) or goal-directed motion (for Agents) from observation and the

severely limited capacities for controlled interaction available to human

infants.

145 Relations between Models

transformations thereof. But it is also in a broader sense itself a model of the

structural possibilities, affordances, transformations, and resulting views of

objects in geometric space. It might also be a model of physical space in

general, one that differs from other mathematically possible models that

employ distinct geometric or topological principles. It is both an abstract

model and a modeling system for providing representations and models of

more particular states of affairs and processes.

A model of human anatomy, by contrast, is generally useful not as a kind

of production system for various anatomical configurations but as a model

of the standard human anatomy. It may be that some such models have

parts that can be modified, removed, or rearranged to model nonstandard

configurations, but to the best of my knowledge, this is not its standard or

preferred use. It can, however, be used to model specific conditions and

procedures, such as the anatomical consequences of removing a bone or

organ or different approaches to surgical intervention.

Where we draw the boundaries around the term ‘model’ here is in

part a matter of deciding what terminology will provide the most useful

set of theoretical resources. I am inclined to use the term in fashion that

treats “models” as offering a space of representational possibilities of states

of affairs. But this usage is extremely broad, allowing models of varying

degrees of generality and abstraction. Model A may provide the representa-

tional space for B, in which case B may be said to be a representation within

the representational system afforded by A. But B may nevertheless itself be

a model if it defines a space of representations of its own. Even a model of a

particular object may do this: a scale model of a car or train may be capable

of being manipulated to represent various states—say, doors open or doors

closed, hooked to the engine or decoupled—and may allow other sorts of

representations as well, such as one of the ratio between the length and

width of the vehicle. Or a model of a 1961 Lincoln limo (the type of car

in which President Kennedy was riding when he was assassinated) might

be used in a representation of the assassination, or as a modeling system

for conspiracy theorists attempting to prove that the shots could not have

come from a single gun.

There can thus be a hierarchy of models, differing in degree of abstrac-

tion, much as concepts can come in hierarchies from the more generic to

the more specific. This sort of idea is also familiar in knowledge representa-

tion, and more generally in object-oriented programming in computer sci-

ence, as the notion of an inheritance class, where one kind of object is based

on another. A computer simulation of a mental model of a particular kind

of solid, for example, might be defined using the class features of a more

148 Chapter 8

The essence of metaphor is understanding and experiencing one kind of thing in terms

of another. It is not that arguments are a subspecies of war. Arguments and wars

are different kinds of things—verbal discourse and armed conflict—and the actions

performed are different kinds of actions. But

ARGUMENT is partially structured, un-

derstood, performed, and talked about in terms of

WAR. The concept is metaphori-

cally structured, the activity is metaphorically structured, and, consequently, the

language is metaphorically structured. (Lakoff and Johnson 2003, 5)

In metaphor, the language and the manner of understanding the source

domain (in this case, war) are taken over as ways of understanding the tar-

get domain (in this case, argument).

What Lakoff and Johnson say about metaphor has a great deal in com-

mon with what I have said about mental models: each metaphor works

systematically and obscures (idealizes away from) some things so as to high-

light others.

The very systematicity that allows us to comprehend one aspect of a concept in

terms of another (e.g., comprehending an aspect of arguing in terms of battle) will

necessarily hide other aspects of the concept. In allowing us to focus on one aspect

of a concept (e.g., the battling aspects of arguing), a metaphorical concept can keep

us from focusing on other aspects of the concept that are inconsistent with that

metaphor. For example, in the midst of a heated argument, when we are intent on

attacking our opponent’s position and defending our own, we may lose sight of the

cooperative aspects of arguing. Someone who is arguing with you can be viewed as

giving you his time, a valuable commodity, in an effort at mutual understanding.

But when we are preoccupied with the battle aspects, we often lose sight of the co-

operative aspects. (Lakoff and Johnson 2003, 10)

Moreover, we can use multiple metaphors to highlight different features of

the target domain. Lakoff and Johnson note several different metaphorical

frameworks for understanding ideas (as people, plants, products, commodi-

ties, resources, money, cutting instruments, fashions) and love (as a physi-

cal force, a [medical] patient, magic, war).

Lakoff and Johnson’s book (which is both eminently readable and well

worth reading) contains far more interesting observation and theory than

can be explored here. From the perspective of model-based cognitive plural-

ism, the important lesson seems to be this: sometimes we can form a model

of a domain by taking a model of some entirely different domain and trans-

posing its structure to be used as the basis for a new model. The system

of already-understood types, connections, and inference patterns from

the source model provides a kind of ready-made scaffolding for a model of

another domain. This is an exceptionally powerful learning technique, as it

provides a way of acquiring the basis of a model of a new domain without

149 Relations between Models

having to construct it from scratch through laborious exploration of the

target domain.

8.4 Triangulation

The thesis that we understand the world through using many domain-

specific models that have proprietary rules, representational systems, and

internal ontologies may explain important things about understanding, but

it also presents problems. We may use many individual models to under-

stand different things about the world, but we do not only use models one

at a time and in isolation from one another. In bodily interaction with the

world, we employ a number of distinct perceptual, motor, and cognitive

systems, not merely simultaneously but cooperatively and in an integrated

manner. Even in off-line thinking, such as imagination, reasoning, and

theorizing, we can think about an object, phenomenon, event, or general

type of problem from a variety of angles, framed in terms of different mod-

els. And this raises questions about (1) how we are able to coordinate them

adaptively at all; (2) how we are able to recognize one and the same object,

phenomenon, and so on, though we are thinking about it through multiple

models; and (3) how we are able to combine insights from different models

through reasoning, so that the resulting understanding we have as a whole

is more than simply the sum of what we would get from several distinct

model-based processes going on simultaneously.

If our only way of thinking about the world were through individual

models, it would seem that at least the second and third questions might

prove impossible, and even the first would require some explanation. If

we assume that models (or at least those that constitute objects at all) each

have their own implicit internal ontologies, positing special types of things,

properties, relations, processes, and transformations, there is a danger that

they would end up being separate gears spinning on their own axes without

engaging one another. Suppose I am playing chess. I recognize a piece as

a knight within the chess model. I also recognize it as a particular kind of

physical object—a small wooden piece I can pick up, a large concrete statue

that would need to be moved by heavy equipment, or perhaps a human

being in costume if it is a game of human chess. But if model-based cog-

nition were the whole story, I would not recognize a single thing as being

both a knight and a concrete statue. Rather, I would have two separate

representations: one of a chess knight, and another of a concrete statue.

Either I would see them as two different things with no way to connect them,

or perhaps I would not even be able to count across models at all, simply

154 Chapter 8

Perceptual Binding

The perceptual binding problem is probably the case that has received the

most scientific attention. A proposal like Crick and Koch’s phase binding

hypothesis provides an explanation of how information represented in

distinct areas of the brain—say, the visual areas for color and form—gets

coupled. Integration of information from different sensory modalities may

additionally use association areas of the cortex that take inputs from mul-

tiple sources. However, these do not seem to be a sensus communis for pan-

modal representations. Rather, the integration of information from various

modalities into a single percept seems to be a matter of how different areas

are coordinated and act in concert rather than being accomplished by an addi-

tional area. There is no more an anatomical sensus communis than a string

quartet ensemble is an instrument over and above the violins, viola, and

cello. Moreover, the explanation invokes nothing like language-like repre-

sentations, but neural systems in a kind of dynamic resonance pattern. And

whereas a language-like representation supports the combined representa-

tion of two types of information in a single medium, phase binding treats

the situation as involving the coordination of separate representations in

different representational systems and representational media.

Sensorimotor Engagement

Perception is not normally a passive process like a camera recording an

image. It usually takes place as part of engagement with the world, which is

often purposeful and involves motor processes through which an organism

acts on the world, even in the process of exploring it perceptually. Senso-

rimotor engagement involves more than merely binding together informa-

tion from separate perceptual streams. It involves coordinating perceptual,

motor, and orienting systems in a fashion that is propelled by the drives

and interests of the organism and constrained by its physiological and cog-

nitive abilities. Such processes, even when they are primarily “perceptual,”

also evolve as dynamic processes over time, adjusting to explore for new

information in light of present states.

Advocates of “embodied and embedded cognition,” “situated cogni-

tion,” and the “enactive approach” have provided general frameworks for

characterizing such processes, using resources such as dynamic systems

theory. Silberstein and Chemero, for example, write:

We propose that extended phenomenology-cognition be understood as a variety

of niche construction, one in which the constructed niche is an animal’s cognitive

and phenomenological niche. In biological niche construction, the activity of some

population of organisms alters, sometimes dramatically, its own ecological niche as

156 Chapter 8

the animal’s abilities. At the same time, the set of affordances available to the animal

profoundly influence the development of the animal’s sensorimotor abilities. So we

have a three-part, coupled, nonlinear dynamical system in which the nervous sys-

tem partly determines and is partly determined by the sensorimotor abilities which

partly determine, and are partly determined by, the affordances available to the ani-

mal. (Silberstein and Chemero 2011, 7–9; figure number amended to correspond to

the present text)

Depending on the state of interaction between organism and environment,

control of the overall dynamics might be located in various places: in some

neural subsystem, in processes adjusting the coupling, in features of the

environment, or in a more distributed system including both an organism

and objects and processes external to it. While such an explanation does

not focus primarily on operation of subsystems like mental models, this is

primarily because it is intended to be a general framework that is applicable

to many types of relationships between organism and environment. The

enactive approach need not deny that neural systems can be functionally

decomposed into subsystems like mental models, or that these can play

a predominant role in the dynamics of some kinds of tasks or be what is

tightly coupled to more specific features of the environment (the system

modeled) in the performance of those tasks. Coupling mechanisms specific

to model-based interaction might be eminently relevant to the mastery

and aptness of models, and the dynamics of neural change in learning an

important tool for an account of model acquisition. Moreover, the capac-

ity for off-line cognition may quite plausibly involve replacing an online

coupling to external objects with a coupling to mental models that act as

their surrogates. (In this respect, I think that a model-based approach to

cognition provides a natural extension of dynamic coupling accounts of

online cognition.)

The Selfsame Object

None of this so far really addresses the key issue Husserl identified as Hume’s

problem: how we are able to constitute something, perceived and conceived

in various ways and over time, as the selfsame object, which endures through

changes over time and is understood as the same thing even as our percep-

tions of and beliefs about it change. This phenomenon—which we may

call object-oriented cognition—is really a special type of triangulation, distinct

from the practical coordination of different models used in tandem.

I think there may be at least two significantly different sorts of cases here,

which seem to require different sorts of accounts. The first involves object

tracking within a perceptual episode. The brain has comparatively low-level

157 Relations between Models

mechanisms, particularly in the visual system, that seem to be involved

in tracking an object over time. These seem to be capable of dealing with

things like temporarily occluded objects, and perhaps even of constituting

objects that are not yet directly perceived on the basis of cues such as scent

or the vibrations in a spider’s web. Such processes do not seem to require

resources for the postulation of proposition-like hypotheses, though some-

times we find it easiest to describe them in terms of beliefs. They are found

quite broadly in the animal kingdom. But they do not account for the abili-

ties to reidentify something as the selfsame object in distinct perceptual

episodes, or to engage in object-oriented triangulation in types of thinking

other than perception.

On the other hand, it is not clear how many animal species are able to

reidentify something as the selfsame individual on different occasions, or

to think about it as an individual in off-line cognition. An ant can identify

something as another ant, and things such as whether it is of the same

colony, perhaps its “caste,” and states such as carrying home food. But an

ant probably cannot tell one individual worker or drone of its own colony

from another. More likely, each encounter with another nest mate is for it

simply a kind tokening—“worker ant,” “worker ant again.” Mammals and

birds, on the other hand, are able to reidentify specific individuals, and

this ability seems necessary for identification of mates and offspring, and

to undergird social cognition for things like dominance hierarchies, at least

among the more social species. It is unclear just where in the phylogenetic

tree such abilities appear. Perhaps an alligator can see another alligator and

remember it as the same alligator it saw a week ago. Or perhaps it just

thinks, in effect, “male alligator bigger than me” on each occasion, not

treating the two kind tokenings as presenting the selfsame individual.

At least some species seem able to reidentify not only particular con-

specifics but particular inanimate objects as well. A dog seems able to rec-

ognize a particular toy, for example. And of course many animals are able

to identify particular individuals of other species as well—a domestic dog

can recognize its favorite human as well as it can recognize other dogs,

and evidence suggests that even wild birds can distinguish between dif-

ferent humans they have encountered. I suspect that the ability to reiden-

tify individuals may initially have been an adaptation for social cognition

involving conspecifics within social species and is probably one of the key

prerequisites for being a social animal. It may be that once this ability is in

place, extending it to other things—individuals in other species, inanimate

objects—comes for free or at least requires only the perceptual abilities to

discriminate whatever cues are needed to distinguish between individuals.

158 Chapter 8

(You and I have the requisite cognitive resources to think of separate indi-

viduals, but our perceptual abilities are not well suited to distinguishing

between particular ants of the same species and caste.) Alternatively, it may

be that these require further cognitive abilities that build on foundations

originating in social condition.

The ability to reidentify specific individuals seems to require a particular

kind of cognitive resource: concepts that are namelike rather than generic.

Kind concepts (

DOG) and property concepts (MALE, SPOTTED) are by nature

things that can be applied to multiple individuals. Namelike concepts, by

contrast, have the function of picking out and tracking just one thing. This

strikes me as likely to be a special kind of concept, one that is not required

for having ways of tracking kinds and variable properties, and one that has

probably appeared comparatively recently in evolutionary history, though

perhaps independently in several widely separated taxa.

Information Passing

While thinking within a model may often take place more or less autono-

mously, we are also often able to pass information between models. In this

way, at least some model-based reasoning is not entirely encapsulated in

the way that Fodor described modules.

2

My mental model of a social situ-

ation may supply general anticipations about what to expect, but I may

need different types of information, not supplied by that model, to achieve

a more fine-grained understanding of the situation and to make better

predictions. Some aspects of how a waiter will behave—at least while “on

script”—may be supplied by my model of restaurant etiquette. But oth-

ers might require me to know something about his individual psychology:

whether he is passive-aggressive, what his cultural background is, whether

he is an experienced waiter or in training, what other roles he plays in the

restaurant or outside it, what sort of mood he is in. It requires different sorts

of models to understand these things, but if I do grasp them, they can affect

how I run the restaurant model in this particular case.

The analogy that recommends itself to me here is that of parameter pass-

ing in computer programming. Contemporary programming is generally

highly modularized, with distinct subprograms used for different opera-

tions. The different code modules, however, are not simply different opera-

tions that run in parallel; often one calls on another and passes and receives

values of variables called parameters. One module M1 might, for example,

need the area of a triangle but only have information about the length of

the sides. There is a formula for computing area on the basis of the lengths

of the sides, called Heron’s formula.

161 Relations between Models

case, if we use only the social model of professional responsibility, it might

lead to a prediction that the woman will stay at the office until the job is

complete. If we use only the model of maternal responsibility, it might

lead to a prediction that she will leave to pick up her daughter sometime

between the originally expected hour and the time day care closes. In both

cases, each model brackets the factors relevant to the other, and so neither

model alone can be used as the basis for a realistic prediction of real-world

behavior. Of course, in some ways the cases are different. In mechanics, we

have the technique of summation of forces through vector algebra, whereas

this approach is not available in the case of social duties, in which there

might be other meta-techniques like assessing how one duty might trump

another, or there might be methods of finding a satisficing solution. But in

both kinds of cases, any kind of method that is used must go beyond the

resources of a single model, as each model brackets factors relevant to the

other, and both kinds of factors are relevant to the real-world situation. And

there are probably both physical and social cases where we do not have an

algorithmic method that ensures a way of integrating the factors.

Let us also consider a more serious sort of case, in which two models

applicable to the same situation are either incommensurable or inconsis-

tent. Wave and particle models of the same phenomenon—the propaga-

tion of light—lead to contrary predictions of behavior because they use

different representational systems, inference rules, and processes for simu-

lation. General relativity and quantum mechanics are inconsistent with

each other, as are classical and relativistic gravitation. We might view these

cases as analogous to the relationship between Euclidean and non-Euclid-

ean geometries: the models in question have incompatible representational

systems and rules. Each may be apt for a wide range of cases individually,

but their formal structure ensures that when they are combined, problems

will occur.

This may be puzzling from the standpoints of epistemology and truth

theory—I will examine whether it should be deeply and abidingly puzzling

in the final part of the book—but not from the perspective of psychology.

Each model must use some particular representational system. And what

representational system is employed will be constrained by (a) the demands

of the real-world invariants to be modeled; (b) the general constraints of

cognitive architecture (the specific set of types of representational systems

that are available to a mind like our own); and (c) pragmatic demands such

as utility for providing understanding, calculation, and prediction. As these

constraints operate to shape models individually, we have no assurance that

two models will turn out to be compatible with each other. Models that

164 Chapter 9

9.1 Models in Psychology

The Scottish psychologist Kenneth Craik appears to deserve the credit for

coining the expression “mental model” in the cognitive sciences. (And,

even if someone else used it earlier, advocates of model-based approaches

trace their usage of the expression back to Craik.) In a passage oft quoted in

the mental-modeling literature, Craik wrote:

If the organism carries a “small-scale model” of external reality and of its own pos-

sible actions within its head, it is able to try out various alternatives, conclude which

is the best of them, react to future situations before they arise, utilize the knowledge

of past events in dealing with the present and the future, and in every way react in

a much fuller, safer, and more competent manner to the emergencies which face it.

(Craik 1943, 61)

Craik published this in 1943, considerably before investigations in arti-

ficial intelligence. Indeed, at the time, computing machines were largely

shrouded in the secrecy of the wartime code-breaking project at Bletch-

ley Park, though Craik was familiar with and wrote about control systems

in two posthumously published papers (Craik 1947, 1948) and sought a

physiological and “mechanistic” explanation for mental processes. He was

also writing long before evolutionary and adaptive approaches to the mind

became popular (though, of course, this line of thinking had been pio-

neered by William James [1890]), but Craik framed the problem of thinking

in terms of an organism coping with problems in its environment. Organ-

isms are able to do so intelligently, according to Craik, through “explana-

tions” that allow predictions of what will happen in the world and as a

consequence of various things the organism might do to act on the world.

The abilities to explain and predict require external processes to be “trans-

lated” into words, numbers, or other symbols, which are then used to “rea-

son,” and then “retranslated” into external processes, like building a bridge.

While Craik did to some extent explore the idea that such internal pro-

cesses operate on linguistic or verbal representations, his central explana-

tory strategy was to liken it to the construction and use of external models.

Indeed, as I have done in this book, he paved the way to developing the

idea of a mental model by first discussing external models.

By a model we thus mean any physical or chemical system which has a similar rela-

tion-structure to that of the process it imitates. By “relation-structure” I do not mean

some obscure non-physical entity which attends to the model, but the fact that it is

a physical working model which works in the same way as the process it parallels, in

the aspects under consideration at any moment. (Craik 1943, 51)

166 Chapter 9

we think about electricity through “generative analogies,” importing an

understanding of a system of relations in one domain (such as water flow-

ing through pipes) to another (electricity) through a process of “structure-

mapping” (100).

The analogical models used in science can be characterized as structure-mappings

between complex systems. Such an analogy conveys that like relational systems hold

within two different domains. The predicates of the base domain (the known do-

main)—particularly the relations that hold among the objects—can be applied in the

target domain (the domain of inquiry). Thus, a structure-mapping analogy asserts

that identical operations and relationships hold among nonidentical things. The

relational structure is preserved, but not the objects. (102)

The system of relationships, and the structural isomorphism between them,

can be represented diagrammatically (fig. 9.1).

If we may interpolate the language of “mental models” used in some

subsequent publications (e.g., Forbus and Gentner 1997), the models are

what are schematized in the two diagrams and consist of an understanding

of the relations within a system, which are envisioned as residing in long-

term memory and used in reasoning and simulation (Forbus and Gentner

1997). An “analogical model” would thus seem to be an understanding of

a system of relations stored in long-term memory that is formed by the ana-

logical transposition of the structure of another model to a new domain.

There are clear similarities between this view of mental models and the

one that I have described. To possess a model is to posses a lasting abil-

ity to think about a domain in systematic ways. The model is an integral

unit, defined by the systematic interrelations of its elements, and provides

ways of framing, reasoning about, simulating, predicting, and operating on

phenomena in the target domain. The postulation of multiple models of dif-

ferent content domains not only is implicit in the separate descriptions of

different models but is made explicit in Collins and Gentner (1983) and in

Forbus and Gentner’s discussion of qualitative models in physics:

The goal of most qualitative physics research is to build an idealized physical rea-

soner, a system that can reason with sophistication about the physical world in the

way that the best human scientists and engineers do, without their frailties. This

goal leads to a preference for systems that maximize generality and generativity.

That is, the laws of qualitative physics are expressed in domain-independent terms,

and knowledge of domains is expressed in situation-independent forms. It seems

likely that people’s mental models include laws and principles that are at least some-

what domain independent, as well as domain knowledge that is situation-indepen-

dent. But there is ample evidence suggesting that much of what people know about

the physical world and how they reason about it is more concrete than that. …

170 Chapter 9

Nancy Nersessian writes in a similar vein that “in standard philosophical

accounts reasoning is employing deductive or inductive algorithms to sets

of propositions. The understanding of deductive reasoning provided by

classical logic stands as the model” (Nersessian 1999, 7). She notes a simi-

lar assumption in cognitive science and goes on to claim by contrast that

subsequent studies “sparked numerous investigations in different domains

that have led many cognitive scientists to conclude that much of human

reasoning is by means of ‘mental modeling’ rather than through a process

of applying a mental logic to propositional representations” (9–10).

In his introduction to the collection Cognitive Models of Science, Giere

contextualizes several model-based accounts in this way in the course of his

synopsis of an entry by Nersessian in the same volume:

Most historically minded critics of logical empiricism took over the assumption that

scientific theories are primarily linguistic entities. The main exception is Kuhn, who

gave priority to concrete exemplars over linguistically formulated generalizations.

Nersessian adopts a theory of “mental models” as elaborated, for example, by John-

son-Laird (1983). On this approach, language, in the form of propositions, may be

used not to describe the world directly but to construct a “mental model,” which is

a “structural analog” of a real-world or imagined situation. Once constructed, the

mental model may yield “images,” which are mental models viewed from a particu-

lar perspective. This interplay of propositions, models, and images provides a richer

account of the representational resources of scientists than that employed by either

logical empiricists or most of their critics. It may be thought of as an extension of the

model-theoretic approach to the nature of scientific theories as elaborated, for ex-

ample, by Suppe (1989), van Fraassen (1980, 1989), and myself (Giere 1988). In any

case, the cognitive theory of mental models provides the main resource for Nerses-

sian’s account of the dynamics of conceptual change in science. Some such account

of representation seems sure to become standard within a cognitive approach to the

philosophy of science. (Giere 1992, xvii–xviii)

Giere’s and Nersessian’s approaches, which are important articulations of

cognitivist approaches to science, are particularly sympathetic to my view

that mental models form the basis of scientific understanding. Other pro-

ponents of model-based approaches use the term ‘model’ in ways whose

cognitivist commitments are perhaps less obvious. Some deal with the use

of concrete external models, such as Watson and Crick’s tin and cardboard

model of the DNA molecule. Others use the term ‘model’ for analogical

modes of understanding, including the use of diagrams, images, or simu-

lations (all standardly referred to as “analog” representations), or models

based in actual analogies, such as viewing particle collisions on the model of

billiard balls. The use of such analogies is often viewed as playing primarily

171 Other Model-Based Approaches

a heuristic role in theory construction and as being distinct from actual

theories (Bailer-Jones and Bailer-Jones 2002; Hesse 1963, 1974; Holyoak

and Thagard 1995; Kroes 1989; Psillos 1995; essays in Hellman 1988). Some

writers, similarly, use the term ‘model’ for simplified or idealized character-

izations of natural phenomena used in the process of formulating more

adequate theories and perhaps retained thereafter for ease of calculation.

There are, of course, also mathematical models in the sciences, including

computer models.

While uses of the word ‘model’ are diverse, they reflect the common

themes that scientific understanding involves the use of some kind of sur-

rogate, be it mental or external, that has formal or structural similarities to

its target domain. Moreover, while some particular uses of the word ‘model’

may differ—referring to external models, or to modes of thought involving

analogy or idealization—the overall accounts in which they occur are more

consonant with my cognitivist notion of modeling than at first it might

appear.

The difference between using an external model and using a mental

model is not really all that great. External models are already in some sense

“mental,” in that they are models only in light of how they are used in think-

ing and reasoning (though, of course, they are not “purely mental” in the

sense that would imply that there is no external model). Moreover, often

when one uses an external model, one is in fact thinking about the tar-

get system and not the model: one thinks about the target system through

the model. Similar things can be said about analogies like the billiard ball

model of particle collisions: while the model is inspired by the collisions of

actual billiard balls, one uses the model to think about collisions of gas mol-

ecules or other particles, and in practice the source metaphor is forgotten or

becomes transparent. The person using such a model is thinking about gas

molecule collisions in the same way that she thinks about billiard ball colli-

sions, but she is generally not thinking about billiard balls at all in so doing.

Simplification through idealization is likewise already built into my char-

acterization of models, and I do not regard this as a distinction between

different modes of scientific cognition. Some models, theories, and laws

are more simplified and reflect their targets less exactly than others, but

all involve bracketing and distorting idealizations (sometimes called “Aris-

totelian” and “Galilean” idealizations, respectively, in the philosophy of

science literature).

While some philosophers of science distinguish what they call models

(e.g., visualizations, external models, or simplified heuristics) from laws and

theories (sometimes distinguished as things that are framed as equations or

172 Chapter 9

propositions), others view scientific theories themselves as models or fami-

lies of models (van Fraassen 1980; Giere 1988; Suppe 1989; Suppes 2002;

though see the section later in this chapter on the semantic account of

theories for clarifications about the notion of “model” used by some of

these writers). Still others treat models as complementary to theories, fill-

ing in details absent from the abstract theory but needed for its application

to a more particular context (Redhead 1980; Morgan and Morrison 1999).

Again, for the most part, these verbal differences do not strike me as con-

trary to my claim that scientific understanding, including the understand-

ing embodied in laws and theories, ultimately depends on mental models.

Writers who distinguish models from theories often do so to emphasize

ways in which scientific reasoning depends on models (Magnani and Nerses-

sian 2002; Magnani, Nersessian, and Thagard 1999). If we need models as

“mediators” (Morgan and Morrison 1999) between laws or theories (under-

stood as “explicitly formulated principles” [Giere 2004, 744]) and specific

contexts, then the understanding of the theory requires such models. I have

no wish to claim that science does not also include equations, propositional

representations, and symbolic operations over them. My claim is that the

ability to work with equations and other symbolic representations in a

purely formal way does not itself amount to understanding of a scientific

domain, and such understanding is supplied by mental models.

Another use of the term ‘model’ in philosophy of science, however,

is distinctly different from mine. This usage is taken over from logic and

model theory. Model theory is used in the examination of formal systems

in mathematics and logic. A mathematical or logical system is a set of axi-

oms and their inferential consequences under the derivation rules of the

system. Such systems are formal in the sense that they do not have interpre-

tations of the terms assigned. A model of such a system is an assignment of

interpretations to the terms of the system. In logic, this might be an assign-

ment of a domain of objects to the referring terms and of relations to the

two-value predicates. In mathematics, the integers under addition would

count as a model of a group-theoretic structure with a particular type of

operation and properties like transitivity. A “model” in this model-theoretic

sense can serve a number of purposes. It can be used as a heuristic tool

for understanding the abstract structure through a more familiar particular

mathematical system. But it can also be used to test the structure for proper-

ties like consistency and closure.

The “semantic view” of theories in philosophy of science applies this

notion of models to scientific theories. Different versions of the seman-

tic view have been articulated by Suppe (1960), who takes models to be

173 Other Model-Based Approaches

set-theoretic structures, and van Fraassen (1980), who views models as

state-space structures (a survey of variations on the semantic view can be

found in Suppe 1989, chap. 1). Proponents of the semantic view contrast

models with linguistic formulations of theories, and some versions of the

semantic view hold that a model and its target need to be isomorphic (van

Fraassen 1980; Suppes 2002) or partially isomorphic (Da Costa 2003) to

each other. But beyond this, the similarity with other notions of “model”

ends. Model-theoretic models are truth makers for theories rather than non-

propositional cognitive structures through which we understand a scien-

tific domain. Such models are characteristically less abstract than the things

modeled. They are, in fact, special instances of the formal system for which

they are models.

9.3 Models in Theoretical Cognitive Science

The claim that model-based understanding is a key feature of human cogni-

tive architecture is found most clearly in artificial intelligence and theoreti-

cal cognitive science. Some writers use the term ‘model’—or some variant

of it, such as “scale model” (Waskan 2006) or “graphical model” (Danks

2014)—as their preferred technical term. But there is an equally large tradi-

tion that postulates systematic nonpropositional structures that form the

basis of ordinary reasoning, but using other terminology, such as Minsky

and Papert’s (1972) “micro-worlds,” Newell and Simon’s (1972) “problem-

spaces,” and the semantic networks, frames, and scripts I described in chap-

ter 4. Those projects had a great deal in common with my model-based

account, particularly the ideas that understanding comes in domain-sized

chunks and is stored in a nonpropositional form. Indeed, I count them as

important pioneers of a model-based approach, and my acquaintance with

them from the 1980s probably provided a substantial part of the inspira-

tion for my own ideas. I will not, however, redescribe them here, as chap-

ter 4 contains lengthy descriptions of some of them, particularly Minsky’s

notion of a frame.

At about the same time, David Marr (1982) published his influential

book Vision, which provided an account of computational operations that

might explain the processing of visual information from the raw perceptual

array on the retina to a three-dimensional “model” of a scene. Marr uses

the term ‘model’ only for the final stage of the process—a three-dimen-

sional model that is object centered rather than viewer centered—though

the prior processing stage, the “2½D sketch,” might be seen as a viewer-

centered model of a scene from a perspective. These are “models” in a sense

174 Chapter 9

more like Johnson-Laird’s than mine, as they are transient structures that

change with the perceiver’s perception and orientation. However, the abil-

ity to construct such views requires the possession of visual modeling sys-

tems more in accordance with my usage. Marr’s book is specifically about

vision and does not propose that mental models are an important unit

in understanding generally, and one could not extrapolate a more general

model-based view from his theory, as three-dimensional visual perception

is perhaps the aspect of cognition for which models that share formal fea-

tures of their targets are most obviously suited.

Marr also introduced what has become an influential distinction

between three levels of abstraction that are needed in understanding cog-

nitive systems. The most abstract of these, which he calls the “computa-

tional” level, specifies what a system does and its function. The next level,

the “representational” or “algorithmic” level, describes how it does them

in terms of what kinds of representations it uses and the computational

processes it uses to manipulate them. The third, the “physical” level, speci-

fies how the system is physically realized: in the case of human vision, the

neural structures; in the case of computers, the hardware implementation.

This three-level system has been adopted widely by subsequent writers in

cognitive science (though see Danks 2014 for some important clarifications

of its limitations).

Discussions of cognitive architecture tend to be seen as involving Marr’s

computational or representational levels or the intersection between the

two, addressing issues of the number and types of systems and at least a

rough specification of the types of representations (e.g., models or propo-

sitional representations) they employ, independently of questions about

their neural or physical implementation; and at least to the extent that

one accepts Marr’s classification of levels, my account is no exception. My

account is committed to the existence of model-sized units that do a certain

amount of their processing autonomously, and hence to at least some con-

straints on the kinds of representations and processes involved, and also to

a separate system for language-like thinking, which requires different sorts

of representations. I have not, however, proposed more specific features of

the representations or representational systems or the algorithms that oper-

ate over them. This is in part because I wish to present a model-based cog-

nitive pluralism as a plausible and broad thesis, which is compatible with

various more specific hypotheses about the kinds of information-process-

ing structures that might underlie the use of mental models. But it is also

in part because I have a more guarded view about what “algorithmic-level”

descriptions of such systems really provide: I doubt that cognition takes

175 Other Model-Based Approaches

place through the application of algorithms, though cognitive processes

might aptly be described by algorithms (much as I think that psychophysi-

cal effects are described by the Weber-Fechner laws, but very much doubt

that this proceeds by the brain representing and applying a “rule” couched

in terms of logarithmic or power function equations).

Some model-based accounts, however, are more specific in the type and

nature of the models they propose, and I will briefly discuss two of these.

The first is Jonathan Waskan’s (2003, 2006) suggestion that “scale models”

play an important role in cognition. Like most proponents of mental mod-

els, Waskan frames his view in contrast to the “mental logic hypothesis”

that “thinking involves the application of syntax-sensitive inference rules

to syntactically structured mental representations,” proposing the “alterna-

tive hypothesis … that thinking requires the construction and manipula-

tion of the cognitive equivalent of scale models” (2003, 259).

Images and scale models fall under the more general heading of physically isomor-

phic models (PIMs), which are representations that possess some of the very same

properties as that which they represent. Because forethought often requires the

truth-preserving manipulation of representations of three-dimensional spatial and

causal relationships, the PIMs that hold the most interest in the present context are

scale models. (Waskan 2003, 261–262; internal references deleted)

Waskan begins, as I did, by considering external models such as construct-

ing diagrams of situations on graph paper or building a model from Lego

blocks.

Of particular interest is the fact that spatial representations can be used to generate

predictions in a manner that obviates the need for rules (i.e., frame axioms) that

specify the consequences of each possible alteration to a represented system. One

might, for example, use a sheet of graph paper to represent the relative positions of

Harry, Laura, and Carlene. Should one then wish to know what the relative locations

of all of these individuals would be if Harry moved to a new position, one can simply

delete the mark representing Harry and insert a new mark in the square correspond-

ing to the new position.

Two-dimensional spatial media can also be used to represent the structure of

objects, and collections of such representations can be used to predict the conse-

quences of changes in their relative location and orientation. For instance, a card-

board cutout of my coffee table (as seen from above) can be conjoined with two-

dimensional representations (of equal scale) of the rest of the items in my living

room and a depiction of the room itself in order to predict the consequences of

countless changes in the relative spatial locations and orientations of these items.

A highly desirable feature of representations of this sort is that side effects of altera-

tions to the representation mirror the side effects of alterations to the represented

176 Chapter 9

systems automatically—without, that is to say, requiring their explicit specification.

As a consequence, such representations exhibit, at least with regard to a limited set

of dimensions, immunity to the prediction problem. They can, moreover, easily be

scaled up to include representations of further objects. (Waskan 2003, 262; internal

references deleted)

As with other discussions of “analog” models, Waskan emphasizes that

scale models reproduce systems of relationships in their target domains,

and that as a result, transformations on the models track transformations

in their targets. Waskan emphasizes the importance of such models in

“forethought”—in anticipating how the world will behave (on its own or if

intentionally manipulated) through simulation or other model-based rea-

soning processes.

Like Marr’s account of vision, Waskan’s theory is more limited in scope

than mine. It is broader than Marr’s, in that it includes rich possibilities

of off-line cognition and anticipations of possibilities in the context of

online cognition. But it is by its nature restricted to modeling spatial phe-

nomena and hence is an account of only a subset of cognitive capacities.

Like me, Waskan does not deny that there is also language-like cognition,

but I also hold that there are also a variety of nonspatial models that pre-

serve relations within, and allow nonpropositional reasoning about, other

domains of understanding. Moreover, Waskan’s scale models seem likely

to be, for the most part, “models” in Johnson-Laird’s sense, rather than

abiding frameworks for understanding classes of phenomena. However,

the capacity to form and manipulate scale models presupposes a more

general modeling system (or a collection of such systems) suitable to

this purpose.

In the most recent book on mental models in theoretical cognitive sci-

ence, David Danks (2014) argues that understanding and reasoning (or at

least a great deal of it; Danks seems to offer different claims about the scope

of his view in different parts of the book) are underwritten by graphical

models. The notion of a “graphical model” is considerably better defined

than most notions of models, thus rendering his theory more directly avail-

able for testing against bodies of empirical data, an enterprise that occupies

much of the book. But the notion of a graphical model was not originally

developed as a notion of a mental model or as a thesis about cognitive

architecture, and much of the point of Danks’s book is to motivate the

claim that it can nonetheless serve such ends.

In the original sense, graphical models are a type of mathematical model

used to represent statistical relationships between variables.

177 Other Model-Based Approaches

A graphical model is a family of probability distributions defined in terms of a direct-

ed or undirected graph. The nodes in the graph are identified with random variables,

and joint probability distributions are defined by taking products over functions

defined on connected subsets of nodes. By exploiting the graph-theoretic representa-

tion, the formalism provides general algorithms for computing marginal and con-

ditional probabilities of interest. Moreover, the formalism provides control over the

computational complexity associated with these operations. (Jordan 2004, 140)

A distinctive feature of such models is their uses of a “graph” in a technical

sense of a structure of “nodes” representing variables and “edges” repre-

senting probabilistic relations between them. (Diagrammatically, these look

much like the structures used to illustrate semantic networks and frames.)

The framework is flexible, in that it can be adapted to an open-ended

number of contexts involving different variables and relations. Graphical

models thus supply a kind of mathematical orthotic for, say, statisticians

or economists reasoning under uncertain conditions, and Danks suggests

that the same kind of structure already exists in the mind as a fundamental

feature of our cognitive architecture.

At their core, graphical models can be understood as compact representations of rel-

evance relations, where different types of graphical models represent different types

of relevance (e.g., informational, causal, probabilistic, communicative). They thus

address a key challenge for any cognitive agent: namely, determining what matters

and, often more importantly, what can be ignored. The term “graphical model”

encompasses many different types of mathematical models, including Bayesian net-

works (also called Bayes nets), structural equation models, random Markov fields,

hidden Markov models, influence diagrams, social networks, command-and-control

structures, and more. At their cores, these models all have a graph: a diagram of

nodes and edges that encodes the qualitative relationships.

From a purely mathematical perspective, the nodes are simply objects, and the

edges can be undirected (A—B), directed (A→B) or bidirectional (A↔B). (Danks 2014,

39–40)

Danks argues that the graphical-model hypothesis can be used to account

for causal inference and reasoning, provide a useful reconstruction of major

theories of concepts, and explain decision-making procedures that effi-

ciently use the relevance information encoded in graphs. Graphical mod-

eling, moreover, encompasses a broad class of more specific model types,

differentiated by their features, such as whether they allow cyclic or only

acyclic structures.

Danks’s notion of a graphical model is broader than Waskan’s scale mod-

els, as the latter are confined to spatial phenomena. It is both narrower and

more exactingly developed than mine. In large measure this reflects the

Chapter 10

The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

10 The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

The most distinctive claim of cognitive pluralism is that we understand the

world through many mental models of different content domains. The claim

that cognition involves the use of a number of special-purpose systems that

detect, track, and allow interaction with different parts and aspects of the

world, taken by itself, may not be quite a consensus view; but many previ-

ous authors have claimed that the minds of nonhuman animals are com-

posed largely of a grab bag of useful cognitive tricks, and argued that this is

a good strategy—and perhaps the only biologically plausible strategy—for

evolving intelligent animals. What is more controversial is the idea that

a further proliferation of special-purpose ways of understanding various

aspects of the world is still a good strategy once we have animals like human

beings, who possess capacities for language and explicit reasoning. Really

there are two separate sorts of issues here. The first arises from the pecu-

liar disconnect we often see between discussions of human minds and the

minds of nonhuman animals. Often, even people who think that animal

minds are composed largely of a bundle of closed instincts and good tricks

and acknowledge that human beings are products of evolution nevertheless

talk about human minds as though we had been designed from scratch to

be general-purpose reasoners. This strikes me as psychologically naive and

scientifically unrealistic. Second, even if we acknowledge that our capaci-

ties for reasoning, language, and language-like thinking are things added to

an older suite of more specialized abilities, there are quite reasonable ques-

tions about whether the newer and more sophisticated forms of thinking

and reasoning also take the form of many separate areas of understanding

about distinct domains, and whether this would still be a good design strat-

egy for minds that are no longer restricted to developmentally canalized

capacities that are products of natural selection.

182 Chapter 10

motley mix of the old and the new, as in the case of the three visual systems

humans possess, or the ability to extract depth information from multiple

cues. This is something that I think the evolutionary psychologists have

gotten more or less right: it would be downright astonishing if whatever

landmark mutations conferred our distinctively human traits also resulted

in the loss of hundreds of millions of years of accretions of special-purpose

instincts.

Another way of putting it is to say that evolution does not operate like

an engineer, who can make large-scale changes between models and even

go back to the drawing board and start from scratch. Evolution is limited by

the range of mutations on genes that can produce organisms that are viable

throughout their developmental sequence and capable of breeding. This

evolutionary constraint also sets a limit on how drastic a change can be in

species that reproduce sexually: a mutation that produces greater success

for the individual organism in everything save breeding will not get passed

on if the genetic changes make it reproductively incompatible with the rest

of the population. We now know that mutations do not need to be as tiny

and gradual as Darwin supposed. But compared with engineering, evolu-

tion is still a gradual and incremental process. When traits are lost because

they no longer confer an adaptive advantage, this is likely to happen on

the glacial timescale over which evolution operates on species. Perhaps our

descendants will have progressively fewer special-purpose canalized mecha-

nisms; but if so, the process will likely take thousands or tens of thousands

of years. (This is, of course, something that could change if we take an

active role in altering the human genome.)

“Heritage” Traits Are Still Useful

Moreover, it is by no means clear that losing some of these traits would be

a good thing. Take the reaction of disgust. Scientists now generally believe

that disgust evolved as a highly flexible mechanism for avoiding sources

of contagion, such as excrement, blood, open wounds, skin diseases, ver-

min, and rotting tissue. The mechanism is triggered by many stimuli, oper-

ates quickly, and makes it difficult to force oneself to come into contact

with whatever is regarded as disgusting. Of course, sometimes it is triggered

by things that are not really dangerous. Most slithery things are not really

dangerous. As I child I had a strong reaction of disgust to mushrooms,

including the innocent and nutritious mushrooms used in cooking. And,

as it turns out, leprosy—perhaps the paradigmatically disgusting disease

afflicting human beings—turns out to be among the least contagious of

diseases.

183 The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

A more precise knowledge of fields like biology and medicine can pro-

vide a far more exacting understanding of what classes of things present

biological hazards, the mechanisms through which they operate, and the

protocols that would allow us to deal with them safely. To a limited extent,

having such knowledge may allow us either to repress ill-founded reactions

of disgust or perhaps even to edit the set of stimuli that provoke them. But

such knowledge does not cause the disgust reaction to go away, and argu-

ably this is a very good thing. The capacity for disgust cannot be unlearned

because it is not part of a knowledge base that can be affected deeply by

other things we learn. It is a deeply ingrained mechanism of its own. And it

continues to be a useful mechanism, one that could potentially save us from

sources of contagion—particularly novel ones—that we might not respond

to sufficiently quickly by way of our scientific knowledge.

Or take the case of sex. Human sexual instincts are far more “open”

than the hardwired programs for reproduction found in insects or in the

species of birds that have characteristic mating rituals. But they are an

important motivational component in human reproduction. It is true that

we can understand human reproduction far more accurately in biological

and medical terms. But a being that had only such scientific understanding

of reproduction would have no intrinsic motivation to actually engage in

reproductive acts. And it would probably be quite impaired at things like

identifying suitable mates and their availability to breed, as our ability to

identify these in large measure depends on the operation of special biologi-

cal mechanisms sensitive to cues involving biological changes (pupil dila-

tion, increased blood flow to the lips and genitals) and behavioral patterns

indicative of gestational cycle and interest. (People could just ask each other,

“Would you like to make babies with me?” but I will leave it to readers to

decide for themselves whether that would be an effective sexual overture.)

When it comes to the things that natural selection really cares about, like

avoiding danger and producing offspring, evolution has provided a highly

effective set of tools that it is difficult to improve on, the lack of which

would leave us seriously impaired.

Or consider the ability to detect and respond to social cues, which is so

important to members of a social species such as our own. There are human

beings, such as autistics, who are impaired with respect to these abilities.

Some high-functioning autistics can learn about them by way of a kind of

theoretical reasoning and compensate to an impressive degree. But even

they never fully compensate for the lack of elements of the maturationally

normal cognitive tool kit that the majority of human beings possess. For

the rest of us, learning more about social interaction by way of, say, research

185 The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

the interests that make them relevant, then understanding will come in

“chunks” of corresponding size. Gravitation is a good candidate for a single

theory because it is the uniting feature of certain regularities of the motions

of bodies, and ones we encounter in ways that matter on a regular basis, as

well as because it turns out to be a single and fundamental force. If you mix

other things into a model along with gravitation, not only do you make the

cognitive work unduly complex, but you also obscure understanding of real

regularities. But we may have use for more than one model of gravitation,

some theoretical and others not. It is a good thing that we have an intuitive

understanding of falling bodies, which, while less accurate and projectable

than general relativity or even classical mechanics, is better for catching

falling vases or avoiding falling off cliffs. And even in scientific contexts,

we may need multiple models for phenomena like collisions at different

energy levels, partly because the particles themselves behave differently,

and partly because the most useful ways we have of observing, conceiving,

and acting on particle collisions differ with context.

So we have a first reason for a plurality of models: the world demands it.

There are many real patterns in the world, and the most efficient way—per-

haps the only way—to model them is one by one. (There are often ways of

combining them, such as vector algebra, but this presupposes already pos-

sessing models of the individual forces.)

An Objection: Most Patterns Are Not Fundamental

Now, in some contexts, one might object that “many real patterns” can

turn out to all be consequences of a single, more fundamental phenom-

enon. What we now call gravitation was once thought to consist of two dis-

tinct sets of principles: one for celestial bodies circling in the heavens, and

another for falling bodies beneath the sphere of the moon. Electromagne-

tism and strong and weak forces were all accommodated within quantum

theory, and many physicists expect there to be a unified field theory that

will fold gravity into a single theory with them. This is a legitimate question

in philosophy of science, one that I return to in part 3. But it will not do as

an argument about what is psychologically possible.

Could God have made creatures ab initio that thought about the world

solely in terms of the best theories we now possess, or a unified field theory,

if there is such a thing? Perhaps. It’s never a good gamble to bet against

what God could do. Could an organism that thought in this way, and only

in this way, be produced by natural selection? Probably not. Organisms that

attained this sort of very general understanding would probably have to do

so the way we have: by learning models of many more specific phenomena

186 Chapter 10

first, and then reasoning and experimenting their way to something more

general. Without a plurality of such models, there would be no way to get

to the more general theories. And even for purposes of the sciences, the

more specific models—of electricity, magnetism, particle collisions, nuclear

cohesion, planetary orbits, ballistics, and so on—are still used, and for good

reason. A more basic theory may explain more particular theories as special

cases but may still be useless for capturing the regularities captured by the

more particular theories. Biological processes may all be a result of underly-

ing physical processes, but neither evolution nor the Krebs cycle “pops out”

of the physics equations, and attempting to reason about, say, the origin of

species or even metabolism in quantum mechanical terms would be a very

bad way to go about it.

Moreover, a being that thought only in general and basic physical terms

would not be very good at interacting with its environment. The task of fig-

uring out what is edible or dangerous would be impossibly cumbersome—

and would not even make sense for an animal that did not also have models

of feeding and predation. And since there are domains that are not special

cases of physics—mathematics, ethics, aesthetics—the organism would not

be able to think in those terms. Which is to say, it would not be able to

think about all the things we can think about. In short, appeals to the ideal

of unification are irrelevant to psychology: unification is an achievement

that presupposes preexisting models, and a model that is “unifying” in the

sense of capturing the causal or compositional basis for other phenomena

is not necessarily a substitute for them in thinking or interacting with the

world. What is important for an organism is the ability to efficiently track

patterns that are salient, not those that are fundamental, and most of the

salient patterns are not fundamental. Being able to understand increasingly

fundamental theories allows us to think about new things, and to think

about them in illuminating ways, but it does not diminish the importance

of thinking about them in other ways.

Real Patterns and Affordances

I have spoken of mental models tracking “real patterns” in nature, such as

the gravitational attraction between two bodies. It is tempting—perhaps

irresistibly tempting—to think of such patterns as “objective” and “inde-

pendent of us.” And there are important ways in which there is something

to this characterization. One of these is seen most clearly by comparing

gravitation and the corresponding property of mass to a property like edi-

bility. Edibility is always an organism-relative property. What is edible to

one type of organism may not be edible by another. Meat is a potential

187 The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

meal for a lion, and a drop of nectar for a butterfly, but not vice versa. Like-

wise, what counts as dangerous, hospitable, or suitable for mating depends

on what kind of organism you are. So some properties, including those

that are most important biologically, are found neither in the organism,

nor in objects in its environment, but in some sense at the interface

between them.

J. J. Gibson, the founder of ecological psychology, called such properties

affordances and would say that the nectar “affords eating” to the butterfly—

that is, makes it available in a fashion the butterfly can exploit (Gibson

1966, 1977). Affordances are “real” in that they are not imaginary and in

that detecting an affordance is not making a mistake but getting something

right. They are “objective” in the sense that they do not depend on what

anyone believes or how she feels about it. But they are not “objective” in

the sense of being located solely in the object to which they are attributed. (In

one philosophical terminology, they are not intrinsic.) Both metaphysically

and scientifically, they are perfectly respectable on a par with gravitation,

though of course they are not fundamental, and many of them may not

appear among the principal theoretical terms of any science.

On the other hand, the concepts and models that we use to think about

affordances can differ greatly, from the standpoint of psychology, from the

models we use to think about a world of objects and properties. In particu-

lar, an organism can detect and respond to affordances without conceiving

them as things or as properties attached to things. We can think of edibility or

dangerousness as properties of things, to be sure. But even organisms that

probably lack anything closely resembling human concepts or even object-

oriented thought need to be able to detect and respond to affordances if

they are to do things like eat and avoid danger. Mosquitoes are sensitive to

differences in levels of carbon dioxide in the air and use these differences

to navigate toward mammals to obtain a blood meal. They probably do not

represent any of this to themselves in terms of objects and properties but

merely have circuitlike mental models in their tiny brains that allow them

to surf the affordance trail. Much of our nonconscious cognition consists

in affordance detection as well: we simply register that a particular surface

does or does not afford a stable foothold and adjust our path accordingly,

for example. But much of our conceptual thought is oriented toward affor-

dances, too: we see a chair as a comfortable spot to sit down or a water foun-

tain as a potential source for slaking our thirst. When reliable connections

exist between features of the environment and particular things we need

or do, affordance detectors pick out real patterns as well. They are simply

real patterns that involve us, with our particular set of needs, wants, and

188 Chapter 10

capacities, rather than patterns that do not depend on us (or at least depend

far less on us), such as gravity.

Real Patterns, Idealized Models

Models may aim at tracking real patterns, but some of them fail. And those

that succeed in biological terms—that is, track them well enough to be of

use to the animal—may not track them perfectly. Which is to say, once

again, that models are idealized. We have already addressed one type of

idealization: the bracketing idealizations involved in isolating one set of

features by ignoring others. But we have not addressed distorting idealiza-

tions, such as treating bodies as point masses or remapping wavelengths of

light onto a subjective color space. Distorting idealizations can, of course,

be a bad thing when we are confronted with situations in which the distor-

tions matter. But in other cases, the very features that count as distortions

can also enable easier comprehension and reasoning. And from a biological

perspective, both evolved cognitive systems and ones produced by forms of

learning that are not regimented like the sciences are shaped by processes

that converge on good-enough models rather than ones that are optimal

for purposes of exactitude.

Sometimes idealizations that distort by making simplifying assumptions

are needed to make problems computationally tractable. And even when

a more exacting model is computationally tractable in principle, it may

not be so for every actual mind. Some people can grasp Newton’s mechan-

ics but not Einstein’s; others cannot comprehend mathematical physics of

any sort. It is a good thing that the vast majority of us have more intuitive

models (learned or unlearned) that allow us to predict the trajectories of

falling bodies and to throw footballs. And these are good things for the

mathematical physicist to have, too. Mathematical physics is more apt for

rocket science but is not very apt for avoiding falling objects. Because there

are several epistemological and practical factors that go into the aptness of

a model, different models of the same phenomenon can be apt for different

purposes, and hence it is good to have more.

It is thus a wonderful thing that organisms like human beings are built

to form models that are useful to them, and also that some of these models

provide more exacting theoretical understanding. We have to begin with

models that have a great deal of us built into them—affordance models,

ways of knowing how to move about the world and how to manipulate

objects with the particular types of bodies we possess, models that are cen-

tered on things like what is good (or bad) to eat, what is dangerous, who is

friend or foe, and so on. Each of these provides a unique type of epistemic

189 The Plausibility of Cognitive Pluralism

and practical grip on the world and is useful for a particular set of purposes.

But we are also capable of refining our interests to things that are not of

direct biological relevance, such as discovering increasingly exact and gen-

eral models of patterns in nature, in ways that have increasingly less of us

bound up in them—that is, models that are increasingly objective. In fact,

we have acquired interests in an enormous number of things, and what we

could form interests in appears to be remarkably open-ended. But to be able

to incrementally expand a repertoire of interests in almost arbitrarily many

ways requires us to be able to form models of arbitrarily many different

domains.

Redundancy: Expected and Unexpected Benefits

One type of multiplication of models—redundancy—has particular advan-

tages of its own. One thing it does, of course, is to make an organism more

resilient in the face of injuries that compromise one of the redundant sys-

tems. But redundant systems do not function exactly alike. Redundant per-

ceptual systems like those for extracting information about depth respond

to different cues and hence are useful under different optical conditions.

Redundant cognitive systems may represent their common target differ-

ently, thus conferring different inferences and breakdown patterns. And

when two systems with the same target produce conflicting results, this

provides impetus for deeper empirical and theoretical investigation, both of

the phenomena in the world they aim to track and of the cognitive systems

themselves. Redundant systems can be productive of greater understanding.

Multiple Idealized Models, Epistemic Triangulation, and Compensation

for Forced Error

More generally, given that an organism is using idealized models of particu-

lar domains, it is naturally beneficial to have an abundance of models. On

the one hand, the bracketing idealizations of models imply that multiple

models are needed to cover different aspects of the world. On the other

hand, as we have seen, even a single model of one target domain can be

supplemented by another, idealized in a different way and employing a dif-

ferent representational system. Different models can compensate for one

another’s limitations. The result is a better understanding of reality, not in

the form of a single broader or more accurate model (though sometimes

that results as well) but through a kind of epistemic triangulation of the world

through a number of different vantage points and lenses.

In the extreme case, any given model may be subject to forced errors: mis-

takes that are ensured by the way it processes and represents information.

190 Chapter 10

The production of standard visual illusions in the human visual system

would be an example of this. But conditions probably exist under which

most or all models are forced into error. Consider our deeply ingrained

assumption that every physical object has a determinate location at any

one time. This assumption is encoded into classical physics, as well as the

core object system, folk physics, and likely a lot of special-purpose models

in between. And the assumption is safe unless we are faced with some of

the problems of quantum mechanics. In those cases, any representational

system that is forced to represent objects as having determinate positions

is forced into error.

Note, however, that we are not forced into these errors, even if particu-

lar models we employ are. I can measure the lines in the illusory pair and

confirm that they are of equal length. And with sufficient intelligence and

training, I can understand quantum mechanical descriptions of the behav-

ior of electrons and abstain from insisting on the assumptions of intuitive

and classical models. What gives us the ability to go beyond the limitations

of a given model is the very fact that we can have multiple models and

use them to triangulate the world more precisely. If we could only think

of physical objects through the core object system—or, for that matter,

through classical physics or quantum mechanics—we would lack some of

the cognitive flexibility that we in fact possess. So for anyone inclined to

suppose that a single-model cognitive architecture would be preferable to a

pluralistic one, ask yourself the question: which model would you choose?

And what would be lost in abandoning all the others?

I wish to conclude this line of thought by considering a particular appli-

cation of it. Kant held that the faculty of Sensibility always organizes sensa-

tion in terms of Euclidean geometry—so far, an empirical claim about the

psychology of perception. But he went on to use this in a transcendental

argument to the conclusion that space necessarily has a Euclidean geom-

etry. I think the argument is a valid one, though I think the conclusion (and

hence at least one of the premises) is false. One Kantian assumption is that

“the world” we are speaking about in science is what he calls the phenom-

enal world: the world-as-interpreted-through-the-Forms-of-Sensibility-and-

Categories-of-the-Understanding. So if the Forms and Categories force us to

represent any possible object of thought or experience in a particular way—

say, as located in a Euclidean space—then it is a necessary truth about the

phenomenal world that any phenomenal object will have that property.

And so if we are forced to think about physical objects in Euclidean terms

and cannot think of them in any alternative terms, then the phenomenal

world (of humans) is indeed necessarily Euclidean.

194 Chapter 11

cognition alone. It provides a medium in which we can think different

kinds of thoughts. It allows us to acquire models that nonlinguistic beings

could not acquire. And it provides a platform for new types of reasoning,

including not only syntactically based inference but also a variety of types

of critical thinking that require us to think about thoughts (or their linguis-

tic representations) as objects in their own right. Animals with modeling

engines probably existed for hundreds of millions of years before language

users appeared on the scene; but the addition of language vastly increased

the scope and power of model-based understanding. Some of the forms of

thinking that are built on the foundation of language are only hundreds or

thousands of years old.

11.1 Cognitive Complementarity

Before turning to the distinctive features of human cognition, let us con-

sider briefly some of the components of cognition and intelligence that we

share with many other species. Evolved special-purpose mechanisms and

the ability to learn through conditioning provide an ecumenical baseline

for most animal cognition, and both can be found in some form even in

animals as simple as flatworms. There are other strategies that are far from

ubiquitous but are found in different forms in a number of species: incorpo-

ration of the environment into the extended phenotype (insect hives, spi-

derwebs, beaver dams), social distribution of cognitive function (whether

in the different operations performed by different castes of ants, which pre-

sumably involve differential expression of a common genotype, or in social

animals like vervet monkeys or prairie dogs taking turns as sentries), and

the possession of redundant neural systems (such as our multiple systems

for extracting depth cues) that not only increase resiliency but also extract

information relevant to the same ends differently and under different con-

ditions. Other advances have appeared more recently in our evolutionary

lineage, such the increased curiosity and capacity for exploratory play char-

acteristic of mammals, and tool use, which is found in rudimentary form in

a number of species but is enormously expanded in human beings.

There are clearly interesting empirical and speculative questions in this

vicinity for cognitive ethology and evolutionary psychology, such as which

species have particular capacities, when they might have appeared in evo-

lutionary history, what adaptive advantages each was selected for, and how

some might have been precursors or enabling conditions for others. What

I wish to emphasize, however, is a much more general point about how to

think about the relationships between different components of intelligence

195 The Complementarity of Models and Language

that may initially have appeared as distinct watersheds in the history of

cognition. And the point is that however they might have first arisen, they

often exist today not only alongside one another but also in complementary

relationships.

Two very different types of complementarity deserve mention. The first

occurs when each type of system does something that the other cannot.

“Nativistic good tricks” provide an organism with ways of doing things that

could not be learned through “blank-slate conditioning.” (Or even if they

could be so learned in principle, the costs of having to learn them would be

astronomically high.) For example, animals more or less need developmen-

tally canalized ways of recognizing potential mates by responding to highly

specific types of cues and likewise need to perform the mating acts typical

of their species without having to learn them through observation or trial

and error. The vast majority of species also are born or hatched with some-

thing much closer to full adult capacities for perception and locomotion

than human infants and need to have such abilities immediately because

they do not have the benefit of an extended period of parental care. Being

able to learn through conditioning, by contrast, supplies precisely what

“nativistic” abilities lack: the ability to increase the organism’s adaptive

repertoire beyond what has been selected for and in response to demands

of its current environment, which is sometimes an environment that has

changed significantly from that of its ancestors.

But there is also a second type of complementary relationship between

canalized species-typical abilities and conditioning. There are some spec-

tacularly “closed instincts,” like the Sphex wasp’s routine for depositing its

eggs in a locust it has paralyzed. But many “instincts” are more “open,” in

the sense that they can be fine-tuned through conditioning. Some species

of wasps, for example, can build respectable nests on the first try but build

better nests on subsequent attempts. A kitten has an instinct to pounce on

small moving things but becomes an efficient hunter only through prac-

tice. “Built-in” abilities and conditioning are in one sense distinct building

blocks of intelligence, but much of an animal’s adaptive competence is a

result of their interaction.

Redundant systems—ones that provide parallel pathways to extracting

what is at least roughly the same sort of information, such as the variety of

ways the human visual system acquires information about depth—are also

complementary with one another. Of course, one advantage redundancy

confers is that it makes an animal’s cognitive abilities more resilient if it

loses one of the systems. A person who loses an eye can no longer use bin-

ocular depth cues, but there are a number of monocular cues left to draw

196 Chapter 11

on. But different systems also exploit different types of information, so that

they are useful in different contexts. Monocular accommodation (adjust-

ment of the focus of the lens of the eye) and convergence (the different

angles of the eyes when viewing objects at different distances) are particu-

larly useful at close distances, monocular movement parallax (provided by

moving the head) at medium distances, and linear perspective (such as the

sides of a road converging in the distance) and aerial perspective (the blue,

hazy look of distant mountains) at long distances. In a single visual episode,

a correct estimation of distance may require the use of multiple cues, and

dissonance between the information provided by two systems prompts a

search for more information.

While other species doubtless possess a modeling engine, and surely

many can form models of things that we cannot because they are attuned

to different affordances in the world through different perceptual organs

and forms of embodiment, human beings vastly outstrip other species in

the number and variety of things we can form models of. Perhaps this is

due in part to some difference in the neural mechanisms that ultimately

underwrite the formation of models or the greater sheer volume of such

resources available in the human cortex. But it is just as plausibly related

to other abilities we possess that are complementary to model formation.

Capacities for tool use have often been singled out as prime factors lead-

ing to distinctively human intelligence, and the ability to use tools (and

particularly to readily learn their uses, invent new ones, and pass them

on through social instruction) seems to go hand in hand with the abil-

ity to learn new models. In one way, this is just obvious: one needs to

learn a model for the use of a particular tool to employ it effectively. But

beyond this, there are connections to broader systems of models. On the

one hand, we don’t just hammer or saw for the sake of hammering and

sawing. These activities make sense, and the conditions for their optimiza-

tion become manifest, only in the context of some further set of projects

that require them. Hammering and sawing make sense only in the broader

context of building things through carpentry and the requirements these

impose on shaping and joining particular types of materials. More gener-

ally, having an expanded range of interests, and models related to those

interests, creates a market for a capacity to invent and use tools. On the

other hand, tools expand our ways of recognizing and exploiting the affor-

dances the world offers, many of which would be not only unavailable but

invisible to us without the requisite set of tools. Tools thus change what we

can have models of. This is perhaps most obvious in the case of scientific

instruments. Microscopes, telescopes, prisms, and centrifuges all allow us

197 The Complementarity of Models and Language

to explore new phenomena and partition them in new ways. Experimental

setups reveal new systematic relationships between variables. But no sharp

dividing line separates science from ordinary life here: simple machines like

the lever and pulley supplied crucial transitions to modern mechanics but

originated in more mundane ways, perhaps ultimately stretching back to

whatever capacities for tool use emerged in early primate ancestors, and are

found today in less-developed ways in other primate species. Likewise, car-

pentry tools opened up a whole new world of things that can be done with

wood, which no one would have conceived of by interacting with trees and

sticks using only their eyes and bare hands.

Active curiosity and exploratory play, which seem to be characteristic of

mammals and are also found in at least some birds, are also highly comple-

mentary to the capacity to form and refine models. Indeed, being curious

in ways that motivate systematic exploration of novel objects and environ-

ments seems to be so well paired with the capacity to form models of new

content domains that it is tempting to suspect that there might have been

a close historical relationship between them: that one was an enabling con-

dition for the other, or they coevolved, or if they appeared independently,

each made the other far more valuable than it would have been in isola-

tion. Exploratory play likewise seems to be well paired with the formation

of models, as it allows models of interaction with physical and social envi-

ronments to be acquired and refined in a fashion insulated from selection

pressures.

Identifying complementary relationships between cognitive systems or

cognitive traits in present-day species can help to motivate further questions

about their evolutionary history and how they interact in development.

Two systems may have appeared independently, and their complementar-

ity might be a happy coincidence. One system might be a necessary precur-

sor for the other. Or they might each have appeared initially in different

and more limited forms, and their interaction might have provided the

conditions for each to be expanded and shaped in ways that exploit their

combined benefit. While I am enthusiastic about the project of exploring

such questions, I will not pursue them in any depth here. My principal con-

cern here is with the relationship between models, language, and language-

like thought.

In the case of the relationship between model-based cognition and

natural language, it seems clear that model-based cognition and even the

modeling engine appeared long before the capacity for natural language.

The status of structurally language-like thinking and its relation to public

language on the one hand and to mental models on the other are more

198 Chapter 11

complicated questions. It might be that there are (or were among our homi-

nid ancestors) species that possessed some measure of language-like think-

ing but no capacity for syntactically articulated public language. Conversely,

language-like thinking might first have appeared as a form of internalized

speech and hence be found only among language users. It is also possible

that the neural structures used for public language are the very structures

used for language-like thinking, but the public and private expressions of

these potentialities are in principle independent of one another, with the

further possibility that just how fully each is developed may depend on the

presence of, and interaction with, the other.

I do not have an optimistic assessment of the prospects for settling such

questions decisively: assessing the forms of thinking in prelinguistic chil-

dren or nonlinguistic adults is tricky business, and we have no way of test-

ing the capacities of our long-dead hominid ancestors for either language or

language-like thinking. However, even if we are unable to settle questions

about origins and priority of appearance of baseline abilities, we will see

that there is nonetheless good reason to think that some types of linguisti-

cally based skills that can be exercised without overt speech are likely to be

acquired and mastered through the use of public language, often in ways

that also involve linguistic instruction and the use of written symbols. Base-

line competence in public language provides a scaffolding on which further

language-based skills can be erected. But all of this also depends crucially on

the complementary relationship between language and models.

In the remainder of this chapter, I will first stake out a position on the

relationship between model-based cognition on the one hand and both

language and language-like thinking on the other and then briefly explore

a number of ways in which the addition of language and language-like

thinking augments and transforms the forms of thinking available through

model-based cognition alone.

11.2 Language and the Priority of Models

One clear feature of language and language-like thinking that distinguishes

them from models is their form. Language is a medium characterized by a

syntactic structure and a stock of lexical elements that can occupy syntactic

slots. Models, of course, also have their own kinds of “formal shape,” but it

is not one characterized by sentence-like structures or transformational and

inferential rules that operate on their syntax. In a model, the conceptual ele-

ments of the model are constitutively tied to the inferential rules, and also

to ways of interacting with the world. In language, we can combine lexical

199 The Complementarity of Models and Language

items regardless of their origins or constitutive semantic inference patterns.

In this sense, language and language-like thought are “domain general.”

The same linguistic structures and rules are applied to representations

of various content domains and can be used to combine elements refer-

ring to different domains. On this point, advocates of central cognition

and a language of thought had something right: human cognition involves

more than the ability to think about particular domains in domain-

specific ways, and this is true even if we recognize that domain-specific

understanding can take the form of learned models and not just modules

that are developmentally canalized and appear principally in perceptual

preprocessing.

If you were to include within the scope of the word ‘language’ every-

thing that might appear in a text on language or linguistics, it would cut

a wide swath: not only syntax and semantics but pragmatics, phonetics,

phonemics, prosody, dialect, and so on. Of course, much of what would

thus be regarded as “parts of” natural language would not be parts of lan-

guage-like thought, as the list includes acoustical and pragmatic features of

public languages. Because I have characterized “language-like thought” as

a form of thinking with structural units analogous to those of language, it

would have to involve syntax, or at least something structurally analogous

to syntax. And there are specialized uses of the word ‘language’ that require

no more than this, as when we speak of “formalized languages.” So there

are “thin” notions of language that treat it simply as a system of syntactic

structures, (uninterpreted) lexical types and tokens, and perhaps generative

and inferential rules defined over these.

Philosophers have generally assumed that language-like thought would

also have to include more or less the same semantic elements found in nat-

ural language as well. And in one sense this is clearly correct: by and large,

when we think in a language-like form, we are not dealing with a purely

formal language. But just how much of what we call “semantics,” even with

respect to public languages, is really linguistic? The question is not yet clear,

as we have yet to specify the boundaries of what to count as “linguistic.”

But in the present context, where we are asking what the addition of lan-

guage or language-like thinking adds to the cognitive resources of beings

who already possess model-based cognition (or whose ancestors did), we

have some reason to draw the boundaries of the “truly linguistic” more nar-

rowly than we might in other contexts. If, as I have suggested, inferential

semantics is grounded in models that are not themselves language-like, a

good portion of what we call semantics is not “linguistic” in the sense of

having its origins in distinctively linguistic capacities.

200 Chapter 11

Consider an example. Suppose I am told (in language), “Napoleon was

short and vain.” Understanding this sentence allows me to make a variety

of inferences: that Napoleon was short, that he was vain, that he was less

than seven feet tall, that he would be likely to react badly to criticism, that

there was at least one person who was both short and vain, and so on. How

much of this understanding is a result of either linguistic competence or a

capacity for language-like thinking? Of course, the mere ability to parse the

sentence and make any sense of it at all requires competence in English.

Moreover, inference from a sentence of the form “x is P and Q” to “x is P” or

to “there is something that is P and Q” might well be based on understand-

ing how the language works, and likewise for any syntactically based infer-

ences I might make using it as a premise. But my understanding of what

heights are counted as short when dealing with human beings, or what

vanity is, or how a vain person is likely to respond to criticism is based not

in truly linguistic competence but in having models of the relevant content

domains. A person can have perfectly good linguistic competence and lack

the knowledge of a particular content domain that he or she would need to

make a semantically based inference.

The lexical items in a public language or a system of language-like

thought do indeed somehow tap into the separate forms of understand-

ing afforded by models: linguistic utterances and language-like thoughts

can express what I understand through models. And if someone is learn-

ing a language, part of what she has to learn is what lexical items tap

into which models. Someone learning English as a second language, for

example, may already have a mental model of vanity but not know that it

is expressed in English by the word ‘vanity’. But if the problem is that she

is a competent English speaker but has somehow never formed an under-

standing of vanity, this problem cannot be corrected by further learning of

the language. Rather, she needs to become familiar with the phenomenon

of vanity and form a mental model that tracks its salient characteristics.

Someone whose social cognition was impaired in ways that rendered her

incapable of understanding vanity might be able to learn what sorts of

things people say about people labeled “vain” and mimic them, but this

would not amount to an understanding of vanity. She would merely be

faking it when the conversation strays onto that topic. Her deficit in social

cognition, however, need not imply any impairment of her competence

in language.

For purposes of exploring the relationship between model-based cog-

nition, language, and language-like thinking, I will therefore construe

“language” in a fairly “thin” way, excluding from it forms of thinking and

201 The Complementarity of Models and Language

inference whose basis lies in model-based cognition. Of course, there are

other contexts in which it would make sense to adopt a “thicker” construal,

one in which “language” includes all that can be expressed in language,

what one can do with language, and so on. My aim is not to make a claim

about the range of ordinary or technical uses of the word ‘language’ but to

try to distinguish what contributions are made to cognition and reasoning

by the capacities for language and language-like thinking over and above

those grounded in model-based cognition. And in this sense, language and

language-like thinking are representational media characterized by syntac-

tic structure and lexical elements typed according to what syntactic slots

they can occupy.

Once we have characterized language and language-like thought in this

fashion, two implications that might otherwise be surprising seem clearly

to emerge. The first is that much and perhaps all of what we think of as

“semantics” does not really arise out of language at all. Many (perhaps all)

truly semantic connections arise out of models. Lexical units can express

and encode such semantic properties, but without models, language would

be largely devoid of semantic content. And this leads to the second impli-

cation: without such a relationship with mental models, language and

language-like thinking would be of little use and would confer little or no

adaptive advantage. They would be something analogous to purely formal

languages, in which the symbols can be rearranged syntactically but have

no further connection to one another or to the world. And if this is true,

it is no accident that a capacity for language arose only once model-based

understanding was firmly in place. Language contributes a great deal as an

addition to model-based cognition but confers little or no adaptive advan-

tage without it.

11.3 Two Objections

Before passing on to further discussion of the relation between language,

language-like thinking, and models, let us consider two possible objections.

The first comes from the computationalists, who would likely concede that

natural language is a recent and uniquely human trait, yet also claim that

thinking in general must take place in some sort of language of thought,

even if it must be in some ways very different from public language. The

second is implicit in discussions of causal semantics: that what we need for

a semantically pregnant language (whether public or private) is not a sys-

tem of mental models but merely reference-fixing relations for lexical units

in a language-like representational medium.

202 Chapter 11

Computationalism

In the last section, I claimed that merely possessing an internal “lan-

guage”—in the thin sense of a system with syntactic structure and some

set of syntactically based techniques for producing symbol strings from

other symbol strings—would not confer semantic understanding. To this,

advocates of the computational theory of mind might point out that Tur-

ing showed us how syntactic operations can be made to track semantic

relations, and this was the first (and perhaps the only) proposal for how

there could be meaning-respecting mental processes that do not require

a magical semantic interpreter. After all, some of the early explorations of

model-based views of semantic understanding—Minsky’s frames and other

projects in AI that took place around the same time—were implemented

in digital computers, and whatever semantic competence (or simulation of

semantic competence) they demonstrated was ultimately based in syntacti-

cally driven computations.

However, note that the sort of “syntax” involved in such systems is not

the syntax of the natural language in which the input and output sentences

are couched. Such “syntactic” processes are machine language operations

operating over binary digits that are not themselves representational at all.

We must therefore be careful to distinguish two senses in which computa-

tional processes might be called “linguistic” or “language-like.” One thing

this might mean is that the computer has been programmed to support

representations in a form something like a natural language and to perform

operations on these—that it has representational types that are at least struc-

turally analogous to sentence types or judgment forms. This is an important

goal of artificial intelligence, but it is a feature absent from most of what

the majority of computers do. We do speak of “the machine language” of a

particular computer and call the rules of the operating system “syntactic.”

But what we mean by this is not that the symbolic units are structurally

analogous to sentences or judgment types. The syntactic forms of machine

languages have little in common with those of natural languages, and all

that is really meant in calling them “syntactic” is that they are nonsemantic.

So when we speak of computers essentially being devices that manipulate

symbols according to syntactic rules, what we really mean is that programs

have their own distinctive forms of symbols and syntax, and this ultimately

drives the performance of the computer. This is quite generally true of com-

puters—indeed, it is close to being a definition of digital computation—but

it does not require the use of anything analogous to a natural language.

Program languages, particularly those that operate at the most fundamen-

tal level of bitwise operations, bear little resemblance to natural languages.

203 The Complementarity of Models and Language

As a consequence, advocates of the computational theory of mind tend

to mix together two very different types of claims about the mind. (I do not

mean to imply that they conflate them, though I am trying to caution the

reader not to do so.) On the one hand, computationalists often claim that

intentional states like beliefs and desires involve “mental representations”

that are at least closely analogous to structures in natural languages—say,

that intentional states are functional relations to representations with a

compositional syntax that has a subject-predicate structure. On the other

hand, they also claim that thinking in general is couched in some form

of symbolic representation and driven by “syntactic” (i.e., nonsemantic)

processes, presumably at some more fundamental level analogous to the

machine code of a digital computer, with allowances made for the dif-

ferences between the “implementing” systems of chips and neurons. The

latter claim does not apply only to intentional states we humans experi-

ence, such as judgments. If human cognition is “computational” in this

sense, presumably the cognitive processes of crocodiles and butterflies are

“computational” as well, though the “computations” are simpler and per-

haps couched in the different “machine languages” of different types of

brains. But if this is true, the claim that thought is computational does

not imply that it is structurally language-like. And if some language-like

structures are built on such “machine-level” architectures, we have no rea-

son to suppose that any semantic properties of the system supervene on

their specifically language-like form. It might instead be a consequence of

other structures that can be built on the machine-level architecture, such

as frames or models. So even if we grant (1) that cognitive processes are

accomplished through “computation” (in the machine-level sense), and

(2) that structurally language-like systems are built out of machine-level

computational resources, and (3) that some sorts of data structures and

machine-level computational processes can, in the right configurations,

confer (or at least mimic) semantic understanding,

1

it does not follow from

this that the kinds of data structures and machine-level processes that con-

fer understanding are the ones that are structurally language-like. Indeed,

the very concerns that led to the development of structures like semantic

networks and frames suggest that any semblance of understanding that

can be programmed into computers requires model-like, rather than lan-

guage-like, structures.

Causal Semantics

Since the influential publications of Putnam (1975) and Kripke (1980), a

great deal of philosophical work in semantics has concentrated on how the

204 Chapter 11

reference of names and kind terms is fixed. In particular, there have been

several variations on the general notion that reference is fixed through

causal relations: Kripke’s (1980) baptismal account, Fodor’s (1987) causal

covariation account, and Dretske’s (1987, 1988) teleofunctional account in

which the meaning (i.e., reference) of a term is what it has the function

of indicating. For our purposes, what matters is the possibility that such

accounts might supply a language-like system of mental representations

with semantic content without recourse to non-language-like units such as

mental models.

Let us assume, for purposes of argument, that some sort of causal or tele-

ofunctional relation is sufficient for fixing references of names (or name-

like mental representations) and kind terms (or concepts tracking kinds).

(Indeed, I think such theories have at least some grain of truth, which I

expand on in chapter 16, though I think such stories make sense only

within a broader story about mind and world.) This supplies an explana-

tion of semantic competence only to the extent that semantic competence

is confined to reference—that is, to tracking individuals and kinds.

But clearly this is a much thinner and more limited notion of semantics

than what motivated the need to posit things like mental models. Semantic

understanding is not simply a matter of being able to name or track classes

of things; it also involves being able to grasp their characteristic proper-

ties, relations, behaviors, and transformations. Even if we suppose that, in

coining a term or concept for water, I thereby come to track a particular

type of stuff, and even to pick out that kind of stuff in all possible worlds,

it by no means follows that I thereby gain any understanding of that kind

of stuff. Indeed, it implies neither (1) that I gain a grasp of the properties

that kind of stuff really has (which is, in fact, an important part of the stan-

dard development of such accounts) nor even (2) that I have any particular

“folk” understanding of its nature or how it behaves. Whatever forms of

understanding I might have must be reflected in a systematic set of ways of

representing and making inferences about it—the very sort of thing that I

have argued requires a mental model. Not only is no such model ensured

by the kind of causal relation that is supposed to secure reference, but

according to such theories, it would have to be to some extent independent

of reference, as I and my Twin Earth doppelgänger are supposed to have

isomorphic models that differ only with respect to reference. Not only do

causal accounts of reference not supply a way to explain such inferential-

semantic competence, but their standard development ensures that they

are independent of it. If there is any illusion that they obviate the need for

something like mental models, it is only because discussions of them have

205 The Complementarity of Models and Language

sometimes redefined ‘semantics’ in narrower terms that exclude inferential

dispositions from the domain of semantics.

Moreover, while causal accounts do not make reference a consequence

of mental models, they do not make it a consequence of language either.

Generally, what is supposed to secure the reference of a concept is some

kind of causal relationship with things outside the mind, generally through

perception. According to causal theorists, what makes a concept mean

“cow” is not the fact that it can be embedded in particular syntactic struc-

tures or manipulated through formal inference techniques, but the fact that

its tokening is caused in the right sorts of ways by cows. And what assures

this is not the language-like structure of Fodor’s central cognition, but the

encapsulated processes of his perceptual modules.

11.4 What Language Adds

What sorts of cognitive benefits does possessing public language and lan-

guage-like thinking confer that could not be had through model-based cog-

nition alone? In this section, I discuss a number of these benefits, with

attention to how they complement model-based cognition, both in the

sense of adding things that cannot be had using models alone, and in the

sense of how the two types of thinking interact to add up to something

more than the sum of the parts.

Communication and the Acquisition of Models through Language

The most obvious advantage afforded by public language is that it allows

for communication in ways that models do not. It is possible to build inter-

subjectively available external models for some things we think about, and

sometimes these are essential for instruction, communication, and joint

attention; but external model building alone would be an extremely cum-

bersome form of communication. But we should also make an important

distinction here between linguistic communication of propositions about

domains that speaker and hearer both already understand in similar ways

and the use of language in the process of teaching one another the use of

new models.

A great part of everyday linguistic communication involves the exchange

of information already framed in terms of models that both speaker and

hearer already understand. If I say, “There’s another big storm coming in

tomorrow,” and you understand the local weather patterns this time of

year, this may communicate something rich in specific implications. In a

New England winter, a neighbor who heard and believed it might expect a

206 Chapter 11

substantial snowstorm, stock up on salt and gasoline for the snowblower,

and so on. Someone uttering the same sentence in Florida in summer, or

in the Arabian desert, would likely mean something quite different, and

uptake would require models of different sorts of meteorological events. If

I posted the sentence on a blog and followed it with “What should I do to

prepare?” readers who did not know my location or did not understand the

relevant type of thing called a storm would not know how to advise me (in

one case, because they would not know which model to apply, in the other

because they would lack such a model).

The purely communicative use of language generally succeeds only to

the extent that speaker and hearer already share the kind of frame of ref-

erence provided by a mental model. When models are shared, a compact

utterance can provide enough information for a rich set of inferences. But

without such a shared understanding, there is unlikely to be uptake about

the implications or even the sense and reference of the lexical items. If I

read a random sentence from a book on a topic I know nothing about, I

can probably recognize it as a grammatical sentence but will have no real

understanding of what it is saying. It is the models that lie in the back-

ground that generate a space of possible sensible representations in lan-

guage. To understand what is meant, I may have a great deal of work to do

acquiring the requisite models.

But to do so, I need not engage in a process of rediscovery de novo.

Language can also provide more efficient means for guiding me through

the process of model acquisition. Indeed, the art of using language in this

manner is precisely what is needed for a good explanation or the composi-

tion of a good textbook. In some cases, a really good verbal explanation

may be all the external prompting a reader or hearer needs to form a model

that at least roughly corresponds to the speaker’s or writer’s. In other cases,

language may at least play important assisting roles, such as pointing out

where the important variables lie or correcting or sharpening the learner’s

understanding. Learning a manual skill, a form of dance, or the structure of

a new type of music probably cannot take place without exposure to, and

practice with, the domain of study, and things like mimesis, pointed rep-

etition, and reshaping of what the student is getting wrong may be indis-

pensable. But even these can often be greatly aided by the use of verbal

prompting. (“You are swinging the hammer from the side and bending the

nail rather than driving it in.” “In this style of playing the jig, the accents

go on the first and third of six beats, not the first and fourth.”) Commu-

nication using terminology based in other, already-shared models can thus

help the learner quickly revise a new model she is building while learning.

207 The Complementarity of Models and Language

And terminology based in the new model can adroitly be paired with care-

fully selected examples or demonstrations to help the learner attend to

the units that the new model tracks. (“This passage is played spiccato—like

this,” followed by a demonstration of the bowing technique, and then per-

haps examples and explanations differentiating spiccato bowing from other

bouncing styles such as ricochet.)

Metaphor

In chapter 8, I briefly explored Lakoff and Johnson’s (2003) claim that a

great deal of human understanding is based in metaphor. I related this to

model-based understanding by suggesting that metaphorical transposition

involves taking a model of one domain and using its structure as the scaf-

folding for a model of a different domain, with subsequent revisions to

accommodate the differences between domains. In the standard sense of

the word, metaphor is a linguistic phenomenon, and so it might seem to

follow that if Lakoff and Johnson are correct, a great deal of human under-

standing is possible only because we have the linguistic capacities that can

form a basis for metaphor. We should, however, be cautious in drawing this

conclusion, as nonlinguistic mechanisms might also be available for trans-

posing the structural features of a model to a new domain. This strikes me

as an important empirical question we should be careful not to prejudge.

But even if nonlinguistic methods can achieve this result, mechanisms

based in linguistic metaphor may be more efficient and have broader scope

and are clearly powerful tools for the transmission of model-based forms of

understanding. To take one of Lakoff and Johnson’s examples, just using a

conflict metaphor for argument can prompt the hearer to activate a conflict

model and begin to use it as a way of thinking about argument. She might

eventually have thought of this way of looking at things on her own, but

language allows it to be transferred quickly and to proliferate through a

community, enlarging the stock of shared models that can be used in rou-

tine communication.

Models That Require Language

Several of the examples I used in discussing the idea of a mental model

involved forms of understanding that nonlinguistic beings could not

acquire at all. It goes without saying that models of domains that them-

selves involve language—a model of the sonnet form, or even of restau-

rant interactions—would be unavailable to nonlinguistic beings. Scientific

understanding requires more than a grasp of grammar and reference, but

it is unlikely that our ancestors could have progressed very far beyond folk

208 Chapter 11

physics or folk biology without increasingly regimented forms of linguistic

representation and communication. (And we might well wonder whether

even maturationally normal forms of folk theories can be developed in the

absence of normal linguistic interaction, which is after all part of the normal

developmental environment of human children.) Likewise, the acquisition

of forms of mathematical understanding that go beyond what is present in

the core systems takes place through linguistic interaction and may directly

exploit cognitive capacities originally used for language or language-like

cognition.

It would at this point be a matter of speculation just what proportion of

the mental models we use depend essentially on language. I am prepared

to allow that the proportion may be quite large indeed. Language provides

new forms of representation, communication, and interaction—not least

in the ability to form concrete questions—and together these greatly expand

the sphere of things we can form interests in, explore to find the relevant

patterns, interact with, and think about. Mastery of a domain still requires

us to form a mental model of it, but there are domains that are revealed

to us only because we can think in language-like ways and communicate

through language.

Representation and Reasoning across Models

One fundamental advance afforded by language is that it provides a

medium in which we can think thoughts that combine elements from dif-

ferent models. The inferential patterns associated with lexical items in a

language or concepts used in language-like thought may come from the

life they lead within models; but from the standpoint of language and

language-like thinking, a lexical or conceptual item’s model of origin is

irrelevant. It is simply a unit of a particular logical or grammatical type.

Concepts and lexemes originating in different models can be combined

grammatically, propositions involving them can be joined with logical con-

nectives, and the resulting propositions can be assembled into forms of

logical inference whose validity does not depend on their semantic values.

This endows us with capacities for cross-domain representation and reason-

ing that go beyond simply using two models in tandem, such as triangulat-

ing a common referent.

While this is an extremely powerful cognitive advance—so much so

that we might well regard it as one of the most important features of truly

human cognition—the marriage between model-based understanding and

language-like representation is imperfect. There are grammatically well-

formed sentences that do not actually make sense once you understand

209 The Complementarity of Models and Language

the meanings and implications of the terms. A single lexical item may

stand in for elements in more than one model, where it functions differ-

ently, producing ambiguity or even paralogistic reasoning. And we tend

to assume in logical inference that the terms or concepts employed have

sharply defined extensions, and forget that concepts as psychological enti-

ties tend to have fuzzy boundaries and originate in idealized models. Lan-

guage, or at least logical reasoning based in language, seems to “want”

things like bivalence and well-defined extensions, but this seems to be

something of a mismatch with what model-based understanding provides.

This, I suggest, is the psychological explanation of many apparent para-

doxes and is a result of adding a language-like form of thinking optimized

for one set of purposes to a preexisting model-based form of understanding

optimized for others.

Linguistic Creativity

Language also affords its own forms of creativity. Precisely because gram-

matical sentence formation is relatively unconstrained by model-based

semantics and new sentences can be constructed more or less at will, we can

construct sentences that express things that we might never have thought

of on the basis of model-based thinking. Of course, the vast majority of ran-

domly constructed sentences have little cognitive value. Some are merely

amusing (e.g., puns, at least if you consider puns amusing), others evocative

(poetry). But sometimes they may spur new ways of thinking that prove to

afford genuinely useful new ways of understanding the world. The initial

creative act may not have been a product of insight but might nonetheless

generate new insight.

Higher-Order Cognition

Language also seems to provide the basis for several forms of higher-order

cognition, in which we think thoughts about thoughts or thought struc-

tures. Perhaps some basic forms of higher-order cognition are nonlinguis-

tic, such as simply being aware that I am having a particular sensation,

thought, or experience (though this might better correspond to what is

sometimes called “higher-order perception”; cf. Armstrong 1968, 1984;

Lycan 1996). The analytic power of higher-order cognition, however, seems

to reside in the ability to attend to features of thoughts, and particularly

to either linguistically formulated thoughts or linguistic representations of

those thoughts. We can raise questions about the clarity of a term or con-

cept, or about the meaning of a proposition, only when we can represent it

as an object of thought, as opposed merely to thinking about other things

210 Chapter 11

through it. We can examine the validity and cogency of an argument or

check the steps of an inference only when we can represent the argument

and its constituent propositions as special kinds of objects. The capacity to

treat thoughts (or their Fregean contents, or their linguistic or logical rep-

resentations) as objects of thought is not required to be able to think at all,

but it would seem to be a prerequisite for critical thinking.

This description, of course, leaves a number of questions open, such as

whether various techniques of critical thinking are directed toward thought

tokens, thought types, Fregean propositions, or linguistic representations

such as sentences. It also leaves open the question of whether critical lan-

guage-like thinking depends essentially on public language. I think there are

two types of (potentially defeasible) reasons to assume that it does. First,

critical thinking generally involves thinking about representations formu-

lated in a public language, even if this is done without overt speech. Sec-

ond, we generally learn to think critically through dialectical interaction

with others. While I cannot rule out the possibility that a clever individual

might develop forms of critical thinking on her own, it seems quite likely

to me that, in general, the capacity for individual critical thought arises by

way of a kind of internalization of interpersonal dialectic. (Of course, even

a brilliant individual who pioneers critical thinking from the ground up on

her own would do so using linguistically expressed thoughts, even if some

of the vocabulary is of her own invention and has not been shared with

others.)

External Symbol Storage

An important extension of natural language is provided by writing. While

a good portion of the earliest extant examples of writing are accounting

records, anything that can be said can also be represented in external sym-

bols. Merlin Donald (1991) has argued that external symbol storage is itself

one of the great watersheds in the history of human cognition, particularly

because it allows the storage and retrieval of information to be freed from

the vagaries of individual memory. Before writing, the stock of informa-

tion available to a community was largely confined to what was known

and remembered by its elders. Writing allows information to be preserved

indefinitely and to be conveyed to broad audiences, widely separated in

space and time.

But external symbol storage can also serve as an important cognitive

prosthesis that expands and refines our ability to think and reason more

clearly. A written sentence can be scrutinized and reexamined, allowing

us to better understand it and to analyze it critically. As a consequence,

211 The Complementarity of Models and Language

it is also possible to set down in writing thoughts that would be difficult

to express or comprehend orally because they stretch the storage limits of

auditory parsing. In assessing a line of reasoning, it is an enormous benefit

if one can use written formulations that stay put, which we can refer back to

as needed. And certain forms of writing, such as the schematic representa-

tions used in logic, help to clarify the logical forms of propositions. It may

be (as Plato claims in the Seventh Letter) that there are significant disad-

vantages to writing as opposed to the living dialectic of oral discourse, but

writing also has signal advantages for clear analytic thinking.

Social Knowledge Production

Finally, while knowledge and understanding may be attributed in the

strictest sense to individuals, their production is often inescapably social in

character. Things like contemporary scientific theories and systems of laws

are seldom the work of one person working in isolation. Not only does one

person’s work build on another’s, but it is often the case that the formation

of a model requires teams of individuals with different types of expertise

and distinct duties working together to craft something that none of them

could accomplish alone. Even if the final product is something that an

individual is capable of understanding, it may well be that, in the pro-

cess of developing it, none of the members of the team understood the

whole product both comprehensively and in detail, and the process of

coordinating the different components depends essentially on language.

Mental models are indeed essential to the process, but their coordination

takes place not via mechanisms like triangulation that operate within indi-

vidual minds but through carefully developed special means of commu-

nication, crafted toward a particular end, but erected on the foundation

of language.

11.5 Summary

Public language and language-like thinking are cognitive capacities distinct

from model-based cognition. They are comparatively recent additions to

the cognitive tool kit and would have been of little use to animals that did

not have substantial capacities for model formation. They inherit much of

their semantic content from mental models and do not themselves provide

a basis for the same types of reasoning and understanding supplied by men-

tal models. But neither are they simply separate additions to the cognitive

tool kit. They provide distinct forms of thinking and reasoning that com-

plement model-based processes and allow us to refine our mental models

216 Chapter 12

12.1 Visions of Unity and the Problems They Face

Let’s start by reviewing what has been said so far about the units of knowl-

edge and understanding. If knowledge is justified true belief, then the units

of knowledge are sentence sized. I have used the term ‘understanding’ for a

broader and more interconnected sort of comprehension of a domain—an

understanding of chess, or of Newtonian mechanics, or of the Japanese

tea ceremony—and argued that mental models are fundamental units of

understanding. The implicit rules of a model are among the things that

might be counted as dispositional beliefs (say, that bishops move only

diagonally or that bodies exert a gravitational attraction described by the

inverse square law). The conceptual resources of models are used to frame

more specific judgments (say, that the white bishop can capture the black

rook on the next turn or that this rock is accelerating in free fall toward the

ground). The understanding associated with a model also includes abilities

to recognize particular situations as ones to which the model may aptly be

applied and to act in a fashion guided by the model.

To get clearer on ways that beliefs and models might be “unified” or

“disunified,” it is useful to start with science, if only because there has been

so much prior discussion of “the unity of science.” Science has often been

characterized in terms of a set of beliefs about theories, laws, and empirical

facts, but scientific theories are really paradigm examples of mental models.

We can have beliefs about scientific models—say, that Newtonian mechan-

ics provides an apt model for certain types of situations. Explicitly formu-

lated laws express basic commitments of such models. And more specific

types of scientific beliefs and judgments involve the use of a model to frame

a situation and apply the rules of the model to reason about it. But scientific

models also stand in various relationships to one another: they involve

consonant or dissonant commitments, representational systems, and forms

of reasoning and can be used to license judgments that are consistent or

inconsistent with one another. I thus begin by discussing three visions of

scientific unity, along with brief summaries of reasons that they have been

difficult (and perhaps impossible) to achieve.

Three Visions of Scientific Unity

Some visions of the unity of science are cast in terms of scientific knowledge,

beliefs, or propositions and based on two key ways that propositions can be

related: consistency and implication. It would generally be assumed that

two scientific beliefs—or two beliefs generally—that are known should be

consistent with each other, because to be knowledge, they must be true,

217 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

and two inconsistent beliefs cannot both be true, at least in standard log-

ics. If two scientific theories imply conclusions that are not consistent with

each other, we thus have reason to think that something must be amiss

with at least one of them. This might seem to be a simple truth of logic and

hence a fairly minimal type of “unity,” but it is not at all trivial to make it

work out the way we anticipate: the best scientific theories we have, gen-

eral relativity and quantum theory, in fact seem to produce inconsistencies

when combined.

A second and stronger vision of unity is based on the implicatory rela-

tions between propositions. Two such implicatory relations are particularly

important. The first is the Laplacean determinist view that a comprehen-

sive set of laws of nature (regarded as propositions) combined with a com-

prehensive description of the state of the universe at a time t should imply

a comprehensive description of the state of the universe at any later time

t + ∂. The second is the reductionist view that there is some lowest-level

description of the world (say, in the vocabulary of fundamental physics)

from which all the legitimate higher-level descriptions of the world (say, in

the vocabularies of chemistry, biology, and psychology) can in principle be

derived. Both determinism and reductionism have sometimes been regarded

as views that must be true. No less a philosopher than Kant claimed that it

is a synthetic a priori truth that we must regard all events as determined by

a law of nature.

1

And some of the twentieth-century positivists and empiri-

cists regarded intertheoretic reduction as a norm of the logic of science,

eventually leading some philosophers who believed some supposed phe-

nomena (such as intentional states and ethical facts) to be irreducible to

become eliminativists about them. But the questions of whether all events

are causally determined and whether all scientific theories are reducible to

fundamental physics also seem quite plausibly to be higher-order empirical

questions (a view taken, e.g., in Oppenheim and Putnam’s [1958] “Unity

of Science as a Working Hypothesis”). And as empirical hypotheses, both

have fallen on hard times. Reductionism reached its zenith in the early

1960s, but since that time, philosophers of science who have examined the

relationships between theories carefully have repeatedly found that they

fall short of the standard of reduction as axiomatic reconstruction (Horst

2007). Quantum theory employs probabilistic equations and, in some of

its philosophical interpretations, is regarded as truly indeterministic. And I

argued in Laws, Mind, and Free Will that even nonprobabilistic classical laws

do not imply a commitment to determinism, and a commitment to them

is compatible with a commitment to anomic events, including free will and

miracles (Horst 2011).

218 Chapter 12

A third vision of unity is that an ideally completed science would employ

a single comprehensive theory of everything. This would not mean that

more particular theories of things like chemical reactions, thermodynam-

ics, or neural dynamics would cease to be employed, only that they would

turn out to be either derivable from the grand unified theory as special

cases applicable (and perhaps much easier to use) in particular contexts,

or else sufficiently close approximations of the implications of that theory

to be useful in those contexts. As theories are, in my view, models and not

propositions, we may regard this as a vision for replacing our many dif-

ferent models of distinct phenomena with a single comprehensive model

without a loss of explanatory power or predictive accuracy. The search for

a grand unified theory in physics is generally seen as an attempt to find a

single theory to unite a relativistic theory of gravitation and a quantum

theory of strong-weak-electromagnetic force. Many theoretical physicists

assume (and we might well ask why they so readily assume it) that it is only

a matter of time until we will hit upon such a theory, or at least that it is

available in principle, even if no one in fact uncovers it. But this is by no

means an obligatory view. Stephen Hawking, for example, has changed his

mind on this question:

Up to now, most people have implicitly assumed that there is an ultimate theory,

that we will eventually discover. Indeed, I myself have suggested we might find it

quite soon. However, M-theory has made me wonder if this is true. Maybe it is not

possible to formulate the theory of the universe in a finite number of statements. …

Some people will be very disappointed if there is not an ultimate theory, that can be

formulated as a finite number of principles. I used to belong to that camp, but I have

changed my mind. (Hawking 2002)

I will return to Hawking’s views shortly, as they are tied up with his “model-

dependent realism”—a view that I discovered only late in the process of

writing this book, but which has a great deal in common with cognitive

pluralism.

Beyond the Sciences

Even if scientific knowledge and scientific models were to turn out to be

unifiable in one or more of these ways, we would still be faced with the

question of whether our other, nonscientific beliefs and the models in which

they are framed can similarly be unified. The most notable philosophical

problems are about the relationship between normative claims (particu-

larly ethical claims) and positive claims—that is, beliefs about natural laws

and matters of fact. As Hume taught us, no set of claims about facts and

219 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

laws entails any normative claim. And Kant’s view that we are compelled

to regard the world of nature as causally deterministic was in precarious

balance with his view that we must regard human action as free in a sense

that is incompatible with causal determination. Even within ethics we are

led to paradoxes in which two opposing views seem compelling, and there

are alternative metaethical models (consequentialist, deontological, virtue-

theoretic) that seem both irreducible to one another and to often entail

conflicting conclusions about cases.

There is also a set of problems about the relationship between mathemat-

ics and the world of nature: mathematical truths are not a consequence of

how the world is, and have a kind of necessity that could not be underwrit-

ten by empirical facts and laws. Mathematics cannot be reduced to phys-

ics. But neither can physics be reduced to mathematics (despite the hopes

of some thinkers of the seventeenth century), as there are purely physi-

cal properties like mass as well, and various mathematical systems provide

descriptions of various alternative forms space might take, and waves,

particles, and fields that behave in alternative ways. And the discovery of

non-Euclidean geometries in the nineteenth century brought the startling

realization that while individual mathematical systems might be internally

consistent and derived from a small set of axioms, there are indefinitely

many such systems whose axioms are inconsistent with one another.

We might, moreover, raise similar questions about many more ordinary

domains of understanding. Chess pieces and chessboards are typically gar-

den-variety physical objects—pieces of wood or plastic. (The ontology of

the “pieces” in computer chess is more complicated, but still physical. The

status of those in mental chess turn on whether the mind itself is physical.)

But a complete understanding of the pieces and board in physical terms

would not confer an understanding of the game of chess. Perhaps the die-

hard reductionist might insist that “the game of chess” is simply a set of

conventions that could be reduced to the mental states of those who share

the conventions, which could in turn be reduced to fundamental phys-

ics. And if such reductions could be carried out, they might well explain

the behavior exhibited in chess matches. But it is unclear that they would

explain the game as an abstract entity any more than an explanation of the

mental states of mathematicians would explain mathematics.

We thus have three visions of how beliefs and models might be uni-

fied, each with corresponding possibilities for disunity. The first and most

modest views “unity” in terms of global consistency: to be unified, our

beliefs (including the commitments implied by our models, at least when

aptly applied) must be mutually consistent. The second is framed in terms

220 Chapter 12

of implication: that there should be some relatively conservative set of

beliefs and models from which the others can be derived. The third is that

“unity” would consist of a single comprehensive and self-consistent model

in which all our beliefs and judgments can be framed, and in such a fash-

ion that nothing we know or understand on the basis of having multiple

models is lost in the process.

12.2 Disunity as a Problem

At some level, most of us—not just philosophers and scientists—find dis-

unities of belief and understanding troubling, and this leads us to seek ways

to unify them. It would be useful to take a moment to examine the nature

of this situation, and of our dissatisfaction with it.

First, we each find ourselves with some number of conflicting and even

contradictory beliefs. Sometimes it is that we believe one thing on one

occasion or when primed in a particular way, and another on another occa-

sion or when primed in a different way. But sometimes we find ourselves,

even upon deep reflection, equally committed to two contrary claims and

do not know how to resolve the tension between them.

Second, we find this situation dissatisfying. It drives us to attempt to

find a way of resolving the contradiction. It is no accident that paradoxes

drive much of the histories of both philosophy and science. This seems to

be a deep and productive feature of human psychology: that when we are

pulled toward two contradictory beliefs, we are spurred to find some way

to resolve the contradiction. Often we succeed, and some of these successes

have been watershed moments in the history of human knowledge. A more

complacent species would have learned far less about the world.

Third, we do not just have conflicting beliefs; we have multiple ways of

framing things through models. (This is a slightly more contentious claim

than the first two, because it involves a bit of theory.) Sometimes this is just

a matter of having different ways of framing things. And sometimes it seems

to amount to something more serious: the different ways of framing things

are in various ways in tension with one another, such as being incommen-

surable or implying contradictory inferences.

Fourth, the disparities between models are also dissatisfying. They are

probably not as immediately troubling as contradictions between beliefs,

except perhaps when they generate contradictory beliefs. Yet something

within us is puzzled and troubled even by having two models that frame

the world in different terms, and seeks to find some way of bringing them

into some deeper harmony.

221 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

We might summarize the second and fourth points by saying that the

mind has a kind of drive toward finding ways to unify a system of beliefs

and of understanding, respectively. This, of course, is a point famously

made by Kant. Kant’s attendant observation should be added: the mere fact

that we have a drive to unify what we believe or the ways we understand

things does not itself entail that we will in fact be able to do so. And to this

we may add a fifth point, which is also a variant on Kant: we have notions

of particular ways that knowledge and understanding might be brought

into greater unity. Kant had his own hypotheses about what these are and

their cognitive underpinnings. I would suggest that we see evidence of a

distinct set of these in the types of unification that philosophers and sci-

entists have in fact sought: global consistency of beliefs, reduction, and a

single all-encompassing theory.

I will explore, in chapter 14, a way of developing a sixth point, also

foreshadowed by Kant: the ways that features of cognitive architecture can

generate particular types of illusions, some of which have to do with the

mind’s drives to unify knowledge and understanding in particular ways. For

present purposes, it is perhaps enough to say that our dissatisfaction with

disunities is clearly a feature of something about our minds, but a psycho-

logical drive to unify by no means ensures that the project can be carried

out to its desired ideal conclusion.

Why might our beliefs and models, as we find them, be disunified? We

have already explored one part of an answer to this question with respect

to models: having various models of different aspects of the world is a good

strategy for building a capacity for understanding many features of the

world into finite minds, and each model must represent things in some

particular way. What we have yet to explore is how the ways models are

idealized can lead to disunities of understanding. If beliefs are constrained

by the ways we can frame thoughts through the resources of models, some

problems about disunities of belief may also be explained in the process. But

in general, there need be no deep mystery about why a given finite mind,

at any given time, might encounter conflicts among its beliefs and models.

No one ever thought that everyone’s system of beliefs was in fact compre-

hensive or consistent, and anyone who thought that about the models used

to frame such beliefs was psychologically naive. Claims about unification of

knowledge and understanding are claims not about our beliefs and models

as we find them but about what it might be possible to do to bring them to

greater unity.

The more trenchant question is this: is there a way of understanding

why, in spite of millennia of philosophical inquiry and centuries of science,

222 Chapter 12

our beliefs and models might still present every indication of being abid-

ingly disunified? And to this there would seem to be several distinct types

of possible answers. The first is that the disunities of knowledge and under-

standing are only a symptom of the current state of our knowledge and

understanding—our current state of ignorance, as it were. Given enough

time and investigation, all disunities would all be resolved. A second is that

there are indeed principled disunities of knowledge and understanding,

and the reason for this lies in something about the world. A modest version

of this would be that we need multiple fundamental theories because there

are in fact multiple fundamental forces. A robust variant would be that

understanding is disunified because the world was already, in some sense,

disunified before it (Dupré 1993). A third possibility is that there are things

about the world that minds like ours are simply unsuited to understand-

ing—what Colin McGinn (1991) calls “cognitive closure.” There are things

about the world that we understand that dogs do not understand. Canine

minds are cognitively closed to those principles. Similarly, once one thinks

about it, it seems utter hubris to suppose that there is nothing about the

world that human minds are cognitively closed to. I think this is a plausible

idea, but what I wish to explore is a fourth alternative: that there may be

features of our cognitive architecture—of the things we do understand in

particular ways—that may themselves lead to disunities between the ways

we understand them; and that minds like ours may be unable to produce a

set of beliefs that is globally consistent or a single comprehensive model of

everything without losing some of the epistemic grip on the world that we

gain through many more localized, idealized models and the beliefs they

license.

12.3 Model-Based Understanding as a Source of Disunity

The basic idea here is fairly straightforward. It is the idea that there are

features of models that have implications for how two models are related

to each other, and sometimes these involve incommensurability, irreduc-

ibility, and inconsistency. Not all combinations of models are fraught with

these problems, but the fact that some are is simply a consequence of the

fact that models are each idealized ways of thinking about particular con-

tent domains that involve particular systematic ways of representing and

reasoning about their target domains. Viewed as a system for representing

and reasoning, a model has a particular formal shape that can be described

by rules. If two models do not represent their targets in the same ways,

they can be incommensurable. Of course, if two models are sufficiently

223 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

incommensurable that their domains do not overlap at all, they cannot

produce contradictions. But if two models do have overlapping domains,

and the formal features of the models are logically incompatible, they can

jointly produce contradictions. And whether one model M

1

can be reduced

to another model M

2

depends on whether M

2

possesses the right resources

on which a construction of M

1

can be based.

While pure mathematics is special in several ways, we can understand

some of the basic issues most clearly by considering it first. Consider two

geometric systems: a two-dimensional Euclidean geometry and Riemann’s

geometry of the surface of a sphere. Each can be described by a system of

axioms and theorems, and indeed they share a substantial number of axi-

oms, differing chiefly with respect to Euclid’s parallel postulate. In Euclid-

ean space, a line stretches indefinitely in two directions, and for any point

P not on a line L, there is exactly one line through P that is parallel to

L—that is, the two lines do not intersect. On the surface of a sphere, the

equivalent of a line is a geodesic, like the earth’s equator. Start at any point

and continue in any direction, and eventually you will return to the point

of origin. There are no parallel lines on the surface of a sphere. (Cartogra-

phers do speak of “parallels,” but they are not really lines as defined in the

system, nor are they parallel in the relevant mathematical sense. To follow

a cartographic “parallel” around a sphere, you would have to orient your

path slightly to the left or the right. And two geodesics—say, the equator

and the Greenwich meridian—intersect at two opposite points.) The paral-

lel postulate is true in Euclid’s geometry but false in Riemann’s. And there

are other differences as well: for example, the sum of the interior angles

of a triangle on the surface of a sphere will always exceed 180 degrees;

the Pythagorean theorem is false in a spherical geometry, as you can

have a triangle with three right angles; and so on. If you reasoned from

premises taken from the two geometries, it would be easy to generate a

contradiction. Neither geometric system can be derived from the other,

and there is no self-consistent third system from which all the axioms

of both can be derived, because to produce the contrary axioms and

theorems, the third system would have to already contain contradictory

assumptions within it.

So here is the first crucial point: any particular model employs a par-

ticular representational system; it allows us to represent the world in some

particular set of ways and not in other ways, and it employs a particular set

of inference rules and not some other set. From this point, several others

follow. First, one model may allow us to represent things or draw infer-

ences that another cannot, and we may need multiple models if we need

224 Chapter 12

the different types of representations and inferences each supplies and we

cannot find a single model that supplies them all together. Second, two

models can turn out to be incommensurable or license incompatible infer-

ences. As we shall see, this is not always as serious a problem as at first

it might appear, because in some cases two models are not aptly applied

to the same situations and hence should not really license contradictory

judgments. But it is still an important source of potential contradictions

and paradoxes. Moreover, models that are incommensurable or license con-

tradictory inferences cannot be reduced to one another or to some third

(internally consistent) model. There is also another reason that one model

M

1

may be irreducible to another model M

2

: if there are types of representa-

tional resources or inference rules in M

1

that are lacking from, and cannot

be constructed from, the resources of M

2

.

What we have arrived at here are the elements for explanations of

various types of disunities of belief and understanding in terms of the fea-

tures of our cognitive architecture. If understanding comes in the form

of models, and each model employs a particular representational system

that is optimized for particular ends, it is quite possible for two or more

models to carve up the world in incompatible ways, to be formally incom-

patible, and to license incompatible inferences. Two models can each

be eminently apt for their own purposes and yet not play well together.

Given the assumption of a model-based cognitive architecture, we should

expect to find such disunities, and the thesis about cognitive architecture

supplies a kind of diagnosis of their source. In some ways, it is a defla-

tionary diagnosis: conflicts in belief or understanding need not imply that

“the world is disunified” (whatever that might mean) but may be artifacts

of the cognitive architecture through which our minds understand the

world.

Yet in another way, this is also a disconcerting insight. It may be that

the disunities we find today are things we can bootstrap our way beyond,

by finding a better set of models that do not conflict in the same ways, and

perhaps even finding a single super model of everything that is self-consis-

tent and allows all the legitimate insights provided by our existing models.

But it could also turn out that this is impossible—that either features of our

cognitive architecture itself or their combination with the particular set of

things we encounter and care about in the world requires multiple models

to provide maximal epistemic and practical traction on the world, and in

some cases these models may, in combination, produce inconsistencies and

paradoxes. If this is the case, certain disunities of belief and understanding

may be principled and abiding for minds like ours.

225 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

The question of whether there are such principled and abiding disuni-

ties, I think, cannot be settled decisively in advance or by purely theoretical

considerations. We cannot know a priori how many independent principles

are at work in the world, and so any intuition that there should be just one

must reflect a cognitive bias. Nor will it do to appeal to an intuition that

“the world must be comprehensive and self-consistent,” because the ques-

tions about unifying belief and understanding depend not solely on how

the world is but on how we are able to understand it, and hence involve

empirical questions about human cognition. On the other hand, the mere

fact that our present ways of understanding the world are disunified in vari-

ous ways does not entail that we cannot achieve better ways of understand-

ing it that are better unified. There is no way of ruling out in advance a

new insight that would change everything, because we could only evaluate

its prospects by knowing what it was, and by definition future insights are

unknown. Whether disunities of belief and understanding are principled

and abiding is ultimately an open-ended empirical question.

So here is a second important point. A model-based architecture for

understanding can (and does) result in de facto disunities of belief and

understanding but does not itself answer the question of whether such dis-

unities are a kind of principled limitation on knowledge or understanding.

It does give us reason to be suspicious of any intuitions we may have to the

effect that there should ultimately be a single, all-encompassing model of

everything, or that we should be able to find ways to reconcile all our con-

flicting beliefs. There is no reason to assume that the evolutionary forces

that shaped our cognitive architecture would have done so in a fashion

that ensures such a capacity. (And even if one believes that there was a

certain amount of special intervention by God in the design of human

minds, there is little reason to think that the design would have included

the capacity to have a fully unified understanding. Perhaps the sense of

mystery engendered by paradoxes that cannot be resolved in this mortal

life is precisely what God was after.)

The only kind of evidence we have on such a question would have to

come from looking at cases. And here we find things that pull us in two

contrary directions. The histories of philosophy of science are filled with

examples of surprising unifications—say, that the things we see in the sky

are not made of a different sort of matter operating on different princi-

ples, and the orbits of the planets and the behavior of falling bodies are

explained by a single principle of gravitation. But they are also filled with

discoveries of new phenomena requiring the postulation of new forces and

other explanatory principles. And there are still deep disunities, both old

226 Chapter 12

and new, that we do not know how to resolve. To name just a few: the

gulf between facts and norms, commitments to competing normative prin-

ciples, the independence of mathematics from nature, wave-particle dual-

ity and other puzzles of quantum theory, and the tensions between it and

relativistic theories of space-time and gravitation.

I began with examples of models of mathematical systems because they

most clearly illustrate ways that the features of models can provide the

basis for disunities of belief and understanding. But there are also impor-

tant issues that we cannot illuminate using mathematical examples. Pure

mathematics is special in that it is not accountable to anything outside the

mathematical system. There are, of course, important questions about what

physical systems each geometry can provide apt representations of, but a

discovery that space is non-Euclidean does not amount to a falsification

of Euclidean geometry. It is simply the system it is. And the fact that two

geometries produce seemingly contradictory pronouncements on things

like the parallel postulate and the Pythagorean theorem does not result in

any deep paradoxes. Mathematically speaking, the parallel postulate and

the Pythagorean theorem are not simply true-full-stop or false-full-stop;

they are true-in-Euclidean-geometry and false-in-spherical-geometry. There

is no further question about their truth, except for corresponding ques-

tions about whether they are true in additional types of geometric systems.

Someone who mixes together incompatible commitments of two systems

in an inference is simply making a blunder.

A different set of issues arises when we apply multiple models to real-

world situations. It is here that issues about the ways the models are ideal-

ized and whether they are aptly applied arise. What makes a model good

for its purpose is that it tracks patterns in the world sufficiently well for that

purpose, and in a fashion that allows us to think, reason, and plan about

situations in the world, and it does so by having a representational system

and a set of implicit rules that do a good-enough job of tracking such pat-

terns. The fact that any given model represents only some things, and in

elegant and comprehensible ways, is what allows it to provide insight into

particular real patterns. Two different models may track different patterns

and may need to represent them in different ways to be elegant and com-

prehensible. But the very features that make each model apt for its given

purpose may present problems when we try to use two models together

to understand a real-world situation to which they both apply. This is a

general and schematic story about a source of disunities of belief and under-

standing. In the ensuing sections, I explore its application to a number of

cases.

227 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

12.4 Scientific Disunity

For approximately the past century, physics has had two highly success-

ful, well-confirmed theories: a relativistic account of gravity and space-time

and a quantum mechanical account of strong, weak, and electromagnetic

forces. One of the major projects in theoretical physics is an attempt to

unite the two into a single theory. It may be that there would be some

physicists who would care about finding a grand unified theory simply

because they found the postulation of two distinct fundamental forces that

require different models to be inelegant or ontologically profligate. But this

cannot be the entire reason that physicists care so much about a grand uni-

fied theory. After all, for a long time, physicists operating within classical

mechanics were quite content with the idea that there are several inde-

pendent fundamental forces—mechanical force, gravity, electromagnetism,

chemical bonding. The difference was that scientists assumed that precisely

because these forces were independent, and all assumed a common Newto-

nian understanding of space and matter, their contributions to a comprehen-

sive and consistent mechanics could be computed through vector algebra.

There were several models of what were thought to be independent funda-

mental forces, but they were not inconsistent, precisely because they were

independent. The problem with relativity and quantum theory is that they

are held to be incompatible with each other. Now, if you look into just how

they are incompatible with each other, you will find an interesting vari-

ety of answers: there are differences in assumptions about renormalization,

local causation, and an absolute or relative temporal frame of reference;

and if you combine the mathematics in special cases like black holes, the

results are either inconsistent or mathematically incoherent. Some of these

concern incompatibilities between the formal features of the two models;

others are about how, when combined, they lead to contradictory predic-

tions or even mathematical nonsense.

It would be foolish to try to predict whether the search for a unified field

theory will be successful. What my cognitivist account does is to supply at

least a partial diagnosis of why such a puzzling situation might arise. We can

gain some perspective on this conundrum if we assume that each supplies

an apt but idealized model. Relativistic gravitation and quantum theory are

each extremely well confirmed, and to an extraordinary degree of accuracy.

For the phenomena to which they are applied, each is a highly apt model.

But what does this mean? It means that particular mathematical descrip-

tions do a very good job of tracking a certain set of empirically robust pat-

terns. It is a marvelous thing that the human mind is capable of coming

228 Chapter 12

up with such models. But to be a concrete model at all, each model must

use some particular representational system (and not some other system).

What gives a model a simple and elegant fit with one set of phenomena

may be an idealization that renders it inapt for others. And the represen-

tational systems that are simple, elegant, and apt for two different sets of

phenomena may be formally inconsistent. It may or may not turn out that

it is possible for us to find either a grand unified theory or two compatible

successor theories that would resolve the problem.

Earlier I quoted Stephen Hawking expressing a growing pessimism about

this prospect. Hawking (along with coauthor Leonard Mlodinow) seems to

have reached a view similar to my own about why we might be faced with

such a situation, in a discussion of what Hawking and Mlodinow (2010) call

“model-dependent realism.”

[Model-dependent realism] is based on the idea that our brains interpret the input

from our sensory organs by making a model of the world. When such a model is

successful at explaining events, we tend to attribute to it, and to the elements and

concepts that constitute it, the quality of reality or absolute truth. (7)

Like the overlapping maps in a Mercator projection, where the ranges of different

versions overlap, they predict the same phenomena. But just as there is no flat map

that is a good representation of the earth’s entire surface, there is no single theory

that is a good representation of observations in all situations. There is no picture- or

theory-independent concept of reality. (42)

It is pointless to ask whether a model is real, only whether it agrees with obser-

vation. If there are two models that both agree with observation, like the goldfish’s

picture (of the world, through the distorted lens of a spherical fishbowl) and ours

(without this lens distortion), then one cannot say that one is more real than the

other. One can use whichever model is more convenient in the situation under con-

sideration. … Model dependent realism applies not only to scientific models but also

to the conscious and subconscious mental models we all create in order to interpret

and understand the everyday world. There is no way to remove the observer—us—

from our perception of the world, which is created though our sensory processing

and through the way we think and reason. Our perception—and hence the observa-

tions upon which our theories are based—is not direct, but rather is shaped by a kind

of lens, the interpretive structure of our human brains. (46)

It might be that to describe the universe, we have to employ different theories

in different situations. Each theory may have its own version of reality, but accord-

ing to model-dependent realism, that is acceptable so long as the theories agree

in their predictions whenever they overlap, that is, whenever they can both be

applied. (117)

Hawking and Mlodinow echo my suggestion that the need for multiple

models might be a consequence of our cognitive architecture. But an

229 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

element in Hawking and Mlodinow’s remarks helps us to see something

else that is also important. Just having multiple models that frame the world

in different ways may be a fairly innocuous consequence of how the human

mind works. Where we really need to pay attention to potential problems

is “whenever they overlap, that is, whenever they can both be applied.” It

is only in those cases that they can give rise to contradictory predictions or

inferences. There are plenty of such cases, but in some of them, cognitive

pluralism can help us see that, at least sometimes, we need not be commit-

ted to contradictory judgments licensed by the models if we attend prop-

erly to the ways the models are idealized and aptly applied.

First, consider an experiment in which a metal object is dropped in prox-

imity to a magnet. If we apply a gravitational model, we will get a descrip-

tion of the resulting motion of the falling object. If we apply a model of

electromagnetism, we will get a different description. They will be different

descriptions; and if either model is used alone, the resulting prediction will

diverge from the real-world behavior observed, because in fact both gravita-

tion and magnetism are at work. There is nothing here that should be all

that surprising. More than one force is at work in most mechanical situa-

tions, and the resultant behavior of objects is influenced by all the forces

at work. There is good reason to have separate models of the forces, both

because they are distinct and separable causal patterns in the world and

because understanding them separately makes them comprehensible to us.

The bracketing idealizations of the models are both psychologically neces-

sary and empirically justified.

In Laws, Mind, and Free Will, I took some empiricist accounts of laws

to task for treating laws (like those of gravity and electromagnetism) as

though they directly license claims about real-world behavior, such as how

bodies will actually move when dropped. If understood this way, the two

laws would have to be seen as entailing conflicting predictions, neither of

which corresponds to the real-world behavior in cases where multiple forces

are at work. Interpreted as universally quantified claims about how bodies

actually behave, the laws would be false. But the source of the error is not

that the laws are false but that they should be interpreted not as universally

quantified claims about actual behavior but rather as idealized claims about

the different forces that are causal contributors to that behavior. The error

in the interpretation of laws is a philosophical error—resulting, I believe,

from an attempt to force scientific laws into a particular logical mold. It is

not an error that any competent scientist or engineer would be likely to

make, though of course the scientist or engineer might overlook a factor that

was in fact causally relevant in a given case. On the other hand, the classical

230 Chapter 12

technique of combining the contributions of separate forces through vec-

tor algebra is applicable only when all the causal contributors in play have

models that are quantified and independent, and this is not the case with

all pairs of models. But really this is a case in which cognitive pluralism

shows us how to resolve an apparent problem. Gravitational and electro-

magnetic models, applied individually and taken as licensing predictions,

do generate inconsistent predictions. But understanding how the models

are idealized should caution us not to take the models as licensing exact

predictions individually, except in cases where only one force is at work,

or the influence of one drowns out the influence of the other within the

degree of accuracy employed.

The situation is different in the case of quantum complementarity.

Wave and particle models represent phenomena differently, and wavelike

behavior is different from particle-like behavior. In classical optics, particle

theories (Newton) and wave theories (Huygens) were assumed to be com-

petitor accounts, and experiments were designed to attempt to settle the

question of which was correct. The underlying assumption was that there

must be a single model that captures the “real nature” of light and can be

applied to all the cases. Classical optics became absorbed into a broader

theory of electromagnetism, and classical electrodynamics was superseded

by quantum theories. But the availability—indeed, the need for—both wave

and particle models persists in quantum theory. In some experimental set-

ups, phenomena are aptly described by wave models, in others by particle

models. This description, however, comes with an important caveat: the

experimental setups are mutually exclusive, and so quantum duality is

not understood in terms of two rival accounts of nature. But neither are

the wave and particle models descriptions of separate forces, like gravity

and magnetism.

Niels Bohr proposed the doctrine of complementarity to account for this

counterintuitive situation. His description of the issues reflects both cogni-

tive and pragmatic elements of his analysis.

However far the [quantum physical] phenomena transcend the scope of classical physical

explanation, the account of all evidence must be expressed in classical terms. The argu-

ment is simply that by the word “experiment” we refer to a situation where we can

tell others what we have done and what we have learned and that, therefore, the ac-

count of the experimental arrangements and of the results of the observations must

be expressed in unambiguous language with suitable application of the terminology

of classical physics.

This crucial point … implies the impossibility of any sharp separation between the

behaviour of atomic objects and the interaction with the measuring instruments which

231 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

serve to define the conditions under which the phenomena appear. … Consequently, evi-

dence obtained under different experimental conditions cannot be comprehended

within a single picture, but must be regarded as complementary in the sense that only

the totality of the phenomena exhausts the possible information about the objects.

(Bohr 1949)

The first paragraph reflects a cognitive constraint, in this case on how evi-

dence is conceived and expressed. The second reflects a pragmatic aspect:

our epistemic access is mediated by measuring instruments, and there is no

“sharp separation between the behavior of atomic objects and the interac-

tion with the measuring instruments which serve to define the conditions

under which the phenomena appear.” This leads to a pluralist conclusion:

Different experimental setups reveal different patterns of behavior, and we

need different models to capture the patterns. If the models were taken

as descriptions that were independent of experimental setups, they would

generate conflicting descriptions and predictions. But in fact, the experi-

mental setups are mutually exclusive, and the results one obtains with

each are stable. I would interpret this as implying something about how

each model is idealized and where it is aptly applied. Treating the mod-

els as unidealized would not only generate conflicting predictions but also

result in an inability to see how we actually have ways of determining with

some surety how matter behaves in the different cases. Conversely, in this

example, properly understanding how the models are idealized, and more

specifically the range of cases in which each can be aptly applied, prevents

the formal incompatibilities of the models from entailing commitments to

contradictory beliefs or predictions about more specific cases.

But there are other cases in the sciences in which multiple models are

used to frame discussions that result in incompatible implications that can-

not be resolved by restricting their apt use to particular experimental con-

texts. A useful example is the ongoing debate within biology about the

proper way to understand species. If we are to believe the developmental

psychologists, folk biology contains an intuitive concept of species that

includes assumptions such as that animals and plants come in species

kinds, individual organisms are produced by parents of the same species,

and members of the same species share characteristic habitats, physiogno-

mies, and diets. The intuitive essentialism of this notion was made explicit

as a philosophical doctrine by Aristotle, who also initiated a project of

understanding species through a taxonomy based on differences in traits,

which culminated in the Linnaean taxonomic system in the late eighteenth

century. Today many biologists and philosophers of biology would see this

type of taxonomic classification as centered on criteria for identification

232 Chapter 12

and differentiation—pragmatic criteria employed by the observer that

are at best contingently related to properties that are salient for a modern

biological classification. Darwin repositioned the notion of species as the

fundamental unit of evolution, and his theory of evolution provided two

notions that have played a central role in more recent concepts of species:

interbreedable populations and common descent. These two notions, how-

ever, have been emphasized and developed in different ways by theorists

in biology, resulting in a number of distinct refinements of the concept of

species. (Mayden [1997], for example, distinguishes no less than twenty-

two different concepts of species in biology.) These may be grouped into

two main traditions.

The first tradition emerged from the “evolutionary synthesis” of system-

atics, genetics, and evolution (Dobzhansky 1937; Mayr 1942). Mayr’s for-

mulation of the “biological species concept” was particularly influential:

[A] species consists of a group of populations which replace each other geographi-

cally or ecologically and of which the neighbouring ones intergrade or interbreed

wherever they are in contact or which are potentially capable of doing so (with one

or more of the populations) in those cases where contact is prevented by geographi-

cal or ecological barriers. …

Species are groups of actually or potentially interbreeding natural populations

which are reproductively isolated from other such groups. (Mayr 1942, 120)

The notion of “reproductive isolation” is key to the biological species

concept. One crucial question separating subsequent developments of

the concept was whether merely extrinsic barriers to interbreeding, such as

geographical separation or ecological barriers like mountain ranges, should

count as differentiating species. Dobzhansky’s definition of “isolating

mechanisms” was sufficiently broad to imply such a conclusion, though

the first quote from Mayr implies the opposite conclusion. The answer

one gives to the question has implications for things such as whether

populations that are temporarily isolated thereby count as separate species,

and (more importantly) whether, if they are later reunited with related

populations with which they interbreed, what were separate species can

then remerge. (Perhaps most strikingly, if merely geographical isolation

can be determinative for species separation, various isolated human

populations were arguably until recently distinct species that have been

reunited into a single species through the availability of long-distance

transportation.)

But perhaps more interesting from the standpoint of biology was the

discovery that in many species, populations that have overlapping habitats

233 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

and are capable of interbreeding in fact do not do so. Isolating mechanisms

(such as the different mating calls used by distinct populations of repro-

ductively compatible birds) seem to be an important factor in speciation,

at least among sexually reproducing species, and models that make such

mechanisms central to the concept of species thus highlight and allow con-

stitutive inferences about real patterns in nature. At the same time, this

emphasis also involves a costly idealization: most organisms do not repro-

duce sexually—there is no such thing as an interbreeding population of

bacteria or fungi—and in other taxa (particularly plants) hybridization also

plays a significant role that is screened out by the biological species concept.

The second tradition, by contrast, emphasizes common descent. The

most influential version of such an approach is the cladistic approach,

based in the notion of a clade, which consists of an ancestor and all its

descendants, living and extinct. (Depending on the details of the specific

cladistic theory, an “ancestor” might be an individual organism, a popula-

tion, or a species.) Cladistic classifications are treelike structures; but unlike

the Linnaean system, they are intended to represent real and evolution-

arily salient relations of lineage and divergence. (Linnaeus, like Aristotle,

assumed species to be unchanging and eternal.) Cladistic classification

produces representations of a hierarchy of taxonomic levels in a treelike

structure, in which a species is a lineage between two branching points. Of

course, most such branchings occurred in the remote past, and so the data

for cladistic analysis must often be drawn from morphological “characters”

reconstructible from fossils, though molecular features of DNA can also be

used for modern specimens and for fossils from which reliable DNA infor-

mation can be obtained. The use of characters as the basis for constructing

cladograms is what allows the cladistic methodology to be extended to the

remote past (something quite important for a classification based on lin-

eage), but there is a great deal of dispute over the choice of relevant and

reliable characters that are diagnostic of lineage and relatedness. (To take a

toy example, using striped fur as a character would result in a biologically

unrealistic analysis of the relatedness of lions, tigers, and zebras.) While the

goal of cladistics analysis is a reconstruction of lineage, using characters as a

basis for taxonomy runs the risk of the resulting system being a classification

system that fails to represent a deeper evolutionary reality.

The distinction between classification systems and biologically signifi-

cant units is often noted in the theoretical literature on species. But atti-

tudes toward this, and implications drawn for the concept of species, differ.

Mayden (1997), for example, excoriates the conflation of merely pragmatic

234 Chapter 12

means to differentiate species with the deeper goals of evolutionary biology

and holds out hope for a species concept that is suitable for the latter:

Much of the turmoil embodied in the species problem ultimately derives from our

packaging inappropriate criteria for species into a single concept. This results from

a traditional conflation of function of concepts with their applications, definitions

with concepts, taxonomic categories with groups, and ontological status of real spe-

cies with teleological approaches to recover them. Analogous to classifications of

supraspecific taxa, our forging inappropriate and ambiguous information relating

to theoretical and operational discussions of species ultimately results in a trade-off

between convenience, accuracy, precision, and the successful recovery of natural

biological diversity. None of these expectations or intentions of species or classifica-

tions is attainable through composite, and possibly discordant, concepts of biologi-

cal diversity or its descent.

With this in mind can one tease apart the theoretical concepts and operational

definitions of species and develop a primary concept applicable to the various enti-

ties believed to be species? I think this is possible through a hierarchical view of

species concepts and their definitions. (Mayden 1997, 383)

Dupré (2001b), by contrast, holds that we should view the concept of spe-

cies in terms of units of classification rather than of evolution:

It is of course possible that the units of evolution could also serve as units of classifi-

cation, and that this is in fact the case seems to be very widely assumed by writers on

the topic. But, and this is the first thesis I shall defend in this paper, units of evolu-

tion are far too diverse a set of entities to provide a useable partition of organisms

into classificatory units. If this is correct we need to decide whether the term species

should be applied to units of evolution or units of classification. And here, if any-

where in biology, it seems to me we should honour conventions of priority. Species

were understood to be basal units of a classificatory system millennia before anyone

had thought to formulate a theory of evolution. And to this day almost everyone

who is not professionally involved in theoretical systematics assumes that the spe-

cies category is a classificatory concept. So I conclude that species should be treated

as units of classification not units of evolution. (Dupré 2001b, 203–204)

Moreover, Dupré notes that classificatory interests, even within biology,

are diverse, leading him to endorse a pluralistic view of classification and

species.

We do, after all, generally classify the objects with which a scientific theory deals in

relation to the demands of that theory. But this argument, even when more thor-

oughly fleshed out, is unconvincing. Classification in biology has a life of its own.

Biologists in areas only tangentially connected to evolutionary theory, such as ecolo-

gists, ethnobotanists, or ethologists, need to classify organisms, as do foresters, con-

servationists, gamekeepers, and herbalists. As will be discussed below, for many, per-

235 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

haps even most groups of organisms, evolutionary considerations are of little or no

use for classificatory purposes. And finally birdwatchers, wildflower enthusiasts, or

just biologically engaged members of the public, may choose to classify organisms,

even if they do not need to do so. These diverse groups of people require workable

classifications that enable them to communicate among themselves and to members

of other such groups, record information about natural history, and so on. If, as I

argue, units of evolution inadequately meet these needs they must be distinguished

from units of classification. Furthermore, it follows that in biology classification and

theory are more autonomous from one another than seems to be the case in most

parts of science. The fact that classification cannot, at least, be closely tied to the

central theory of biology leaves room for the thoroughly pragmatic and pluralistic

approach to biological taxonomy that I shall advocate. (Dupré 2001b, 204)

While I am not in a position to take a stand on whether there is a viable

unitary notion of species, or a variety of such notions, corresponding to the

units of evolution, Dupré’s analysis at the least sheds light on why we find

such a variety of ways of constructing the notion of species, and of classifi-

cations of organisms into species. There are a variety of practical scientific

(and nonscientific) standpoints from which the classification of organisms

is called for, and these call for different ways of conceptualizing species.

This is, moreover, not merely a matter of arbitrary convention or taste:

the different approaches reveal different real patterns in the things studied,

even if which patterns are regarded as salient depends on one’s theoretical

and practical interests. From the standpoint of cognitive pluralism, the fact

that different pursuits—including various scientific pursuits—require us to

adopt different models that cross-classify to bring the various salient pat-

terns to light means that we have a need for a variety of models that are

not fully aligned with one another, which produce different verdicts on the

boundaries of species but are apt for different purposes. And this may well

be a principled and abiding disunity, as the different purposes and salient

patterns may well not prove to be reducible to a single common denomina-

tor. Dupré’s other point—that there is more than one factor relevant to the

“units of evolution”—likewise gives us reason to suspect that we may require

multiple conceptual frameworks to fully understand them separately, and it

may not be possible to compress these into a single model that can serve as

an optimal successor to the intuitive notion of species.

12.5 Irreducibility

I will try, much more briefly, to summarize some potential barriers to inter-

model reduction. One of the most straightforward of these is simply that

236 Chapter 12

the would-be reducing model lacks the formal resources needed for a con-

struction of the model one is seeking to reduce. The most important and

familiar family of cases of this type consists of normative models such as

those involving ethical principles. The familiar adage “you cannot derive

ought from is” may originally have been posed as a claim about deductive

inferences in arguments, but it is equally applicable to the reconstruction

of one model from another. Models suited only to talking about facts and

regularities lack a kind of resource that is distinctive of those models that

can be used to frame normative claims. The latter are not what mathema-

ticians would call a “conservative extension” of the former. To get from a

purely positive to a normative model, you need to add something new. We

find a similar situation with the relationship between modal and nonmodal

logics: whereas it is possible to, say, treat the various logical connectives in

first-order logic as constructions from a single (albeit less intuitive) connec-

tive, it is not possible to construct the modal operators for necessity and

possibility from nonmodal resources. The reasons for this sort of irreduc-

ibility are straightforward, but the implications are significant: whatever

the state of our model(s) of purely positive claims, such as empirical facts

and laws, they cannot provide a sufficient basis for reconstructing the con-

tent of our normative and modal models.

Two of the more familiar philosophical objections to reductionism are

multiple realization and emergence. We speak of multiple realization prin-

cipally when some functionally specified kind—like AND-gate or heart—is

always (or at least often) built out of some physical components, but there

are many physical configurations that could be used to make something

with the same functional description. It may well be that, in each separate

case, the functionally specified system has the functional properties it does

as a result of its physical configuration. But this falls short of a reduction

for two reasons. First, the models used for the realizing system (say, phys-

ics or cellular biology) do not contain the relevant functional concepts.

Given a model containing those concepts and a sufficiently rich physical

or biological description of an individual system, one might be able to

deduce that it was an AND-gate or a heart, but only by way of compar-

ing it with the standards supplied by the functional model. Second, the

physical or biological model does not capture the relevant generalizations

of the functional model: the functional laws do not “pop out” as laws,

and thus, without the functional model, real and salient patterns would

go unrecognized.

Dennett’s case for the independence and need for the intentional stance

seems to involve considerations of both of the aforementioned types. On

237 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

the one hand, in his view, intentionality is a notion tied to rational norms,

and those norms cannot be constructed from physical-stance or design-

stance characterizations. On the other hand, when we adopt the inten-

tional stance, we are able to discern real patterns that would go unnoticed

without it. Those who take a functionalist view of intentionality agree with

something like the second point—that the generalizations of intentional

psychology do not “pop out” of physical or neuroscientific descriptions.

I am inclined to agree with Dennett, however, that our understanding of

intentional states is not purely functional, like our understanding of AND

gates or even hearts. Rather, we have special ways of conceiving of agents

and agency that have their own proprietary concepts, stemming originally

from the core agency system, that cannot be reconstructed in physical or

functional terms.

Arguments for the irreducibility of consciousness proceed along similar

lines. Levine (1983), Jackson (1982), and Nagel (1974) argue that the frame-

works provided by the physical sciences do not provide even candidate

explainers from which we could derive the characteristic features of the

first-person phenomenology of experience. Chalmers (1996) makes things

more explicit: our understanding of the physical world is cast entirely in

terms of structural and functional properties, but neither structural nor

functional properties supply the right sorts of resources for deriving the

qualitative character of experience.

These considerations might suggest that we encounter problems of irre-

ducibility specifically in the case of human phenomena: intentionality,

consciousness, normativity. And perhaps we find special kinds of problems

for reduction here that we do not find elsewhere. However, as I argued in

Beyond Reduction (2007), we find very few true reductions in the natural sci-

ences, either. And at least in some cases, when we look at particular types

of models and their would-be reducers, we can see principled reasons why

this might be so.

The word ‘emergence’ is used to describe a number of supposed rela-

tionships in nature. Here I am concerned with a type of “emergence” that

would consist in phenomena that occur only in systems of a certain size

or certain degree of complexity, whose occurrence and principles cannot

be derived from models of the behavior of their constituent parts. The

level of complexity need not be a very high level of complexity or the size

very great. Indeed, a useful example is found in the fact that atomic-level

properties (e.g., the behavior of electrons in orbitals) and molecular-level

properties (e.g., involving the sharing of electrons) cannot be fully derived

from particle-level properties (e.g., of how free electrons behave). One way

238 Chapter 12

of looking at this, sometimes favored by emergentists, is to say that there

are “new” properties that “emerge” only in complex systems. (And so we

need separate models of all the relevant sorts of complex systems.) This

would pose a problem analogous to the inability to derive the regularities

of functional systems, though it is not a case of multiple realization. It

seems to me that one could also view the problem from a different angle:

that individual electrons do have (dispositional) properties to behave in

particular ways in orbitals, to play roles in molecular bonding, and so on,

but these properties will be screened out in experiments that are performed

on free electrons. From a cognitive standpoint, to obtain a good model of

free electron behavior, we need to bracket other (dispositional) properties

of electrons, and hence the model of free electron behavior is idealized in a

way that prevents derivation of the emergent phenomena. But there is no

reason we could not read the dispositional properties they manifest in par-

ticular complex systems back onto the individual electrons. Yet note that

in so doing, we are not reducing our model of atomic-level phenomena to

models of how the constituent particles behave “on their own,” but rather

building dispositions for atomic-level behavior into our models of particles

in the form of dispositions, capacities, and powers that need to be specified

in higher-level terms.

This, in turn, leads to a broader issue. Some models are “outward look-

ing” in that they assume something about a broader and more encompass-

ing context. Take, for example, a model of an organism that treats it as

embedded in an environment. Such a model may be designed primarily to

bring out features of the organism but treats it as an open system. Perhaps

some of the salient extrinsic variables will be specified but an open-ended

number left unspecified. Moreover, some of the features of the organism

that are thus highlighted will be inseparable from the broader context:

respiration, nutrition, procreation, and being predator or prey cannot be

understood as features of the organism in isolation. Indeed, if you were to

try to reconstruct these notions in terms not centered on the organism as

the canonical level of description, the natural way to do so would be by

moving outward, to a description of a larger and more encompassing system,

defined at a higher level of organization, rather than by microexplanation.

Reductive microexplanation is thus a strategy ill suited to capturing the

generalizations or explanatory power of such models, because what they

depend on is a larger and more complex, rather than a smaller, system.

Likewise, the biological species concept and cladistic concepts of species

are defined in terms of actual and possible interbreeding relations in popu-

lations and of historical lineages, respectively. These concepts cannot be

240 Chapter 12

model is more powerful than acquiring individual beliefs because models,

while confined to particular content domains, are nonetheless systematic.

Models provide ways of representing and reasoning about any number of

states of affairs within their domains. The range of models available to us

is further expanded through their complementary relationship with lan-

guage and language-like thinking, by social transmission, and by more regi-

mented processes of inquiry such as those found in philosophical analysis

and the sciences. These allow us not only to create new models, but also to

refine existing models, to consider and use multiple models, and to test one

model against another.

On the other hand, the very features that make this strategy so power-

ful—that models are used to frame and produce judgments, that model-

based inference methods are well suited to their domains, and above all

that models are idealized and employ particular types of representations

and inference rules—can also result in disunities in understanding and

belief. Most obviously, just having multiple models is itself a modest form

of disunity. More troubling is that models with different representational

systems and inference rules can produce inconsistent beliefs and judg-

ments. And this offends a second epistemic sensibility: a desire that the

things we understand and believe be consistent with one another.

A model-based architecture for understanding is characterized by a built-

in tension between comprehensiveness and consistency. We acquire more

comprehensive understanding first and foremost through having more

models, but the addition of each new model carries the risk of generating

more inconsistencies with the commitments of other models. Sometimes,

of course, apparent inconsistencies turn out to be illusory: two models may

have incompatible commitments, but these imply inconsistent judgments

about the world only in cases where both models are aptly applied to the

same situations. In cases like quantum complementarity, it turns out that

the conflicting models are aptly applied to disjoint sets of cases and as a

result do not commit us to inconsistent judgments about particular cases.

And sometimes we are able to resolve the problem by replacing one or both

models with one or more successors that do not jointly produce inconsis-

tent judgments. Our drive to resolve conflicts and inconsistencies provides

a kind of regulative norm for both philosophy and science. But there is no

guarantee that it can be carried out to its ideal conclusion, whether in the

form of a single comprehensive and self-consistent model or at least a set of

distinct models that play well together.

What should we do when faced with a trade-off between comprehen-

siveness and consistency, beyond hoping for a better day? One way of

241 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

eliminating inconsistency, of course, would be to simply stop using one of

the models that plays a role in producing it. But in practice, both in science

and in ordinary life, we in fact seem to care more about understanding as

many things as possible than we do about having a single model or even

eliminating paradoxes. Thus, to quote Hawking and Mlodinow, we counte-

nance the possibility that “it might be that to describe the universe, we have

to employ different theories in different situations” (Hawking and Mlodi-

now 2010, 117; italics mine). Outside of science, we are probably even more

comfortable having different ways of understanding situations that work

for us, are less likely to be aware of the discordances between them, and are

troubled only when the discord is brought to our attention—and perhaps

even then only to the extent that we are philosophically inclined. When

push comes to shove, comprehensiveness generally trumps consistency: we

care more about having good-enough ways of understanding and dealing

with a variety of situations than about how well all that understanding

and all those beliefs hang together as a whole. We need understanding, and

hence the models that supply it. Consistency is something we want—and

some care about it more than others—but it is not something we need.

But in what sense do we need understanding? In one sense, this might

simply mean we have a strong internal drive for it. And it is easy to see why

such a drive would be biologically adaptive: the more about our environ-

ment we understand, the more we can deal with in adaptive ways. What

Hawking and Mlodinow seem to have in mind, however, is something

slightly different: we “need” multiple scientific models if we are to explain

all the data. Most human beings have gotten on quite well without any

understanding of the phenomena that make up the subject matter of con-

temporary physics—we do not need it in a biological sense—but one of the

effects of human cognitive evolution is that our potential range of inter-

ests has expanded well beyond “interests” in the biological sense. But the

“need” here is still a kind of pragmatic need: we need a model M if we are to

understand (and be able to intervene on) X.

Of course, the range of things we have interests in understanding and

acting on goes well beyond science. And in many cases, the goal of a

theoretical understanding that covers all the data, which looms large for

a theoretical physicist like Hawking, is either far less important or lack-

ing altogether. Philosophers working in metaethics care about the merits

of various metaethical theories—consequentialist, deontological, virtue

theoretic—and as a consequence they are interested at a theoretical level

in the fact that these theories can produce contradictory evaluations of

which actions are morally praiseworthy, and interested in questions about

242 Chapter 12

whether one can be reduced to another or whether one can decisively be

shown superior to the others. But the metaethical theories are themselves

likely grounded in ways of evaluating persons and actions that are part of

the developmentally normal cognitive tool kit. We quite naturally evaluate

actions in terms of their costs and benefits, regard people as having duties

that they fulfill or shirk, and attribute character traits that we admire or

despise. Sometimes we are perplexed when we find that different means of

evaluation lead us to opposing conclusions about which people or actions

are good. And a given individual might habitually use one mode of evalu-

ation in preference to the others. But even when faced with conflicting

intuitions, we probably seldom even consider the possibility of giving up a

mode of moral evaluation. Each of them provides insights that the others

cannot, and though these may be quite unlike the explanation of scientific

data, a similar principle is at work: that, when push comes to shove, we are

willing to pay the price of perplexity or paradox rather than lose a useful

and powerful tool for insight.

This, moreover, may point to a different kind of “necessity”: there may

be some kinds of models that we are in some sense psychologically inca-

pable of giving up. Modes of ethical evaluation and perhaps an assumption

of freedom that is implicit in some of them might fall into this class, as

might assumptions about a world of classical objects in space and time, and

models of causation and teleology. It is not that people—or at least some

people—cannot conceive of alternatives and even endorse them at a theo-

retical level. Some people can and do regard classical objects, causation,

teleology, free will, and ethical properties as illusions or even as nonsense.

But this does not mean that these theoretical commitments prevent them

from forming judgments, or at least candidate judgments, on the basis of

deeply entrenched models that assume them. At best, it may allow them

to reflectively disavow the truth of the judgments or the aptness of the

models. Note, though, that this too reflects a kind of disunity if, in making

or being disposed toward such judgments, one treats them as true and the

models as apt but reflectively disavows them.

And while the situation is most striking when it involves models that

operate automatically and perhaps even ubiquitously, it also appears in a

lesser form whenever we employ models about which we have reservations

or we know to have limitations. Being an academician, for example, has

provided me with no small number of occasions to become aware of the

limitations of my understanding of particular topics, and the even greater

limitations of the simpler models of those topics that I try to convey in my

courses. In my course on early modern philosophy, for example, I present

243 Disunities of Knowledge, Science, and Understanding

stories about figures like Descartes, Hume, and Kant. I try to avoid say-

ing anything truly false but know full well that I leave out things that are

ultimately important: for example, saying that Descartes equated matter

with extension and hence matter has its properties necessarily leaves out

other features of the Cartesian system such as the role of divine choice in

deciding how matter would be divided into particles and even in decid-

ing what the truths of logic and mathematics should be. I also know just

enough about the scholarship on such issues to recognize that I do not fully

understand how they fit together in Descartes’s thought. (And, as my fellow

philosophers have no doubt experienced for themselves, saying anything,

particularly anything critical, about Kant in a professional context risks

having any Kant scholars in the audience explaining many things I do not

understand about Kant’s philosophy.) I use mental models of the thought

and works of other philosophers in my thinking, teaching, and writing, but

at the same time I am aware that these models are not fully adequate. And,

of course, this goes for any number of nonphilosophical topics as well.

This is, perhaps, a kind of expression of the Socratic virtue of knowing

what you do not know (or understand). It strikes me that anyone who has

developed this intellectual virtue is always in something like the position of

the advocate of a mild form of negative theology. The strong form of nega-

tive theology says that our concepts are so unsuited to talking about God

that we can say nothing true about God and perhaps ought not to try. The

milder form says that all our theological claims must be hedged: “This, but

not quite this, and much more as well.” I think that a proper appreciation

of the idealized and perspectival character of understanding based in men-

tal models should lead us to adopt a similar attitude much more broadly.

We make claims using the models we have—what alternative do we have

beyond a principled silence? But we also know that the resources of those

models are limited, some in ways we understand, and no doubt others in

ways that we do not. To the extent that the model is apt, we count as true

the best ways we have of expressing what can be said using its resources.

But we should be reluctant to say that it is the truth, the whole truth, or

nothing but the truth.

246 Chapter 13

intuitive claims was the parallel postulate: that for any line L and point P

not on L, there is exactly one line passing through P that is parallel to L.

The founders of non-Euclidean geometries, however, recognized that the

parallel postulate could be denied without self-contradiction, and various

alternatives to it would result in distinct alternative geometries. Euclid’s

parallel postulate may seem as though it must be true, but the reason for

that is to be found not in the definitions and axioms of the system or the

principle of noncontradiction but in a separate set of “spatial intuitions”

to which the human mind is strongly biased. This discovery caused a crisis

in mathematics, spawning the formalist movement, which sought to find

ways of reconstructing mathematical systems in terms not dependent on

mathematical intuitions.

In contemporary philosophy, appeals to “intuitions” are often used

to justify important claims. In metaphysics, claims about what is neces-

sary and what is possible—things that go beyond what could be settled

by empirical experimentation—are often explicitly grounded in “modal

intuitions”: for example, that there could be a being that was a molecule-

for-molecule duplicate of you but lacked conscious experience (Chalmers

1996). In ethics, not only claims that some particular action is good or evil,

but also fundamental claims such as that human beings have natural rights,

are justified by appeals to intuitions. However, unlike mathematical intu-

itions, which tend to be about things that everyone, or at least the experts,

agree on, appeals to intuitions in contemporary metaphysics and ethics are

often precisely about matters that people have different intuitions about.

For some, what seems intuitively obvious is that a molecular duplicate of

a person would have to have all the same mental states, and Jeremy Ben-

tham famously quipped that the notion of natural and inalienable rights is

“nonsense on stilts.”

Intuitions, in the sense of judgments that are not reached on the basis

of explicit reasoning from something else yet strike us as clearly true (and

hence not requiring further justification), are by no means the sole prov-

ince of mathematicians and philosophers. We think intuitively all the time

in daily life. Indeed, if you were to monitor the judgments you make on an

average day, you would probably find that most of them were not reached

through any kind of argumentation or reasoning (or at least not any you

could detect). Much of the time, intuitive judgments are nonetheless quite

dependable. In fact, when you think about it, any reasoning you do engage

in has to start with some set of assumptions that serve as the premises from

which you derive the conclusion. The conclusion is derived through rea-

soning from the premises, but on what basis did you believe the premises?

248 Chapter 13

process” or “dual system theories.” One of the main figures working in this

area, Daniel Kahneman, writing with Shane Frederick, summarizes:

The ancient idea that cognitive processes can be partitioned into two main fami-

lies—traditionally called intuition and reason—is now widely embraced under the

general label of dual-process theories. … Dual-process models come in many flavors,

but all distinguish cognitive operations that are quick and associative from others

that are slow and rule-governed. … We adopt the generic labels System 1 and System

2 from Stanovich and West. These terms may suggest the image of autonomous

homunculi, but such a meaning is not intended. We use systems as a label for col-

lections of processes that are distinguished by their speed, controllability, and the

contents on which they operate. (Kahneman and Frederick 2002, 51)

The quote shows that the notion of “dual systems” really indicates two

classes of processes, differentiated in terms of their speed and controllabil-

ity. There might be numerous more specific processes sharing the System

1 profile, which presumably might operate through different mechanisms.

In spite of our tendency to disparage intuition by contrast to deliberate

reasoning, System 1 reasoning can be very good at what it does, and is

recognized as an important feature of expertise, the acquisition of which

involves the transition from System 2 to System 1 processes. Kahneman

and Frederick continue:

Although System 1 is more primitive than System 2, it is not necessarily less ca-

pable. On the contrary, complex cognitive operations eventually migrate from

System 2 to System 1 as proficiency and skill are acquired. A striking demonstra-

tion of the intelligence of System 1 is the ability of chess masters to perceive

the strength or weakness of chess positions instantly. For those experts, pattern

matching has replaced effortful serial processing. Similarly, prolonged cultural ex-

posure eventually produces a facility for social judgments—for example, an ability

to recognize quickly that “a man whose dull writing is occasionally enlivened by

corny puns” is more similar to a stereotypical computer programmer than to a ste-

reotypical accountant. In the particular dual-process model we assume, System 1

quickly proposes intuitive answers to judgment problems as they arise, and System

2 monitors the quality of these proposals, which it may endorse, correct, or over-

ride. The judgments that are eventually expressed are called intuitive if they retain

the hypothesized initial proposal without much modification. The roles of the two

systems in determining stated judgments depend on features of the task and of

the individual, including the time available for deliberation …, the respondent’s

mood …, intelligence …, and exposure to statistical thinking. … We assume that

System 1 and System 2 can be active concurrently, that automatic and controlled

cognitive operations compete for the control of overt responses, and that deliber-

ate judgments are likely to remain anchored on initial impressions. (Kahneman

and Frederick 2002, 51)

249 Models and Intuition

In the latter part of this quote, Kahneman and Frederick seem to assign to

System 2 processes only a kind of monitoring function. I think this would

be an overstatement, as we are also capable of using regimented reasoning

processes like application of logical syllogisms or rules of column addition

in a deliberately controlled way to produce judgments, and explicit reason-

ing allows us to derive conclusions we are unable to reach through System

1 thinking. But my main reason for introducing the foregoing quotes is

to provide perspective on how some psychologists think about intuitive

reasoning: it is a kind of thinking that occurs rapidly, automatically, and

through processes that are often skilled yet “opaque”—that is, cognitively

impenetrable.

Other psychologists speak of concepts and judgments as being intuitive

or counterintuitive. In cognitive science of religion, Paul Bloom (2004,

2007) claims that both children and adults are “intuitive dualists.” Pas-

cal Boyer and Justin Barrett, by contrast, claim that supernatural concepts

like those of immaterial souls and ghosts are “minimally counterintuitive”

(Boyer 2001; Barrett 2004a, 2004b, 2009). Calling a judgment or a concept

“intuitive” here seems to mean that it is “intuitively recommended”—that

is, seemingly true, plausible, or, in the case of concepts, unproblematic.

‘Counterintuitive’ seems to mean the opposite of this: a counterintuitive

judgment or concept is one that comes with an internal sense that there

must be something peculiar about it.

These references to contemporary psychology, however, do not tell us

much that we did not know before. Beyond the important claim that exper-

tise is characteristically exercised through intuitive processes, they largely

just confirm the distinctions we have already developed. The claim that

intuitive processes are “automatic” amounts to little more than the claim

that they are not the kind of processes found in explicit reasoning, in which

we can control and monitor the steps. The fact that they are fast—that is,

fast by contrast with methodical explicit reasoning—may be no more than a

consequence of the fact that the latter sort of process is slow and labori-

ous. Moreover, intuitive processes do not always seem to be fast: the devel-

opment of a creative idea or an intellectual insight might require a great

deal of time. When I reach an impasse in writing, I often do something

else—take a walk or sleep on it—allowing unconscious parts of my mind to

work on the problem. Sometimes it is a matter of hours, days, or months

before an answer pops into my awareness. Of course, precisely because the

process is unconscious, it is difficult to determine just when it is at work

or how long it takes. It may be that the actual process takes milliseconds

and happens just before I am aware of the outcome. Or it may be that some

251 Models and Intuition

act in a goal-directed fashion and that people act on the basis of their beliefs

and desires are fundamental principles of these models. We use such mod-

els automatically and routinely; and to use the models at all is to constitute

things as agents with goals or with beliefs and desires. You cannot consti-

tute something as an action without imputing goals, beliefs, or desires. You

can reject the aptness of the model for particular cases and assent to the use

of another interpretive framework instead—it was a patellar reflex and not

a deliberate kick, it was an animatronic robot following a program—but in

so doing, you reject not only the beliefs and desires but the applicability of

the whole framework of imputing agency at all. A candidate judgment that

violates these rules triggers a particular type of cognitive dissonance with

the model, and this is experienced as its being counterintuitive. A judg-

ment that expresses the content of the rules is quickly and unconsciously

confirmed as being an implication of the model, is experienced as being

intuitively recommended, and can be produced by some mechanism that

translates the implicit rules of the model into propositional form or con-

firmed by a mechanism that compares the propositional expression with

the rules of the model. Judgments like “agents have goals” seem like neces-

sary truths, perhaps even platitudes, because to think or talk about agency

at all, one must be using a model that imputes goals, beliefs, or desires.

Indeed, there are clear senses in which they are necessary truths. “Agents

have goals” is something like an implicit axiom of models of agency, and

hence is true-in-agency-models in much the way the parallel postulate is

true-in-Euclidean-geometry. To use agency models at all, one must treat

things constituted as agents as things that act to achieve their goals, and in

order for the constitution of something as an agent to be apt, the imputa-

tion of goals to it must be apt as well.

Similar things can be said about the intuitive representation of objects in

space. To represent something as being in space, one must represent it in a

fashion that assumes that there is space on all sides of it. (Of course, “space”

is said in a proprietary sense here, corresponding to a geometrically defined

space, not as “empty space.” If someone says, “There is no space to the left of

the cabinet,” because the left side of the cabinet is flush against a wall, they

mean there is no empty space, not that the wall exists outside space.) This

seems to be a basic feature of the model (or a set of models) we use to repre-

sent objects in space. As a consequence, the question “Is there (geometric)

space to the left of it?” seems absurd to ask, as the answer is a straightfor-

ward consequence of basic principles of the model and hence, from the

standpoint of someone working within the model, should go without say-

ing. The assertion “There is nothing to the left of it, not even empty space,”

252 Chapter 13

is highly counterintuitive, because you have to use a spatial model to

make sense of it at all, yet what is asserted violates the implicit rules of

the model.

In some cases, we may be unable to form a representation of the candi-

date content within the model at all. Our spatial intuitions may be unable

to accommodate a representation of a three-dimensional space that curves

back on itself like the two-dimensional surface of a sphere. We can con-

ceive of such things through other means—say, mathematically—but they

seem abidingly counterintuitive because they are dissonant with a deeply

ingrained model of spatial geometry that is more or less Euclidean. Likewise

there is a way in which ways of thinking about things for which I do not

already have a model are bound to seem counterintuitive—that is, they

seem counterintuitive at least until I acquire and master the model. The

pronouncements of contemporary science often seem baffling, nonsensi-

cal, or even plainly impossible at first. They lose something of this air once

we master the scientific model in which they are couched, and may even

seem routine and obvious to the practicing scientist when she is using the

requisite models.

The examples of agential and spatial representation both involve models

that are deeply canalized and difficult to disengage. But similar points can

be made about the intuitiveness of judgments that state basic principles

of models whose use is more voluntary. Within the game of chess, it goes

without saying that each piece in play must occupy a single square on the

board. Indeed, within the model of the game, there is no such thing as a

location halfway between spaces. Of course, we are perfectly capable, using

other means, of seeing pieces as straddling two spaces. We can refuse to

interpret them in terms of the chess model at all, or we can wonder which

space an awkwardly positioned piece is “in” for purposes of the game, or we

can interpret it as being in a particular space for purposes of the game. To

not interpret it as being in a particular space is to not interpret it as being

in play in a game of chess at all.

This strikes me as slightly different from the manner in which I intui-

tively see that the bishop can move forward one or two spaces on the right

forward diagonal or can move a third space, capturing the opponent’s pawn.

If I am even a mildly proficient chess player, I simply see these possibilities

and do not need to do any explicit reasoning to discover them. The ques-

tion “How did you know that?” would be puzzling, unless perhaps asked by

someone who does not know the movement rules for chess. The movement

possibilities pop out for me because they are consequences of the implicit

rules (in this case, permissive rules for movement) in my mental model of

253 Models and Intuition

chess, and these permissive rules guide me in recognizing possible moves

within the game. Conversely, if someone moves the bishop along a row

or column, or moves it off the board entirely, this will immediately cause

the type of cognitive dissonance associated with the counterintuitive.

Presumably some unconscious mechanism linked to the model detects a

violation of the model’s rules, and the rule violation is flagged with this par-

ticular phenomenology. It is then impossible to keep operating smoothly

within the model; and to make sense of what my opponent has done at

all, I must reframe it outside the chess model: he is trying to annoy me,

perhaps, or is a child who has lost patience with the game and is just hors-

ing around.

Another type of intuitive process might involve a simulation—say, a sim-

ulation of what would happen in the game if I tried a particular strategy.

This uses the internalized rules of the model to produce a series of represen-

tations of board states, or perhaps a representation of how a strategy is likely

to unfold. Here the internalized rules guide the dynamics of the simulation

process. Similarly, when I imagine the rotation of a solid, the rules of the

model I employ for spatial reasoning generate a simulation, producing an

intuition about the end result. I may well regard the result with confidence,

as it is produced by the rules of the model.

Another type of intuitive process is what is often called “semantic infer-

ence.” Many things seem intuitively obvious about dogs, even if we have not

thought about them before: dogs are animals, carnivores, quadrupeds, and

mortal; dogs have hair, hearts, kidneys, and emotions; dogs are offspring

of other (pairs of) dogs; and so on. We would correspondingly find other

claims counterintuitive: dogs are vegetables, vegetarians, bipeds, immortal,

or robots; dogs have scales, gills, or opinions on philosophical issues; dogs

are created on engineers’ workbenches, are made of fire, or have parents

that are fish; some dogs have masses greater than that of the earth; and so

on. Some of the intuitively obvious claims might have been learned and

stored as facts about dogs, perhaps even appearing in part of a definition or

characterization of dogs you learned; but many of them are things you are

unlikely ever to have thought of before, and yet they are intuitively obvi-

ous. Why might this be so? An answer that recommends itself is that the

concept

DOG either is itself, or is part of, a kind of richly structured semantic

entity that affords a rich set of inferences that go beyond the judgments

that have previously been formed.

Pascal Boyer (2001) suggests that species concepts like

DOG are formed

on the basis of a highest-order concept that is a constitutive part of folk

biology, which he characterizes as the “ontological category”

ANIMAL. Boyer

254 Chapter 13

likens concepts to note cards in an internal database and sees ontological

categories as templates for such note cards that specify both category-gen-

eral assumptions (e.g., animals are mortal and the offspring of same-species

parents) and blank “slots” for other information to be filled in on a species-

level basis, such as characteristic physiognomy, diet, habitat, and so on.

When confronted with a new type of animal, we form a new database entry

on the basis of the

ANIMAL category. This leads us to assume that the species

will have some characteristic physiognomy, diet, and so on, which guides us

in a search for what information needs to be acquired to fill in the blanks.

As we fill them in, we have an increasingly richly specified set of assump-

tions about that species, drawn from the “entry” for the species, the onto-

logical category, and any levels (e.g.,

MAMMAL) lying in between.

The information thus “encoded” need not ever have been a part of

an explicit judgment. At some point, I pieced together a set of assump-

tions about the internal organs—hearts, kidneys, and so on—I expect to

typically find in some superordinate class of animals, and these are either

“written into” my model of dogs or else linked with it in a fashion I can

readily exploit. Others may be built into my mental model of dogs through

experience: I observe what dogs eat, and encode the assumption that they

eat meat into the model even if I never think a thought with the content

“dogs are carnivores.” Unless prompted, I may never form a judgment on

questions such as whether dogs have kidneys, are carnivores, are mortal, or

are the offspring of other dogs. But once I am prompted, the answer can

be “read off” the mental model. The judgment is intuitively produced by

being (somehow) read off what is already present in the model in a non-

propositional form, and is intuitively recommended because it is a product

of what is already present in the model.

Boyer develops his theory of concepts in Religion Explained to suggest

that concepts of supernatural beings that figure in religious belief are pro-

duced by starting with a familiar ontological category (or one of its subor-

dinate concepts) and then violating one of the rules—say, a concept of an

immortal dog or a dog that can transform into a human being. These con-

cepts are “counterintuitive” because they violate rules of the ontological

category—say, that animals are mortal, are each members of a single species

kind, or have a (constant) physiognomy. Boyer suggests that supernatural

concepts are special because they (a) violate rules at the category (rather

than the species) level and (b) violate just one rule. But ideas that violate

rules at the species level (e.g., a six-legged dog or a dog without a heart) or

more than one rule (a six-legged dog without a heart) would also be coun-

terintuitive for the same general reason.

257 Models and Intuition

13.4 Models, Intuitions, and Expertise

This model-based account of intuitions can also explain why discussions of

intuition often include expert judgment as intuitive. One way that expert

performance differs from novice performance on a task is that novices con-

sciously think through problems in an explicit, stepwise fashion, whereas

experts often report that “the right answer” simply pops out for them

quickly and effortlessly. Dreyfus and Dreyfus (1992), for example, contrast

the novice and the expert in the following way:

The student automobile driver learns to recognize such interpretation-free features

as speed (indicated by his speedometer). Timing of gear shifts is specified in terms

of speed. The novice chess player learns a numerical value for each type of piece

regardless of its position, and the rule: “Always exchange if the total value of pieces

captured exceeds the value of pieces lost.” But such rigid rules often fail to work. A

loaded car stalls on a hill; a beginner in chess falls for every sacrifice. (Dreyfus and

Dreyfus 1992, 114)

The expert driver, generally without any attention, not only knows by feel and famil-

iarity when an action such as slowing down is required; he knows how to perform

the action without calculating and comparing alternatives. He shifts gears when ap-

propriate with no awareness of his acts. On the off ramp his foot simply lifts off the

accelerator. What must be done, simply is done.

The expert chess player, classed as an international master or grandmaster, in

most situations experiences a compelling sense of the issue and the best move. Ex-

cellent chess players can play at the rate of 5–10 seconds a move and even faster

without any serious degradation in performance. At this speed they must depend

almost entirely on intuition and hardly at all on analysis and comparison of alterna-

tives. We recently performed an experiment in which an international master, Julio

Kaplan, was required rapidly to add numbers presented to him audibly at the rate of

about one number per second, while at the same time playing five-second-a-move

chess against a slightly weaker, but master level, player. Even with his analytical

mind completely occupied by adding numbers, Kaplan more than held his own

against the master in a series of games. Deprived of the time necessary to solve prob-

lems or construct plans, Kaplan still produced fluid and strategic play.

It seems that beginners make judgments using strict rules and features, but that

with talent and a great deal of involved experience the beginner develops into an ex-

pert who sees intuitively what to do without applying rules and making judgments

at all. The intellectualist tradition has given an accurate description of the beginner

and of the expert facing an unfamiliar situation, but normally an expert does not de-

liberate. He does not reason. He does not even act deliberately. He simply spontane-

ously does what has normally worked and, naturally, it normally works. (116–117)

259 Models and Intuition

in this chapter would suggest that (1) the information was already avail-

able, albeit in nonpropositional form, in the structure of a model; and (2)

there are fast-operating unconscious processes available that can (a) pro-

duce a judgment with that content and (b) if presented with the candi-

date judgment, confirm it as implied by the implicit rules of the model.

If beliefs are dispositions that are grounded in stable features of models

plus mechanisms that produce or confirm judgments in a noninferential

manner based on their content when prompted, we have a characteriza-

tion of beliefs that grounds a form of psychological realism but is not com-

mitted to the thesis that dispositional beliefs are sentence-like entities in

the mind.

Moreover, we can also explain the fact that imputations of belief are

also imputations of normative commitments: beliefs of the type I have

described are implied by the implicit rules of their models of origin, and

hence one is normatively committed to them when one is using the model.

Of course, different models have different commitments, and those of one

model may conflict with those of another. This would seem to imply that

we have conflicting dispositional beliefs in such cases. But this is actually

potentially a point in favor of the account. Numerous psychological stud-

ies have shown that the judgments we are disposed to make are highly

subject to context and priming. So it will not do to simply characterize

beliefs as dispositions to judgments without further qualification. More-

over, contexts do not simply magically produce changes in disposition.

We need some way of connecting different contexts with the different

judgments they evoke. One plausible way of doing this is to suppose that

context and priming activate particular models, and as a result, one is

biased toward producing the judgments that are commitments of those

models and not others.

Not all dispositions to form judgments work in this way. The timid per-

son is disposed to judge himself in danger. In a sixty-degree room, I am in

some sense disposed to judge that it is a bit chilly. These dispositions are

probably not based in mental models. But by the same token, it is not clear

that we should think of them as involving beliefs, either. The timid person

has a low trigger point for judgments of danger, as well as for various types

of vigilance, but it strikes me as more appropriate to say that he is always on

the lookout for danger and ready to impute it than that he always believes

himself in danger. Nonetheless it may be that cases exist in which we would

attribute beliefs that cannot be explained on the basis of the implicit com-

mitments of models, and so the hypothesis should be taken as an explana-

tion for at least one class of belief attributions.

263 Cognitive Illusion

experimentalist and would surely have felt compelled to recognize the

problems Young’s experiment presented for his theory had it been devel-

oped within his lifetime. Yet we can well imagine that had he been posed

with the question of how light would behave if shined through two slits

in a partition, Newton would confidently have predicted a result based in

his particle theory. What the particle model would predict if applied to the

situation is fairly straightforward: particles, moving in straight lines, should

result in two bands of light corresponding to the two slits. Indeed, between

the evidence from other types of experiments and the fact that the idea that

light travels in straight lines appeals to common sense (no doubt rooted in

some folk model), Newton might well have assumed that light would have

to go through the slits in straight lines and produce two bands of light on

the opposite wall. But this is not what actually happens. Instead the setup

produces a diffusion pattern of the sort one might expect if light behaved

like a wave.

At the least, the experiment shows that Newton’s corpuscular model

cannot aptly be applied in cases like the slit experiment. Just what it shows

beyond this is complicated by the fact that Newton had in fact devised

experiments of his own whose results seem compatible with a particle

model but not a wave model. And for this reason, classical optics was beset

with a puzzle, as some experimental results suggested one model and oth-

ers another, incompatible model. Without a model that made sense of all

the experiments, no one was really in a good position to claim decisively

that light is either a wave or a particle phenomenon. There were two mod-

els, each of which could aptly be applied to predict results in certain types

of situations but not in others. Moreover, each model produced intuitive

anticipations of what should happen in each context—indeed, what must

happen if light behaves as the model characterizes it. Someone presented

for the first time with experimental results contrary to the intuitive antici-

pations of the model he was using might well be astonished by them (as

many of us are the first time we encounter Young’s experiment) and feel a

need to replicate it for himself. Indeed, even having known of the two-slit

experiment for a long time, I still sometimes find the results counterintui-

tive, in spite of knowing that they are well confirmed.

To take another scientific example, in fluid dynamics, different models

are applied depending on factors such as temperature, friction, viscosity,

compression, and whether flow is laminar or turbulent. The Euler equations

present a comparatively mathematically simple model that can elegantly

be applied to many problems, and are viewed as useful simplifications of

the Navier-Stokes equations. But as Mark Wilson writes, “These frictionless

264 Chapter 14

simplifications display a wide variety of counterintuitive consequences—

viz., airplane wings should experience neither drag nor lift (leading many

nineteenth century experts to glumly predict the impossibility of heavier

than air flight)” (Wilson 2006, 186). The Euler equations are apt for predict-

ing many types of fluid motion and capture important invariants. But they

are also idealized, and in cases where the idealizations matter (such as the

lift on an airplane wing), the model cannot aptly be applied, at least with-

out being supplemented by additional models, in this case Ludwig Prandtl’s

boundary layer. Applying the model inaptly can lead to false predictions

such as the impossibility of heavier-than-air flight. Before Prandtl’s discov-

ery of the boundary layer in 1904, we can well imagine that fluid dynami-

cists, applying the models they had, might confidently conclude that air

flight was impossible, because that conclusion was implied by the models they

had to work with. Of course, one can also apply a model inaptly even if one

already has the wherewithal to know that it is not aptly applied there.

If we assume that (1) models can give rise to intuitions about what will

or even must be the case, (2) models are idealized in ways that render them

apt only under certain conditions, and (3) we do not always know where a

model is aptly applied and may even be unaware that there are restrictions

on its apt application, then we should expect that there would be cognitive

illusions that arise when a model is applied inaptly but we are unaware of

the inaptness. And such unawareness can arise in several ways: as a simple

mistake (we know the conditions for apt application but forget that a par-

ticular case lies outside them), out of ignorance that a particular case is of

a type that lies outside the conditions, or out of a deeper naïveté about the

idealized character of models in general or about the particular model we

are using.

Discussions of “cognitive illusions” in psychology are principally con-

cerned with inapt applications of models. Consider Deborah Kelemen’s

notion of “promiscuous teleology.” Teleological thinking is a common fea-

ture of maturationally normal human minds. It is also found in very young

children, perhaps predating causal explanation. While scientifically tutored

adults tend to reserve teleological explanations for artifacts and (perhaps

with some qualms and hedging) for organisms, Kelemen’s research points

to a developmental pattern in which children at first apply teleological

models much more broadly, and in preference to causal models.

Despite similarities between teleological-functional intuitions in young children and

adults, young Western-educated children reason in teleological-functional terms

about a broader variety of phenomena than do Western-educated adults. In addition

to biological parts and artifacts, they view non-biological natural kinds and their

265 Cognitive Illusion

properties as existing “for” purposes—a finding that has implications for proposals

that teleological reasoning in young children is selective and is the earliest form of

thought that is specifically biological. (Kelemen 1999, 461)

Frank Keil (1992) had proposed that humans have an innate system for

teleological explanations linked to biological thinking. Kelemen’s evidence

that young children show a bias toward applying teleological reasoning to

things they understand to be nonliving seems to belie this hypothesis, and

so Kelemen hypothesizes that a system for teleological reasoning may be

developed on the basis of an earlier-appearing system for understanding

intentional agents.

Experiences that suggest objects exist in the world to fulfill the purposes of agents

might subsequently contribute to the tendency to over-generate purpose-based te-

leological explanations when faced with explanatory gaps. In other words, later on,

in the absence of other explanations, children might draw on their privileged knowl-

edge of intentions and artifacts to conclude that, like artifacts, natural objects exist

in the world because some agent put them there for a purpose. (Kelemen 1999, 466)

If we assume, with Kelemen, that the application of a teleological model to

things other than organisms and artifacts is inapt, promiscuous teleology is

a case of a bias to overgeneralize the applicability of a model in inapt ways,

and subsequent learning about science that is ubiquitous in Western edu-

cation narrows the range of cases in which teleological framing is applied.

This range narrowing may well be a by-product of particular types of educa-

tion and enculturation, without which we should expect to find animistic

tendencies in adult populations. This seems to be the view taken by Guth-

rie (2002), who additionally ascribes “animistic” thinking to nonhuman

animals and describes it as “illusion”: “The attribution of characteristics of

animacy to the nonliving and to plants appears widespread among com-

plex organisms. Because illusion is an inevitable concomitant of percep-

tion, such attribution may be universal” (53).

A second example: In chapter 13, I mentioned research on heuristics and

biases pioneered by Kahneman and Tversky (1973). Research in this tradi-

tion has identified a number of types of cases in which reasoning about

statistical problems deviates from optimal Bayesian reasoning about prob-

abilities. Scientists often regard these deviations as errors in reasoning and

sometimes describe them as “cognitive illusions.” In a critical reply, Giger-

enzer describes Kahneman and Tversky’s program in the following terms:

Kahneman and Tversky (1973) describe the gist of their view as follows: “In mak-

ing predictions and judgments under uncertainty, people do not appear to follow

the calculus of chance or the statistical theory of prediction. Instead, they rely on

266 Chapter 14

a limited number of heuristics which sometimes yield reasonable judgments and

sometimes lead to severe and systematic errors” (p. 237). They see the study of sys-

tematic errors in probabilistic reasoning, also called “cognitive illusions,” as similar

to that of visual illusions. “The presence of an error of judgment is demonstrated by

comparing people’s responses either with an established fact (e.g., that the two lines

are equal in length) or with an accepted rule of arithmetic, logic, or statistics” (Kahn-

eman & Tversky, 1982, p. 493). Their distinction between “correct” and “erroneous”

judgments under uncertainty has been echoed by many social psychologists: “We

follow conventional practice by using the term ‘normative’ to describe the use of a

rule when there is a consensus among formal scientists that the rule is appropriate

for the particular problem” (Nisbett & Ross, 1980, p. 13). (Gigerenzer 1991, 2)

The word illusion is used here in a sense suggesting an error, either in the

outcome of the judgment or in the choice of a heuristic unsuitable to the

problem because it differs from a statistical norm. This is readily translated

into the framework we have been developing, as Kahneman and Tversky’s

explanations of the errors in fact invoke mental models:

Many adults do not have generally valid intuitions corresponding to the law of large

numbers, the role of base rates in Bayesian inference, or the principle of regressive

prediction. But it is simply not the case that every problem to which these rules are

relevant will be answered incorrectly, or that the rules cannot appear compelling in

particular contexts. The properties that make formally equivalent problems easy or

hard to solve appear to be related to the mental models, or schemas, that the prob-

lems evoke. (Kahneman and Tversky 1982, 129–130)

In our terminology, the diagnosis of the errors would seem to be that sub-

jects frame the problem with which they are presented using a model that

is not apt for that problem, and derive an answer using heuristics associ-

ated with the model. Gigerenzer likewise appeals to “probabilistic mental

models” as a general framework for explaining people’s confidence in their

general knowledge (Gigerenzer, Hoffrage, and Kleinbölting 1999).

What seem to be primarily at issue between Gigerenzer and Kahneman

and Tversky are (a) the latter’s use of judgments of professional statisti-

cians as a normative standard for determining when the results of heuris-

tic methods are erroneous and (b) the extent to which the heuristics that

people routinely use are truly inapt, and hence whether the results are truly

“illusory.” These differences are not relevant to our topic here, as we are

concerned with epistemic rather than alethetic illusions, and so what is at

issue is not whether the resulting judgments are correct but merely that we

confidently assume them to be known. What is germane is a conception of

how the mind—or more specifically the application of particular models

to particular problems—can generate cognitive illusions. Reasoning under

267 Cognitive Illusion

uncertainty—with incomplete or unreliable information, or information

that is itself in the form of probability distributions—is a situation that we

routinely face. Even formal techniques like the use of Bayesian methods do

not ensure correct predictions, and such techniques require much learn-

ing and (being of recent invention) were unavailable throughout most of

the history of the species. Using Bayesian analytic methods also requires

possessing a model that incorporates them; but the use of what Gigeren-

zer calls “fast and frugal heuristics” is often necessary and, in many cases,

produces as good or even better results (Gigerenzer, Todd, and the ABC

Research Group 1999). But it is particularly clear in the case of reasoning

under uncertainty that which models and heuristics are apt for a given case

will depend crucially on details of the case and the information available to

the reasoner. Using a model that is inapt for framing a problem is likely to

produce an erroneous assessment.

Of course, this kind of case illustrates that it is often difficult or even

impossible to know for certain whether a given model can aptly be applied

to a particular situation, at least in part because the limited information

involved may prevent us from knowing what kind of situation it is. The

kind of “error” involved may often not be one where we “should have

known better.” The inaptness is ultimately determined by external stan-

dards, though we can also learn a great deal about different models and

what kinds of situations they are aptly and inaptly applied to. When we

do not actually possess an apt model and can only apply the models we do

possess, we may be subject to a weak form of forced error. (It is a weak form

in that it is forced only by the de facto lack of an apt model, as opposed to

the stronger cases in which we are incapable of having an apt model or in

which the use of an inapt model is automatic and cannot be interrupted or

overridden.)

Note, however, that the mere fact that I apply an inapt model that results

in an error is not itself sufficient to make the result count as an illusion.

There are, after all, different ways of applying models. At one end of the

spectrum, I might uncritically assume that the model frames the situation

adequately, and completely trust the resulting judgment, as in the case of

the intuitive judgments described in chapter 13. This would indeed seem

to merit the label “illusion.” At the other end of the spectrum, however, I

might be reflectively uncertain about what would provide an apt model of

a situation, and try out one or more models tentatively and experimentally.

I might refrain from endorsing the output of the model in the form of a

judgment at all, and if it is not a judgment, it cannot be an illusory judg-

ment. Or I might endorse the judgment within the scope of a reflective

269 Cognitive Illusion

drifted into epistemic and alethetic illusion: if you turn an idealized model

into a perfectly universal claim, it may still seem like knowledge if you do

not recognize that the idealization and the intuitive force are still present,

and as a perfectly universal claim it is erroneous. Not all dogs do have four

legs, and not everything people do is a result of their beliefs and desires.

While the production of cognitive illusions is in itself always lamen-

table, the mechanisms that produce them are arguably grounded in fur-

ther features of our cognitive architecture, which confer distinct cognitive

advantages. I will discuss two of these features: intuitive essentialism and

the augmentation of understanding through explicit rules or principles.

Intuitive Essentialism

A good deal of psychological evidence indicates that, even as young chil-

dren, human beings are “intuitive essentialists”—that is, in dividing the

world into kinds, we tacitly assume those kinds to have hidden inner

natures that are responsible for their characteristic observable properties

and behavior. In an article reviewing research on essentialist thinking in

early childhood (including preschool children), Susan Gelman writes:

Essentialism is the view that certain categories have an underlying reality or true

nature that one cannot observe directly but that gives an object its identity, and

is responsible for other similarities that category members share. In the domain of

biology, an essence would be whatever quality remains unchanging as an organ-

ism grows, reproduces, and undergoes morphological transformations (baby to man;

caterpillar to butterfly). In the domain of chemistry, an essence would be whatever

quality remains unchanging as a substance changes shape, size, or state (from solid

to liquid to gas).

Essentialist accounts have been proposed and discussed for thousands of years,

extending back at least to Plato’s cave allegory in The Republic. Numerous fields,

including biology, philosophy, linguistics, literary criticism, and psychology, stake

claims about essentialism. Here we are concerned with essentialism as a psychologi-

cal claim. Although there are serious problems with essentialism as a metaphysical

doctrine, recent psychological studies converge to suggest that essentialism is a rea-

soning heuristic that is readily available to both children and adults. This article

reviews such evidence, and discusses the implications for human concepts. (Gelman

2004, 404)

Psychological essentialism is arguably a deep principle of how children

think and learn about the world. It is not simply that children impute par-

ticular features to kinds of things—say, to species—as essential properties;

rather, they expect kinds (or at least some types of kinds) to have essences,

even if they do not know what those essences might be.

270 Chapter 14

Medin and Ortony (1989) suggest that essentialism is a “placeholder” notion: one

can believe that a category possesses an essence without knowing what the essence

is. For example, a child might believe that there exist deep, non-visible differences

between males and females, but have no idea just what those differences are. The

essence placeholder would imply that categories permit rich inductive inferences,

capture underlying structure (in the form of causal and other non-obvious proper-

ties), have innate potential, and have sharp and immutable boundaries. (Gelman

2004, 404)

Essentialism is an implicit feature of how children think about the world.

(The question of how psychological essentialism is affected by further

learning into adulthood is a topic of greater debate, though it seems clear

enough that essentialist biases continue to operate in some fashion.) But

it is also expressed in generalizations: “lions are carnivores,” “women

are nurturers,” “Germans are strict.” The surface form of the generaliza-

tion admits many fine-grained interpretations; but when it expresses an

essentialist assumption, it imputes a trait as something internal to the

nature of the kind. As the examples show, the “kinds” to which such

thinking might be applied are not necessarily restricted to scientific kinds

like species.

Essentialist generalizations can be produced as a result of experience but

can also be transmitted socially through language. Essentialist thinking is

a powerful inductive tool. Making essentialist generalizations explicit can

also be a powerful tool (see the next section) and also makes them available

for social transmission. Of course, essentialist thinking about subcategories

of human beings is notoriously present in social bias and prejudice, and so

the benefits of a powerful tool for learning and categorization clearly come

with serious cost and risk. This, however, helps to illustrate some of the

types of errors to which essentialist thinking is prone. Even if some kinds

of things are aptly thought about in some contexts as having essences (or

essential properties), we may think about other kinds of things in essential-

ist terms inaptly. And even if there are some kinds that can aptly be imputed

essential properties, we may mistake the wrong properties as essential or

mistake whatever “essentialness” amounts to for universality. If species have

essences, being quadrapedal may be essential to dogs, but not all dogs have

four legs. Female mammals may possess biological features that make them

more likely to manifest nurturing traits, but the expression of these traits

depends on other variables, and there are men and women at both ends of

the range of nurturing behavior.

Various kinds of essentialism have, of course, played significant roles

in the history of philosophy. Aristotelian philosophy may be the most

272 Chapter 14

not be a way of exactly spelling out where the generalization is and is not

aptly applied.

Again, in one way all of this is both intelligible and useful from a psy-

chological standpoint. To the extent that we are ever to learn when a prin-

ciple is and is not aptly applied, we first have to learn the principle and

try to apply it. And this requires that learning the principle be dissociable

from mastering the conditions for its aptness. This opens the gates to inapt

application to particular cases, as discussed in the previous section. But the

unqualified form of the principle also allows it to be interpreted as a per-

fectly universal and unidealized claim.

Mistaking a generalization for a universal claim can, of course, result in

epistemic illusion: the intuitive force of the general claim may still be pres-

ent, but it has been covertly turned into a different sort of claim. (Whether

it is also an alethetic illusion depends on the nonpsychological facts of

whether the content of the judgment is true.) That “Xs are Ys” is a useful

rule of thumb in some unspecified range of contexts by no means ensures

the truth of “All Xs are Ys.” And when we (perhaps unwittingly) transform

a useful generalization grounded in a model that is often apt into a univer-

sal claim, we may still feel the intuitive force of the generalization, not real-

izing that it has illicitly been transferred to an unsubstantiated universal

claim, and hence fall prey to a cognitive illusion.

But the mind’s tendency to elide from general to universal claims can

also be the beginning of a fruitful kind of dialectical process of inductive

testing. “Xs are Ys” is probably too vague to test at all. “All Xs are Ys” can

be tested, often by first being contested, and most claims of this form turn

out to be false. But the dissonance between the intuitive appeal of the gen-

eral claim and the proven falsity of the universal claim drives the mind

to look for a more adequate exact formulation. This is, in fact, one of the

predominant methods we see at work in philosophical discussion. A thesis

may first be proposed on the basis of seeming to be an apt way of viewing

things based on a small set of paradigm examples. The thesis is proposed as

a universal claim (often in the form of putatively necessary and sufficient

conditions), and either the theorist herself or other philosophers then test

it by considering possible counterexamples. Often the account is modified

to accommodate counterexamples and subjected to a further round of criti-

cism, and so on.

From this perspective, I think we can see some of the familiar weak-

nesses and strengths of this approach to philosophy. On the one hand, it is

hardly a new observation that many philosophical theories were motivated

by what in retrospect might seem a woefully small set of paradigm cases.

273 Cognitive Illusion

From the outside, it might seem puzzling how anyone could seriously have

believed theories such as that all thoughts are images or that everything peo-

ple do is done on the basis of rational calculation involving their beliefs and

desires. The corresponding general claims, like “thoughts are images” or

“people decide what to do on the basis of their beliefs and desires,” might

be plausible and useful within some more restricted scope and might be

tied to models that are indeed apt for understanding something. But the

universal claims do not have good inductive support, and one would be led

to very different conclusions if one started from different paradigm cases.

That anyone could have thought the universal claims plausible suggests

that they were victims of a cognitive illusion that involved losing sight of

the restricted scope of the general claim. This type of interpretation is often

offered as a criticism of a theorist and his reasoning process. But it only

really works as a criticism if we assume that the process of finding good

inductive generalizations works by first assembling all the evidence and

then drawing a conclusion from it. Viewed as a dialectical process, often

involving multiple participants playing the roles of defender and critic,

the process of proposing a universal claim based on a restricted range of

cases and then subjecting it to critique by counterexamples can in principle

work quite well, even if in other cases it ends up being unproductive, fal-

sifying the universal claim but offering nothing constructive in its place.

What is perhaps more abidingly peculiar from an epistemic standpoint is

that professional philosophers who adopt the role of advocating a particu-

lar theory in such dialectic often seem to also feel committed to the theory

being true, even when they are aware of poignant counterexamples. I sus-

pect that the roots of the commitment are really to be found in a com-

mitment to an underlying model being apt for understanding a particular

range of cases.

One important question for further empirical investigation is whether

the formulation of generalizations within the resources of ordinary language

facilitates the production of illusions. It is not that we cannot devise careful

uses of language that include explicit hedges indicating the idealization of

the models underlying generalizations or employ more formal logical tools.

Indeed, whole schools of philosophy have been devoted to “correcting” the

vagueness and ambiguity of ordinary language. The interesting question,

rather, is whether some of the structures of ordinary language, like “Xs are

Ys,” lose information that was present in purely model-based understanding

before it was transmuted into language—for example, whether we are more

prone to forgetting the idealization conditions of a model we are reasoning

with when we express it in language in the form of a general claim.

275 Cognitive Illusion

knowledge with what could be experienced and confirmed through sensory

experience.)

One basic difference between my cognitive pluralism and Kant’s philos-

ophy is that my theory locates much of understanding as arising from ide-

alized domain-specific models rather than from sentence-sized judgments

and arguments composed of such judgments. We have seen that there are

ways that the idealization of models can result in a kind of epistemic dis-

unity. I have speculated that sometimes there are incompatibilities between

apt models that are principled and enduring, but I have also endorsed

attempts to reconcile incompatibilities as a regulative principle. And it is

clear that attending to problems that are signaled by having incompatible

ways of understanding things often produces intellectual advances, such as

corrections to models we have previously used, discoveries of better mod-

els (sometimes ones that cover the domains of two preexisting models),

and second-order ways of conceiving the relationships between models,

such as seeing one as a limiting case of another. Sorting out such problems

differs from sorting out inconsistencies between propositions or trying to

unify propositions into a more comprehensive system without attending

to models. By the same token, the ways we try to unify models can lead to

types of illusion that are not apparent if we attend only to propositions and

arguments.

The most basic such illusion is perhaps to assume that all the things that

we justifiably believe on the basis of apt models should be consistent with

one another. Consistency is, after all, a norm of logic. And it is an extremely

powerful norm, as it gives rise to a strong intuitive assumption that two

inconsistent claims cannot both be true. But we now have several reasons

to look past this compelling intuitive assumption.

To begin with, the norm of consistency is a norm for sentence-sized

units: propositions, judgments, beliefs, claims, assertions, sentences. The

introduction of models as a different type of cognitive unit—one that is in

some ways prior to sentence-sized units, as it is models that define a space of

possible propositional representations—complicates matters. What “consis-

tency” means when comparing two models is different from what it means

in comparing two propositions. Euclidean and non-Euclidean geometries

are inconsistent with each other, but this does not mean that at least one

of them is false. Indeed, it makes no sense to speak of a pure mathematical

system being “false,” or of a pure mathematical claim being either true-

full-stop or false-full-stop. Mathematical systems simply are the systems

they are, and the truth of a pure mathematical claim like the Pythagorean

theorem is truth-in-a-system. When models are applied to the empirical

276 Chapter 14

world, there can be formal inconsistencies between their rules and repre-

sentational systems, but this need not constrain us to endorse contradic-

tory propositions, for reasons explored in chapter 12. Some unificatory

projects—such as those involving intertheoretic reduction—have as their

aim relations between models. But even to the extent that we endorse the

principle of noncontradiction for propositions, this gives us no reason to

expect that all apt models should be formally consistent.

Of course, the discussion of disunity also included the observation that

while there are clear cases in which a proper understanding of how par-

ticular models are idealized prevents their committing us to contradictory

beliefs (e.g., in pure mathematical models and cases like quantum com-

plementarity), there are probably many more cases where models frame

matters in alternative ways that seem to be contradictory without the pos-

sibility of any decisive experimental technique for deciding when each is

aptly applied. Nonetheless there can be other ways in which they differ

with respect to aptness. For example, consequentialist, deontological, and

virtue-theoretic models may differ in their assessments of goodness in vari-

ous cases, with no decisive way to arbitrate between them, and yet still

differ with respect to what insights they afford that might prove useful in

moral deliberation and assessment. The norm of consistency indeed gives

us reason for dialectical engagement in such cases, but it is not the only

norm to which we are beholden. Even if our concern is only with theoreti-

cal understanding, there may be other regulative principles as well—such

as having good ways of understanding as many things as possible—which

may pull in opposite directions, and the extent to which any regulative

principle can be fulfilled completely by a given mind depends on empirical

facts about that mind’s cognitive architecture. It is an epistemic illusion to

assume that a given mind must be capable of fulfilling a regulative prin-

ciple, much less fulfilling all of them simultaneously.

Second, we have various strategies for unifying models into a form that

is more comprehensive. A number of these strategies have been developed

in mathematics and the sciences. One family is called “reductionist” and,

in its purest form, involves the axiomatic reconstruction of one domain of

understanding in terms of another (e.g., the derivation of arithmetic from

set theory, or the attempts to show that the special sciences can be derived

from physics). A second is to unify two apparently disparate domains as

special cases of something more general (the most historically important

example is perhaps Newton’s unification of planetary orbits and terrestrial

ballistics in a single theory of universal gravitation). A third and distinct

strategy is to show that one model is a limiting case of another (a paradigm

277 Cognitive Illusion

example would be the claim that the classical universe is a limiting case of

the relativistic universe).

1

A fourth, characteristic of Newton’s approach to

mechanics, is to attempt to view different models as expressing indepen-

dent factors that can be recombined (in Newtonian mechanics, through

vector algebra) to get a global picture. There is also a family of strategies,

which I hesitate to call “unifying,” that we might label “contextual” or

“relativistic.” Their basic approach is to say that different models allow us

to say true things, but in a fashion hedged by contexts. I pick these examples

out because they are familiar and important, but I do not wish to suggest

that this list is exhaustive. Indeed, I regard the list of unifying strategies

as open-ended, as there may be unifying strategies that have not yet been

recognized.

Each of these strategies has arguably been successfully applied to resolve

particular problem cases. What is striking from the standpoint of intellec-

tual history, however, is the confidence with which a particular strategy

has often been endorsed, along with a picture of how things would look

if it could successfully be applied, well in advance of a serious attempt to

apply it. This is, to my mind, particularly striking in the case of reductionist

strategies. Pre-Socratic philosophers seem to have been remarkably confi-

dent that everything must be composed of one of the “prime elements”

of earth, air, fire, water, or aether, though they differed over which one.

Pythagoreans shared a similar confidence that everything was ultimately

numbers. Early modern materialists and some of the twentieth-century log-

ical empiricists had a similar confidence that the special sciences could be

reduced to basic physics, and early proponents who had little scientific evi-

dence to go on (like Hobbes) were no less confident than those who came

after. Indeed, the intuitive appeal of reductionism seems to endure even in

the face of strong arguments from philosophers of science that true inter-

theoretic reductions are rare (Horst 2007). Hobbes and Descartes also

seemed to have had a further ambition of seeing physical properties as ulti-

mately geometric in nature. And many contemporary theoretical physicists

seem to regard the prospect of a unified field theory as something that must

be true.

Chapter 12 explored some reasons why such confidence might in fact

be ill justified. But we might also ask the equally interesting question:

Why would such views recommend themselves to the mind as intuitively

appealing, perhaps even as things that must be true? I think that a plausible

answer is a variant on Kant’s general story about the drive toward unifica-

tion and its propensity to foster cognitive illusion. The mind has a drive to

unify not only its beliefs but the models it uses. There are various strategies

282 Chapter 14

and knowable through synthetic a priori reasoning, because the mind is

constrained to apply the categories to all possible objects of experience.

Cognitive pluralism, of course, is also a cognitivist philosophy. Discus-

sion of its possible metaphysical implications will have to wait for another

book, but clearly there are important questions to be answered about matters

such as its relationship to realism and idealism. I shall confine myself here

to a brief discussion of the question of projective illusion. Because aptness

is ultimately a pragmatic matter, the fact that object-oriented cognition and

schemas for causation are features of our cognitive architecture that provide

basic ways of understanding the world does not debar them from counting

as apt. Indeed, to the extent that models that allow us to constitute a world

of objects standing in causal relations provide good epistemic and practical

traction upon the world, this renders them apt. But to this we should add

two important caveats. First, contemporary science, unlike the science of

Kant’s day, includes models that posit phenomena that resist characteriza-

tion as classical objects. To the extent that the mind strives to force these

into the mold of notions of objects or causation, this may well be a process

that can produce cognitive illusions. Second, when we move beyond the

application of models in ordinary cognition and empirically constrained

science and attempt to think about substance and causation as fundamen-

tal metaphysical categories, we may well move beyond the realms in which

they are aptly applied. In particular, if we adopt the naive realist stance that

treats such categories as mind-independent ways the world divides itself up,

we indeed fall into something akin to projective illusion.

284 Chapter 15

The chapter is divided into two parts. The first considers the implica-

tions of a model-based view of understanding for epistemology, on the

assumption that knowledge is warranted true belief. What is the relation-

ship between models and beliefs? What role do models play in the war-

rant of beliefs and hence their status as knowledge? Are models themselves

things that can be warranted? The second examines the implications of

cognitive pluralism for three influential theories of knowledge: foundation-

alism, coherentism, and reliabilism.

15.1 What Are Beliefs?

Back in chapter 2, I made a terminological decision to speak of occurrent

states involving endorsement of propositional content as judgments. Such

states have sometimes been called “occurrent beliefs” as well, a terminol-

ogy generally used in contradistinction to “dispositional beliefs.” I further

decided to use the term ‘belief’ broadly, to include both judgments and dis-

positional beliefs, whatever the latter might turn out to be. In subsequent

discussions of intuition and cognitive illusion, I concentrated principally

on the notion of judgment rather than that of belief, because those chap-

ters dealt with the production of occurrent states from models. We can

and will discuss the question of how judgments are warranted; however,

epistemologists do not generally confine their discussions of knowledge to

occurrent states but employ a notion of belief that encompasses both occur-

rent and dispositional beliefs. In this chapter we will thus need to discuss

the relationship in which models stand to beliefs as well as to judgments.

I touched on this topic in chapter 13, in conjunction with a discussion of

intuition. Here I take it up again in the context of accounts of beliefs and

other intentional states.

As a first step, I would like to explore how mental models might shed

further light on the psychological underpinnings of what we describe as

beliefs. To begin, let us reconsider several ways of understanding what we

are doing when we ascribe beliefs.

1. Intentional realism: Belief ascriptions in general involve attributions of

mental representations. A statement of the form “S believes P” can be

true only if S has a mental representation with the content P. In this

account, all beliefs are occurrent states like judgments, though they

may not be conscious states and might be represented in ways (e.g., in

cognitively impenetrable subsystems) that cannot be brought to con-

scious awareness. Such an assumption seems necessary for cases in

286 Chapter 15

P as well. Again, this is a framework for understanding belief attribution

(in this case, as holding accountable and scorekeeping [Brandom 1998])

without a psychological story about the basis for the commitments and

inference rules.

5. Sellars’s myth of Jones: In saying “S believes P” we are hypothesizing some

kind of inner state that we conceptualize by analogy with S making an

assertion that P. The supposition that we conceive of inner states by

analogy with assertions involves a kind of agnosticism about the real

psychological nature of the states attributed.

We thus have one proposal (intentional realism) that makes a claim about

the psychological nature of beliefs (but one that is implausible for many

perfectly ordinary belief attributions) and a range of proposals that make

claims about what we are doing in attributing beliefs, and set constraints

on a psychologically realistic account of beliefs without supplying such

an account. Clearly what we should want here is a psychological proposal

that can account for our dispositions to form judgments, the success of the

intentional strategy, the possession of normative commitments, and the

analogy between beliefs and assertions. Mental models help provide such

an account.

First, if we are disposed to judge—quickly, automatically, and confi-

dently—that dogs have kidneys and 117 + 8 = 125, on what basis are we so

disposed? Our discussion of intuitive judgments suggests that, at least in a

wide variety of such cases, the disposition is rooted in the possession of a

mental model containing resources that can generate the judgment with-

out explicit reasoning. I have never before considered whether dogs have

kidneys; but to do so, all I need to do is consult some kind of inner model of

typical animal physiology, and the judgment pops out. I have never added

these two numbers before (or if I have, the result is forgotten), but I have

mastered a model for adding integers, and when I plug these particular

addends into it, the answer pops out. (Note that if we adjusted the example

so that the addends exceeded performance limits—say, twenty-digit num-

bers—your answer to the “do you believe …” question might well be “I

don’t know,” at least until you worked the problem out with pencil and

paper or a calculator.)

It is also natural to speak of facts such as that dogs have kidneys as com-

mitments of models if they are somehow contained in, or implied by, the

models’ rules, representational systems, or data structures. To use language

from AI and theoretical cognitive science, if I have a model of animal physi-

ology that contains a node for kidneys linked to the root node as a default

287 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

feature, or a production rule that generates a representation with the con-

tent “… has kidneys” to things to which the model is applied, then by using

the model and treating it as apt, I am normatively committed to such infer-

ences, even if I do not actually perform them. If the model is apt, there is

also a second kind of normativity: it is an inference that one should make,

because the inferential pattern tracks a real pattern.

We saw in chapter 12, however, that different models involve differ-

ent, and sometimes conflicting, commitments. If we are committed to the

implications of our models—whether their general commitments or the

implications of their application to particular cases—it would thus seem

that we would turn out to be committed to conflicting beliefs as well. This

may initially seem like a problem, but really it is something we should want

a psychological account of belief to imply or at least accommodate. On the

one hand, a wealth of psychological studies show that our judgments are

quite sensitive to context and priming. A natural explanation of this is that

different contexts and priming conditions activate different models, gener-

ating one set of judgments rather than another depending on which model

is activated. On the other hand, we often find ourselves inclined, even after

much reflection, to endorse two propositions we know to be contradictory

when each is intuitively recommended by a model and we are not in a

position to see why one model is inapt or otherwise to adjudicate between

them. It is not clear that the fact that we have paradoxical sets of beliefs

should itself be regarded as paradoxical. But if it is, we seem to gain some

resolution by understanding that the situation is not one of simultaneously

and assuredly endorsing both P and not-P, but one of feeling the pull of the

conflicting implications of two models to which we are committed.

If the phenomenon we call “believing P” amounts to having a model

that can readily generate a judgment with the content P in an appropriate

evoking context in which the model is treated as apt, and we encode this

in the locution “S believes P,” clearly information is lost in the transla-

tion. Here we see the wisdom behind Dennett’s and Sellars’s cautions. Belief

ascriptions look like reports of assertions, and it is tempting to assume that

what is reported must, like an assertion, be propositional and episodic. But

really it is dispositional and normative. It may be a disposition to produce

a certain type of episode—a judgment—but its nature must be understood

in terms of the dynamics of models, and models are not judgments or other

sentence-sized units, and the processes by which they produce judgments

are not logical argument forms operating on sentence-sized units. More-

over, the analogy with assertions may tempt us to suppose that beliefs,

or at least judgments, must take place in a language-like medium. But

288 Chapter 15

models have their own resources for representing particular states of affairs.

Linguistic beings like ourselves can readily transpose many (though not

all) of these into language and language-like thought, but this is some-

thing in addition to a model-based representation. If we assume, on the

basis of how we report it, that it must be structurally language-like, we are

likely to be mistaken. Some, but not all, judgments are made or transposed

into language or language-like thought. Some, but not all, beliefs are also

judgments.

On my view, the intentional strategy is itself typified by a model—one

for interpreting the behavior of agents. Or perhaps better, the intentional

strategy may be a feature of any number of more particular models (the

core agency system, folk psychology, and more specialized models erected

on the scaffolding these provide) for interpreting agents. It may well be

that it does so, as Sellars suggests, by characterizing agents as though their

behavior were driven by language-like inner states. Like any model, this

sort of model is idealized and answers to a number of pragmatic factors

for its aptness. It is particularly apt in cases in which there are psycho-

logical processes involving language-like representations—including, but

not limited to, thinking and reasoning in a natural language. It distorts

its target more when there are model-based judgments that are not trans-

posed into language or language-like thinking, but it can still latch onto

psychologically real episodes even if it (mistakenly) treats them as though

they were in a language-like medium. It also provides ways of talking about

dispositions and normative commitments based in model-based thinking,

though it does so in a fashion that provides no insight into their format

or dynamics. The real patterns it tracks are emergent from an underlying

model-based dynamics. In my view, it is features of these dynamics that are

its real target—a form of psychological realism that is not a realism about

sentence-like representations.

But the strategy can also be applied, with varying degrees of success, to

systems that lack the same model-based dynamics. In the limiting case, we

can say things such as “the thermostat believed it was too cool and switched

on the furnace.” Statements of this kind can allow us to attain some degree

of predictive success even while greatly distorting the way we represent the

system we are predicting. For Dennett, predictive success would seem to be

the only measure of aptness. For me, it is one among several, and I would

insist on a richer analysis of how an intentional strategy model is and is not

aptly applied to a range of cases instead of a simple prediction-based crite-

rion for what is a “true believer.” In my view, the intentional strategy aims

at tracking a particular type of target phenomenon—a form of cognition

289 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

shared by humans and an indefinite number of nonhuman species. It can

be apt for predicting the behavior of other types of systems, but when we

use it for such purposes, we must remind ourselves that we are in effect tak-

ing a model of one target and using it as a model of another.

This approach seems particularly helpful in interpreting ascriptions of

beliefs to nonhuman animals. If we suppose that language and language-

like thinking are uniquely human, and attributions of beliefs ascribe disposi-

tions to form language-like occurrent states, it would seem that nonhuman

animals cannot really have beliefs. On the other hand, ascribing beliefs

to a dog does not seem peculiar in the same ways that ascribing beliefs to

thermostats does. We can make some sense of this, however, if we recognize

that many nonhuman species do have some sorts of mental models, even if

they are not able to form models of many of the things we can, and even if

their models are surely different in their details from ours. Describing their

beliefs in a fashion analogous to reporting human speech involves more of

a distortion of the real psychological content of their mental states, because

they do not have dispositions to make judgments in linguistic form. But

in ascribing beliefs to them, we are nonetheless referring to inner states of

the same kind that we refer to when we ascribe dispositional beliefs to one

another: to dispositions grounded in the models they possess.

15.2 Models as Epistemic Units

Cashing out the notion of belief in terms of mental models provides a first,

but relatively weak, connection to epistemology. In this section, I argue

that there are also more robust connections: models are sources of warrant

for beliefs and judgments, models are themselves epistemically evaluable,

and the fact that models are integral units not reducible to beliefs requires

that epistemology accommodate model-sized units.

Models as a Source of Warrant

I have claimed that models are generative, in the sense that possessing a

model endows a person with a space of possible representations that can

be framed in terms of that model. Judgments about particular situations

are formed by applying a model that is used to frame the situation, and

the resulting judgment is drawn from the space of possible representations

generated by the model. (Of course, we can additionally combine represen-

tations drawn from multiple framing models using the more ecumenical

representational medium of language, but these ultimately derive much

of their semantic content from the models employed.) The fact that a

290 Chapter 15

judgment is framed within a particular model also connects it to the infer-

ential resources of the model: to constitute something as a chess bishop is

to take it to be something that can move diagonally, be captured, capture

other pieces, and so on.

We now need to explore the epistemological implications of the relation-

ship between models and judgments. The basic idea that I will develop here

is a kind of reliabilist thesis: that models are reliable mechanisms for the

production of knowledge in the contexts in which they are aptly applied.

If this is the case, then at least part of what warrants many judgments is

something about the models used to frame them, in which case mental

models are of fundamental importance to epistemology. I will also explore

(in the next section) the further question of whether models themselves are

subject to epistemological evaluation in a fashion that goes beyond their

aptness and reliability—for example, whether we should speak of models,

as well as judgments and beliefs, as being warranted.

We should distinguish two types of judgments and their different rela-

tionships to models. One type of judgment makes explicit one or more

features or commitments of a model. “A body at rest will remain at rest

unless acted on by an external force” and “bodies exert an attractive force

described by the inverse square law” express basic commitments of New-

tonian mechanics. “Bishops may move diagonally” expresses a basic com-

mitment of a model of chess. Insofar as one is using the model, one is

normatively committed to such judgments. And to the extent that the

model is apt, the judgments are true. In many cases, such judgments also

seem intuitively obvious and even necessary to someone conversant with

the model. (Indeed, they are “necessary” in the sense of being constitutive

commitments of the model, much as the parallel postulate is a constitu-

tive commitment of Euclidean geometry and thus necessarily true-within-

Euclidean-geometry.) At least when one is using the model naively—that is,

not attending to the fact that it is idealized and might not be aptly applied

in all cases—such judgments seem self-evident. Indeed, I suspect that the

vast majority of judgments whose truth seems self-evident do so because

they express principles of deeply entrenched models that we can access

through intuitive processes.

1

Of course, the fact that models are idealized

and not apt for all cases implies that we are in danger of epistemic illusion

(see chap. 14) if we endorse such propositions as universal and unidealized

claims. But they are warranted (a) as claims about the commitments of the

model, (b) as claims about what must be the case wherever the model is

aptly applied, and often (c) as prima facie but defeasible assumptions if the

model is one that is broadly and routinely applicable.

291 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

While judgments of this first type are often prominent in philosophy

and the sciences, the vast majority of judgments we make are not of this

type; they are judgments in which models are employed in how we frame

particular states of affairs: “this body is at rest,” “this body will take five

seconds to reach the ground after it is dropped,” “the white bishop is in a

position to capture the black queen.” Such judgments are neither derivable

from nor warranted by models alone, as they also depend on facts in the

world. Nevertheless there are important relationships between the framing

models and the truth and warrant of the judgments. A judgment can go

wrong in one way if it is framed in terms of an inapt model. In the context

of cosmology, it makes no sense to speak of absolute rest. The Archbishop

of Canterbury and the Queen of England may be standing in a diagonal

relation on a checkered dais, and someone glancing at the scene might take

it to be part of a game of human chess; but the observer would be mistaken,

and the bishop is not poised to capture the queen (because he is not a chess

bishop or she a chess queen at all, and the notion of “capture” employed in

chess does not apply to them). If I use an inapt model to frame a situation,

any warrant that its inferential rules might provide for a judgment based

on them is nullified.

We can also go wrong even when we use apt models, if we do not use

their resources to properly represent the particulars of the situation. In traf-

fic court, it does make sense to speak of “being at rest” or “standing still”

(with the surface of the Earth or the roads treated as a fixed frame of refer-

ence), but people routinely seem to think they have stopped at the inter-

section at the base of my street when in fact they have never slowed down

below five miles per hour. The chess player may not see the board properly

or not realize that moving his bishop would expose his king to checkmate.

In such cases, the model employed did provide ways of representing things

in a fashion we would count as true, but the judgment that was actually

made represented things in another way, which we count as false. Again,

in such cases, any warrant that might have been conferred by the model is

nullified. If the board had been as I thought it was, my judgment that I was

in a position to capture the opposing queen by moving my bishop would

have been warranted, but the antecedent of the conditional is in fact false.

When we frame a situation using a model, all the inferential power of

the model becomes immediately available through intuitive model-based

understanding. We are able to attend to further implications through the

lens of the model, often in such a fashion that it does not even seem like

inference, but merely as “simply seeing” things such as that I can capture

the opposing queen. If the framing goes right—if we employ an apt model

292 Chapter 15

and use the best representation afforded by the model for our judgment—

these further judgments are also warranted. Models thus provide richly pro-

ductive mechanisms for generating judgments, and when the model is apt,

they are reliable mechanisms for generating true judgments. Moreover, to

the extent that the warrant is supplied by the inferential potencies of the

model, we may attribute the warrant conferred not only to judgments but

also to beliefs in the broader dispositional sense when they are ones we

are capable of making into judgments using the resources of model-based

understanding.

Are Models Epistemically Evaluable?

Are models themselves epistemically evaluable? Given the standard char-

acterization of knowledge as warranted true belief, models cannot count

as knowledge, because models are not beliefs. (And as the terms ‘true’ and

‘false’ are applicable only to beliefs and to other units of the same size, such

as propositions and sentences, models cannot be true or false, either.) It

is true, of course, that we sometimes speak of some types of models, such

as scientific theories, as “true” and as “knowledge,” but this does not so

much present a challenge as it bespeaks an ordinary language usage that

is broader than technical usage, or a residual assumption that theories are

propositional in character, or perhaps really that we can make statements

about the aptness of models, and such statements can be true or false, war-

ranted or unwarranted.

While I have spoken (albeit briefly) to the reasons for using separate

terms to express the alethetic virtues that are appropriately attributed to

judgments (and other sentence-sized units) and to models, I have yet to

discuss the question of whether models are also units that can be evalu-

ated epistemically for warrant or something like it, apart from questions

of whether the beliefs constitutively associated with them are individually

warranted. We have at least two distinct sorts of questions here. First, are

models, as models, subject to any sort of epistemological evaluation at all?

Second, if they are, are the features that count as epistemic virtues for mod-

els sufficiently like those that count as epistemic virtues for beliefs or judg-

ments that we should use the same terminology for them—for example,

should we speak of models as things that can be warranted?

Given the reliabilist characterization I have given earlier, one might be

led to suppose that models are not likely to be subject to any sort of epis-

temological assessment beyond the fact that they can be reliable mecha-

nisms for producing true beliefs and judgments and consequently confer

warrant on those beliefs and judgments. Perceptual mechanisms are often

293 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

used as paradigm cases of reliable judgment-producing mechanisms. But

such mechanisms—say, whatever neural processes produce a conceptually

laden perceptual gestalt from a pattern of stimulation on sensory transduc-

ers—are not themselves the sorts of things that can be warranted or unwar-

ranted, unless perhaps by that we mean simply that they are reliable. They

deal in concepts and judgments only in their outputs, and their operations

are subject neither to introspective scrutiny nor to revision. To be sure, we

normally proceed on the tacit assumption (a “belief” in a very broad sense)

that the judgments they produce are trustworthy, and we can judge that

they are unreliable under particular conditions on the basis of experience.

These beliefs and judgments can be (or fail to be) warranted, but that does

not mean that the mechanisms themselves are warranted or unwarranted.

The application of the notion of “warrant” to such perceptual mechanisms

seems to be something of a category error.

But this does not imply that belief-producing mechanisms in general are

not epistemically evaluable beyond the question of whether they reliably

produce true beliefs. Special features of the mechanisms involved in percep-

tual preprocessing may debar them from specifically epistemic evaluation:

the mechanisms do not operate on conceptually laden content, operate

automatically, and are not subject to scrutiny or revision. Models can also

operate automatically; and as some modules may also be models, some

models may not be subject to scrutiny or revision, either. But other models

have inference patterns that operate on propositional content, can be used

deliberately as well as automatically, and are subject to scrutiny and revi-

sion in light of reasons to do so.

I have used scientific theories as one paradigm example of mental mod-

els. And scientific theories are clearly held to standards of epistemic evalua-

tion: they are compared with one another for their adequacy, and we speak

of them as being “evidenced” or “confirmed.” It is perhaps a matter of

semantic choice whether we should speak of theories themselves as being

“warranted” or say instead that beliefs about their credentials are warranted

and use some other term (like “confirmed”) for theories themselves. But

some form of epistemic evaluation clearly seems appropriate. So at least

some mental models are subject to epistemic evaluation, whether we call it

“warrant” or “confirmation” or by some other name.

But there are other types of mental models with respect to which it

would sound decidedly odd to apply the same terms. We would be unlikely

to speak of someone’s understanding of chess, restaurant dining, or vanity

as being justified, warranted, confirmed, or evidenced. If we make norma-

tive evaluations of someone’s understanding of such matters, it is usually

294 Chapter 15

in terms of whether they have gotten the model right. Moving a piece in

an illegal way, or failing to see an impending checkmate, or going to the

restaurant kitchen to prepare one’s own meal indicates a limitation or even

a lack of understanding. But the deficiencies they show are more akin to

falsity (having the wrong model altogether) than to lack of warrant.

On closer scrutiny, however, it does make sense to ask questions about

whether one is entitled to all the assumptions implicit in the model one

is using. I recall a stage in learning chess as a child when I had observed

pawns moving two spaces but had not recognized that this is permitted

only on their initial moves. My error was quickly pointed out after I made

what I had supposed to be a clever (but in fact illegal) move; and in ret-

rospect I can see that I had incautiously made what turned out to be the

wrong generalization based on my observations and whatever instruction

I had received in the game at that point. It may well be that this happened

so early in my acquaintance with chess that I had not yet fully formed a

model (even an incorrect one) of the game and was still operating at the

level of memorized rules. But even so, if there had not been early occasion

for the error to be corrected, I might very well have formed a deviant model

of chess. Forming a deviant model is itself still a matter of getting the model

wrong. But we might go on to ask questions about the epistemic merits and

faults of the process through which I formed the assumption that a pawn

can generally move one or two spaces forward. One might debate whether

my internalization of a model with that particular set of deviant rules was

justified—I seem to recall a feeling of outrage at the time that my teacher

had not made it clear that pawns could move two spaces only on the first

move—but the very fact that there is such a question to be asked implies

that epistemic evaluation has a place here.

We can frame similar issues about the understanding of when a model

can aptly be applied. I recall trying to order wine at a fancy restaurant where

such orders are handled not by the waiter or waitress but by a wine specialist

called a sommelier. The model of restaurant dining I was accustomed to was

one in which a single person takes all types of orders for food and drink,

which is indeed an apt model to use in the vast majority of dining establish-

ments I visit. I assumed it would aptly be applied at this particular restaurant

as well, but I was mistaken, and the waiter politely replied that he would

send over the sommelier. It was an understandable mistake; I had no way

of knowing based on a fairly long history of trips to restaurants, no one had

bothered to warn me, it was a mistake the restaurant staff probably encoun-

ter every day, and so on. Arguably, while I had committed a minor faux pas,

I had done so on the basis of assumptions to which I might claim epistemic

295 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

entitlement. Nonetheless I have subsequently adopted a more cautious atti-

tude toward dining in unfamiliar contexts—particularly restaurants with

waitstaff in black tie or where I am faced with an array of more pieces of

silverware than I am sure what to do with. Knowing that dining contexts

are not all alike, I face questions about what I may safely assume. And even

before I had this awareness, the assumptions were merely assumptions, and

in making them, I deviated from some type of ideal epistemic norm.

Models of chess and restaurant etiquette differ from scientific models

in an important way: one has the “right” model of chess or dining sim-

ply by dint of having one that corresponds with the models that others

are using. There is something of the same in understanding a scientific

theory—say, having a correct understanding of classical mechanics—but a

further question arises as to whether that model is an adequate model of

the phenomena it is applied to, and this latter question is at issue in sci-

entific confirmation. But scientific models are by no means unique in this

respect. The models I use to navigate my house or the town I live in have

to track features of those environments if they are to enable me to navigate

successfully, even though their assumptions and commitments are seldom

explicitly expressed. The statistical heuristics we employ in everyday life

are apt (or not) for particular contexts, and we can be in better or worse

positions to assess their aptness. (Hence the tendency of researchers deal-

ing with heuristics and biases to describe inapt strategies as “irrational,”

particularly when the person who employs them is in a position to know

they are inapt.) Our models of social categories such as race and gender are

often woefully inadequate to representing their targets and are produced

and reinforced through mechanisms that are notoriously unreliable for

tracking the facts. The processes of consciousness-raising that can disabuse

us of such social biases are not only morally edifying but also put us in a

better epistemic position with respect to our social understanding.

We probably need far more discussion of the epistemic evaluation of

models than I am in a position to give here, and different types of models are

likely to require different types of evaluation. Epistemic evaluation seems

appropriate with respect to ways a model is produced, how (or if) it can be

scrutinized and adjusted, and how we can learn to distinguish the cases in

which it is apt from those in which it is not and use it only in contexts in

which it is apt. Developmentally canalized models like the core systems

are produced primarily through evolution and development, but these can

perhaps be regarded as prior mechanisms that can be evaluated for their

reliability in producing apt models. Learned models can be held account-

able to standards of confirmation and can generally also be adjusted and

296 Chapter 15

improved on. In both cases, true mastery of the model involves not only

having the model and being able to use it, but also having an understanding

of where it is aptly applied.

Models as Integral Epistemic Units

A model-based view of understanding has implications for epistemology

because models turn out to be important epistemic units in their own right,

over and above beliefs. If models are themselves epistemically evaluable

and furthermore provide warrant for judgments and beliefs, an episte-

mological theory that deals exclusively with beliefs leaves out something

important. But incorporating mental models into epistemology also has a

further implication that will prove particularly important in assessing the

adequacy of two of the major epistemological theories, foundationalism

and holism.

Models are integral units. Often the commitments of a model can be

made explicit in the form of judgments and implication rules, but a model

is not simply an assemblage of beliefs and implication rules that can be

independently specified, as these are constitutively interrelated—or, as it

is sometimes phrased, “interdefined.” This has been a familiar claim about

scientific theories for several decades, and that alone should have been

enough to cause a rethinking of belief-based epistemology. If it is a general

characteristic of mental models, and models are the basis of understanding,

the implications are all the more urgent.

In philosophy of science, theories are commonly regarded as principal

units for confirmation. The credentials of relativistic claims about mass can-

not be evaluated apart from relativistic claims about space and time, and

vice versa. Likewise, applications of the theory to particular cases are war-

ranted by the aptness of the theory as a whole. An adequate epistemol-

ogy of science must accommodate the role of models—as integral units—in

receiving justification and conferring warrant. If similar considerations

apply to models generally, the implications for epistemology are consider-

ably broader. I argue in the next section that this has a serious implication

for the field of epistemology: neither foundationalism nor global coherent-

ism can be a fully adequate epistemological theory, because neither accords

model-sized units their proper role.

15.3 Cognitive Pluralism and Theories of Knowledge

Now that I have given a rough characterization of the cognitive pluralist

view of the interrelationships between models, beliefs, and warrant, let us

297 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

turn to its relation to familiar theories in epistemology and its implications

for those theories. Epistemology is the study of knowledge. Mainstream

contemporary epistemology is pursued under the shared assumption that

knowledge is warranted true belief, alternative theories differing principally

in their accounts of what makes a belief warranted. The traditional alterna-

tives for an account of warrant are foundationalism and coherentism, along

with a more recent contender called reliabilism.

Reliabilism

While reliabilism is a relatively new addition to the list of philosophical

accounts of epistemic warrant, I will address it first, because the character-

ization I have given of the warrant conferred by apt models seems in fact

to be a reliabilist view. The reliabilist holds that a belief is warranted if and

only if it is produced by a reliable mechanism for producing true beliefs in

that type of context. Alvin Plantinga, for example, writes that a belief is

warranted if and only if it meets the following conditions:

(1) It has been produced in me by cognitive faculties that are working properly … in

a cognitive environment that is appropriate for my kinds of cognitive faculties, (2)

the segment of design plan governing the production of that belief is aimed at the

production of true beliefs, and (3) there is a high statistical probability that a belief

produced under those conditions will be true. (Plantinga 1993, 46)

Saying that a mechanism for belief production is “reliable” in producing

true beliefs does not really tell us much about the mechanism, even if the

reliability of the mechanism is cashed out in terms of probability. This is

not necessarily a bad characteristic for the reliabilist theory to have, as there

may be many reliable mechanisms that are reliable in different ways and

for different reasons, and hence a highly flexible account of warrant may

actually be required.

One of the core applications of reliabilist accounts has been to the pro-

duction of beliefs through perception, where the causes of the belief are

not themselves beliefs. It seems clear enough that perceptual processes are

in some broad sense “mechanisms,” and the details of how they work and

why they are reliable can be left to the cognitive scientists. But to extend the

theory further, we would need some way of clarifying what sort of “faculty”

or “mechanism” might be involved in nonperceptual belief formation.

In my account, models provide ways of framing situations and forming

judgments about them, as well as licensing judgments about them. Some

“beliefs” in the dispositional sense, moreover, can be seen in terms of what

inferences are licensed by the inferential rules of the model. Models are

298 Chapter 15

thus, among other things, “faculties” or “mechanisms” for judgment pro-

duction, and when the model is aptly applied, it confers warrant on the

judgments thus formed. It is thus natural to view a model-based account

as a way of fleshing out a reliabilist epistemology with respect to a large

and important class of ways that beliefs are formed through nonperceptual

processes.

Foundationalism

Foundationalism is a very old philosophical view. Variations on it were

endorsed by Aristotle and his medieval followers, by early modern philoso-

phers in both the rationalist and empiricist camps, and by a significant

number of twentieth-century philosophers, including some of the logical

positivists, such as Moritz Schlick (1934/1979). Aristotle is often credited

with first articulating a foundationalist account of knowledge in his Pos-

terior Analytics, in response to a skeptical problem about demonstrative

knowledge, the regress problem. The skeptic argues that whatever is known

must be demonstrated—that is, deduced validly from things that are

already known. But for those things to be known, they must be demon-

strated from other things that are already known, and so on, in an infinite

regress, so that the chain of demonstration cannot get off the ground, and

hence knowledge is impossible. Aristotle seems to endorse demonstration

as a paradigm for knowledge but rejects both the skeptical regress and the

alternative of circular demonstration in favor of the view that there can

be another, nondemonstrative form of knowledge of the first and foun-

dational premises. Thus we have two types of knowledge: things that are

known directly in their own right, and things validly derived from such

foundations. This is the core of a foundationalist view of knowledge: in

contemporary terms, a belief is warranted if and only if it is either (1) prop-

erly basic or (2) derived in the right sort of way (usually meaning by valid

deduction) from properly basic beliefs.

Several brief observations are in order. First, both the core view and the

way it is arrived at bear the distinctive marks of the standard view of cog-

nition. Not only are the units sentence sized (beliefs, judgments, proposi-

tions, or actual sentences) and argument sized (demonstrations), but the

starting point of the discussion is a paradigm of knowledge as a product

of demonstrative argumentation. Second, while contemporary discussions

in epistemology generally employ the word ‘belief’, it seems clear that the

account is really an account of specifically occurrent beliefs (i.e., judgments),

as it is hard to see how merely dispositional beliefs could plausibly be seen

as products of demonstration. And third, I have described what I have

300 Chapter 15

incorrigible, or indubitable. However, around this time there was a growing recogni-

tion that foundationalism was compatible with basic beliefs that lacked these epis-

temically exalted properties. William Alston …, C. F. Delaney …, and Mark Pastin …

all argued that a foundationalist epistemology merely required that the basic beliefs

have a level of positive epistemic status independent of warranting relations from

other beliefs. In light of this weaker form of foundationalism the attacks against

infallibility, incorrigibility, or indubitability did not touch the core of a foundation-

alist epistemology. (Poston 2015)

Modest foundationalism avoids one of the problems with strong foun-

dationalism: its overly high epistemic standard for properly basic beliefs

or judgments. But it retains the core foundationalist commitment to the

assumption that beliefs are warranted individually, some by being properly

basic and others by being inferred from properly basic beliefs. And it is this

commitment that is most directly at odds with a model-based cognitive

pluralism.

From a cognitive pluralist standpoint, the claim that some judgments

are warranted because of how they are inferred from other judgments

need not itself be regarded as problematic. A cognitive pluralist can cer-

tainly recognize that we do sometimes reason using various forms of logical

inference ranging over sentence-sized units, and the validity of the infer-

ence form and the warrant of the premises are surely relevant to the epis-

temic status of the conclusions thus derived. The problem is that this is

neither the only nor even the most fundamental source of warrant, and the

kind of warrant conferred by models does not simply attach to individual

judgments one by one. At the least, some of our beliefs that have excellent

credentials for counting as knowledge, such as those involved in scientific

theories, are neither individually properly basic nor justified by inference

from other beliefs that are already warranted as properly basic. Rather,

the beliefs and the whole framework of concepts and inferential patterns

are warranted together, as a unit. And if the cognitive pluralist is correct

that this is not an idiosyncratic feature of scientific theories, but a much

more general feature of model-based understanding, foundationalism

lacks the resources to explain how an extremely large number of our beliefs

are warranted. At the least, foundationalism is incomplete as an account

of knowledge and requires resources of a very different sort to supple-

ment it.

From a cognitive pluralist perspective, foundationalism seems best inter-

preted as an idealized model of a particular dimension of epistemic good-

ness. It is specifically focused on judgments produced by argumentative

inference, and quite reasonably identifies the validity of the inference and

301 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

the warrant of the premises as factors relevant to the epistemic assessment

of judgments thus derived. The legitimate conclusion of the regress argu-

ment is that, for such a process of transferring warrant through logical

inference to get off the ground, there must be premises that are warranted

in some other way. It would perhaps have been best to stop here and regard

this as a consequence of how the account is idealized: that it is just an

account of warrant-via-inference and simply brackets the question of how

else judgments can be warranted.

Some versions of modest foundationalism, however, have in fact explored

ways that the theory can be supplemented with other sorts of resources,

and at least one of these suggests a way that a modest foundationalist might

attempt to incorporate insights about mental models. One long-standing

problem for epistemology was that of how sensation and perception can

warrant beliefs. Alvin Goldman (1979) proposed a reliabilist account of

this: perceptual beliefs can be properly basic by dint of being produced by

perceptual mechanisms that reliably produce true beliefs. While reliabilism

has gone on to be regarded as an epistemological theory supplying its own

account of warrant, Goldman’s account is often also classified as a founda-

tionalist account, augmented with a reliabilist story about how a certain

class of judgments come to be properly basic. This, in turn, suggests a way

that a modest foundationalist might embrace models as playing a role in

warranting beliefs and judgments. If, like perceptual mechanisms, models

reliably generate true judgments when aptly applied, at least some judg-

ments produced from models might count as properly basic.

I prefer to leave it to the foundationalists to decide what should be

counted as a variant on foundationalism, or a supplement to it, and what

needs to be viewed as a nonfoundationalist account. Clearly the core com-

mitments of foundationalism leave open questions about the noninferen-

tial sources of warrant, and I believe that some of these are derived from

model-based understanding. Just how model-based understanding can be

combined with a foundationalist account is constrained by the fact that

foundationalists group all noninferential knowledge together in the cat-

egory of properly basic beliefs. So whether beliefs that derive their war-

rant from models can be accommodated within a basically foundationalist

framework will depend on how one understands what it means for a belief

to be properly basic. Strong foundationalism, of course, has extremely high

standards for proper basicality, and judgments produced from model-based

mechanisms do not seem to meet those standards. I have explored how

models can produce “intuitive” judgments, but we have also seen that such

judgments are far from infallible, though they may come with a subjective

302 Chapter 15

sense of certainty. But the modest foundationalist is not committed to

such high standards, and there seems to be no obvious and uncontentious

answer to the question of how the modest foundationalist ought to under-

stand proper basicality.

One possibility is that a belief should be counted as properly basic just in

case it is warranted, but not in a fashion derived from logical inference. In

this interpretation, judgments produced by the apt application of models

might indeed count as properly basic. But if this is all that “properly basic”

means, there might be any number of noninferential sources of warrant,

and all that groups them into a class is a feature they lack: they are not

processes of logical inference. This might not be such a problem if they

also shared some feature that rendered them in some recognizable sense

foundational. But it is not clear how the metaphor of a “foundation” should

be understood once one has abandoned stronger forms of foundational-

ism. Perhaps it should be understood epistemically: foundational beliefs

are those about which there are no further epistemic questions to ask. Or

perhaps it should be understood psychologically, in terms of the origins

of beliefs and judgments: the foundational ones are the first epistemically

evaluable ones in a process, or perhaps ones without which no other beliefs

or judgments could be warranted.

It seems plausible to me that beliefs based in models may fit some such

psychological criteria: without models we would have no beliefs at all, and

these are the beliefs on which any other epistemic processes operate. How-

ever, most models are learned, and in learning a model, we often engage

in some sort of process of confirming that it is a good model, at least for

particular epistemic and practical ends. The process of confirmation may

be unconscious, implicit, and nonargumentative (though in cases like sci-

entific models, a good deal of explicit reasoning often goes into building

and confirming them), but models are not really “epistemic foundations”

in the sense of being “givens” whose epistemic credentials can be taken

for granted. As a consequence, the production of judgments from models

does not seem to be an epistemological foundation, either. There are fur-

ther epistemological questions about judgments produced by models: ques-

tions about whether the model is a good model of its domain, whether it is

aptly applied in this circumstance, and whether the judgment produced is

the best judgment among the options available from the model. There are

likewise further epistemological questions about models themselves and

the beliefs expressing their systematic commitments: about how they are

idealized, and about what sorts of cases the models are apt for and hence

about which of the judgments they produce and their implicit constitutive

303 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

beliefs can be true. (These questions, moreover, can be asked not only about

learned models but about developmentally canalized models as well.)

It thus seems decidedly odd to characterize models as epistemic founda-

tions. Models may indeed be in some sense prior to beliefs and judgments,

and the epistemic credentials of beliefs and judgments ultimately depen-

dent on the qualities of the models in which they are framed. But given

that there are multiple learned models, often possessing different constitu-

tive beliefs and licensing contradictory judgments, the resulting picture is

closer to Neurath’s metaphor of a raft we are always reconfiguring than to

Schlick’s model of a pyramid of knowledge.

Alternatively, the modest foundationalist might be inclined to view

at least some of the processes by which models give rise to judgments as

forms of inference, distinct from, but not necessarily less respectable than,

deductive inference. Some foundationalists have long embraced nonde-

ductive inference forms—induction, retroduction—as conferring warrant,

and there seems no principled reason that other inferential processes could

not also be included. This strategy, however, strikes me as problematic as

well. I have no objection to calling some of the model-based processes

that produce judgments “inferences”; indeed, it seems a natural way to

characterize them. The potential sticking point is that if we do so, they

are inferences to things with propositional form but not from things with

propositional form, as models neither are, nor are made up of, beliefs or

judgments. The problem here is that foundationalism characterizes the

inferential grounding relation as one between beliefs, which would not be

true of an “inferential” process in which model-based processes generate a

judgment through their own nonlogical, nonargumentative mechanisms.

Broadening the foundationalist notion of “inference” in this way would

seem to risk losing a distinction that lies at the heart of foundationalism:

the distinction between the kind of warrant conferral that comes through

argument and whatever other ways a judgment or belief might come to

be warranted.

If models are themselves subject to some form of epistemic evaluation

and play a role in conferring warrant on judgments and beliefs, founda-

tionalism is an inadequate account of knowledge. Most fundamentally, it

neglects models as a distinct type of epistemic unit, not reducible to beliefs

and inferences. Because of this, it also lacks the resources to accommodate

the roles models play in warranting beliefs and judgments. Modest founda-

tionalists might seek to treat a model-based account as a supplemental story

compatible with foundationalism, whether by treating models as reliable

mechanisms for producing properly basic beliefs or by treating model-based

305 Cognitive Pluralism and Epistemology

is a prima facie indication of a problem and gives us reason for further scru-

tiny. But it may present an insurmountable problem if it turns out to arise

from the ways different models are idealized. On the other hand, incom-

mensurability between models need not always result in inconsistency

between beliefs, because models are idealized and not applied aptly to all

cases. In some cases, like quantum complementarity, the incommensurabil-

ity of models may not lead to inconsistency of beliefs because we recognize

that one of the models should not be applied in the case at hand, and hence

we do not endorse the application of that model to the case by forming a

judgment based on that model.

15.4 A View of the Status of Accounts of Epistemology

The basic line of criticism I have leveled at standard epistemological views

has been that while each may pick out factors that are relevant to the assess-

ment of warrant, none of them can tell the full story. In the case of foun-

dationalism and coherentism, the problem is that, as general theories, they

leave important things out or get some things wrong. In the case of reliabi-

lism, the issue is that a simple appeal to “reliability” does not tell us much

about the psychological nature of the reliable mechanisms.

Foundationalism, coherentism, and reliabilism are often treated as rival

theories of warrant. In philosophical writing, proponents of one account

will often show how their theory handles a particular range of cases well,

but argue that the rival accounts yield counterintuitive assessments of

which beliefs are warranted. The underlying assumption of such arguments

is that each theory is taken to be offered as a comprehensive and unideal-

ized account of the same thing: something called “epistemic warrant” or

“knowledge.” But cognitive pluralism suggests an alternative way to view

them. Each account is an idealized account of one dimension of epistemic

evaluation. Beliefs can be justified by their relationships to other beliefs

in various ways, and the ways we reason from some beliefs to others are

relevant to the overall status of the derived beliefs, as the foundationalist

suggests. The ways various beliefs cohere or conflict with one another are

also relevant to their epistemic status, as are the ways they are produced

by mechanisms that are or are not reliable in a given type of situation.

Arguably, each account provides a useful way of looking at how beliefs can

go awry that is not captured by the others. We might thus look at differ-

ent epistemological theories not as rival accounts but as multiple ideal-

ized ways of looking at an issue (epistemic warrant, or how beliefs come to

count as knowledge) that is too complex to be handled by a single theory,

Chapter 16

Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

16 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

Many sorts of things are said to “be meaningful” or “have semantic con-

tent.” Some of these are mental: concepts, beliefs and other dispositional

intentional states, judgments and other occurrent intentional states. Oth-

ers are linguistic: words, phrases, sentences, speech acts, utterances, inscrip-

tions. Some would say that logic has its own stock of meaningful units,

which are neither truly mental nor truly linguistic: bound variables, con-

stants, predicate letters, Fregean propositions, well-formed formulas. And

these meaningful entities come in a variety of sizes as well: word-sized units

(lexical units in a language, concepts, predicate letters), sentence-sized

units (sentences, utterances, speech acts, beliefs, judgments, propositions,

well-formed formulas), and larger units such as arguments.

In one sense, we thus have a number of different types of “semantic

units,” differing in compositional size and in whether they are mental, lin-

guistic, or abstractly logical. But we might also ask whether one of these

types of units is fundamental. Discussions of this topic generally list either

two or three candidate answers. Perhaps most common is a two-way divi-

sion between the options of atomism and holism:

Semantic atomism locates meaning at the level of individual words (the meaning

of each word is in it); semantic holism locates meaning at a broader level, ranging

from an indefinite network of linked units to an entire language. (Engler 2011, 266)

The tradition of formal semantics has been resolutely atomistic, in the sense that the

assignment of a semantic interpretant to one element (say, a proper name) is taken

to be intelligible independently of the assignment of semantic interpretants to any

other elements (for instance, predicates or other proper names). One does not need

to know anything about what other dots represent, or what blue wavy lines repre-

sent, in order to understand that a particular dot stands for Cleveland on a map.

The task of formal semantics is a bottom-up one of explaining how semantically

relevant whatsits can systematically be assigned to complex expressions, given that

they have already been assigned to simple ones. Atomism adds that the assignments

312 Chapter 16

The semantic value of the concept DOG commits us to take “dogs are ani-

mals” to be true and licenses inferences from “x is a dog” to “x is an ani-

mal.” It likewise commits us to take “dogs are vegetables” to be false and

incurs no commitment about the truth of “dogs are Pope Francis’s favor-

ite type of animal.” But the meanings of all three sentences are built up,

in the same way, from the semantic values of their constituents and their

respective syntactic structures. The difference between atomists, on the one

hand, and holists and molecularists, on the other, is not (usually) about

whether sentence-sized units get their meanings compositionally, but

about whether (or in what cases) epistemic and inferential commitments

are a consequence of something that word-sized units have in their own

right, or whether word-sized units have such semantic properties because

of epistemic and inferential commitments.

A more stringent notion of semantic atomism adds the additional condi-

tion that the semantic value of one word-sized unit cannot depend on its

relation even to other word-sized units:

Semantic atomists hold that the meaning of any representation (linguistic, men-

tal, or otherwise) is not determined by the meaning of any other representation.

Historically, Anglo-American philosophers in the eighteenth and nineteenth cen-

turies thought that an idea of an X was about X’s in virtue of this idea’s physically

resembling X’s. Resemblance theories are no longer thought viable, but a number

of contemporary semantic atomists still believe that the basic semantic relation is

between a concept and the things to which it applies, and not one among concepts

themselves. (Lepore 1999, 829)

By this criterion, if BACHELOR includes other concepts (MAN and UNMARRIED), the

concept

BACHELOR is not a semantic atom. The older definitional approach

to semantics claimed that we define many and perhaps most concepts

in terms of simpler atomic concepts; and for such a theory to get off the

ground, it had to assume that there must be some concepts that are atomic.

The question, of course, was what sorts of concepts could really be atomic

in this way. One answer, explored by the British empiricists and some of

the early logical positivists, was that the best candidates would have to

be something like Locke’s simple ideas of sensation—or, in more recent

formulations, sense data or qualia. Other recent atomisms have attempted

to ground semantic atoms in causal and informational relations between a

thinker and an object or class of objects. According to one type of causal

theory, a concept C means X because Cs are reliably caused by Xs (Fodor

1987). In another type of causal theory, C means X because Cs were caused

by Xs in a privileged reference-fixing period (Kripke 1980). In Dretske’s

314 Chapter 16

with the first two theses without reference to the further issues posed by

A3, I will use the label ‘atomism’ to refer to views that embrace A1 and A2.

From the cognitive pluralist’s standpoint, the problem with semantic

atomism is that it has no way of accounting for the constitutive connec-

tions within a model between concepts, beliefs, inferential dispositions,

and capacities for perception and action. A change in my understanding

of how a chess bishop is permitted to move is a change in my concept of

a chess bishop as well. This is similar to familiar holist arguments against

atomism, with the important difference that the cognitive pluralist holds

that there is a principled difference between the situations one finds within

a model and outside or between models.

Additionally, the cognitive pluralist is not required to hold either that

the atomist story has nothing right or that there cannot be concepts about

which it tells the best story. What the cognitive pluralist needs to insist on

is that, in the case of model-based understanding, the semantics of a concept

must be constitutively linked to those of other concepts, and to the rules,

representational system, and inferential commitments of the model. It is

compatible with this idea that there are also cases where we have concepts

that are not grounded in this way in models. Indeed, I think that, in cer-

tain learning contexts, concepts can be acquired (at least initially) without

being associated with a well-formed model. When we encounter a new kind

of thing without yet having any concrete understanding of it, the concept

may well take a form very like a conceptual atom. And when we learn a

concept through a verbal definition, it may have constitutive dependencies

on the other concepts through which it is defined but not yet be embed-

ded in a model. I tend to expect that these are primarily characteristics

of learning processes that normally lead toward embeddedness in one or

more models, but this is an empirical hypothesis that would need careful

exploration.

Holism

Conceptual holism is the thesis that all our concepts are constitutively

interdefined, such that a change to any one of them would amount to a

change in all of them. Moreover, holist theses are generally not confined

to semantics. The holism found in Quine (1951) and Davidson (1967), for

example, posits constitutive interconnections between all of a person’s con-

cepts, beliefs, and inferential commitments.

A model-based cognitive pluralism also posits constitutive interconnec-

tions between concepts, beliefs, and inferential commitments and so has

an important resemblance to holism. The difference is in scope. The holist

315 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

holds that such constitutive interrelations are found between all concepts,

beliefs, and inferential commitments. The cognitive pluralist finds them

only (or chiefly) within the concepts, beliefs, and inferential commitments

of a model. According to holists, the network relevant to the semantics of a

concept is completely global. According to cognitive pluralists, it a mental

model.

Distinguishing two types of holist claims will help here. The first is that

anything, from any domain of understanding (including things we do not

yet understand and are completely unaware of), could in principle prove

to be relevant to any other concept, belief, or inferential commitment, and

hence a change to any unit anywhere could require adjustments anywhere

else. The cognitive pluralist can accept this as a “for all we know” kind of

claim: I cannot rule out in advance the possibility that some change in my

understanding of physics might force me to rethink how I understand some

other domain like chess, dining, or ethics. It may seem unlikely, as I cannot

see how it could do so. But this is in part because I cannot anticipate what

change in my understanding in physics might someday come along that

would require such adjustments; and for this reason, I cannot definitively

say in advance what other areas of understanding are insulated from it.

The second and stronger type of holist thesis is that each concept, belief,

and inferential commitment is constitutively bound up with every other,

so that any change is eo ipso a change to everything else in the system.

Cognitive pluralism differs from such a constitutive holism in precisely the

areas where constitutive holism seems most vulnerable. It seems correct

to say that a change in meaning, belief, or inferential commitments has

ramifications to other concepts, beliefs, and inferential commitments, but

those ramifications have limits. If I change my understanding of, say, how

a knight moves in chess, this clearly has constitutive implications for how

I need to adjust my understanding of the concept

CHESS_KNIGHT and other

aspects of my understanding of chess. But it does not follow that I need to

similarly adjust my understanding of mechanics or of restaurant etiquette.

Similarly, a transition from classical to relativistic mechanics involves a

change in concepts of

MASS and SPACE and changes in beliefs and inferen-

tial commitments within the domain of mechanics, but it need not have the

slightest impact on my understanding of chess or the semantics of a con-

cept like

GRANDMOTHER. What cognitive pluralism adds to this commonsense

insight is a theory of why it might be correct: namely, that there is a kind

of psychological unit (a mental model) distinct from concepts, beliefs, and

inferences, which sets the bounds on how far such changes should ramify.

A model-based cognitive pluralism implies that at least some portion of

316 Chapter 16

conceptual semantics is best described by a molecularist picture, but cogni-

tive pluralism goes beyond a mere assertion of semantic molecularism in

providing a theoretical account of what makes it true.

In short, holism gets some things right: (1) some changes in meaning

do or ought to constitute changes in other concepts and in belief and vice

versa, and (2) what we believe is in some ways constitutively tied into the

semantics of the terms we use. But holism errs in being a completely global

and ecumenical thesis. Not all changes in belief and meaning have the

same sorts of implications for every other element of a person’s epistemic

space, and holism lacks the resources to deal with the differences.

16.3 The Multiple Lives of Concepts

Our discussions thus far might suggest a particular view of concepts and

their relationship to models. If a concept used within a model—such as

CHESS_KNIGHT or the concept MASS used in a relativistic model of gravitation—

is constitutively interdefined with the other concepts used in the model

and with the model’s rules and representational system, this seems to sug-

gest that each concept resides within a single model. It might additionally

be used in linguistic inferences that combine concepts drawn from differ-

ent models, and there may be associations between it and concepts drawn

from other models, but these are not constitutive of what concept it is. I will

refer to this thesis that each concept resides in a single model as the residen-

tial view of concepts.

If we accept the larger thesis that models form tightly integrated units,

wherein concepts and inferential commitments are constitutively intercon-

nected, this might recommend the residential view of concepts. But there

are also reasons to suspect that the residential view cannot be correct, or

at least that it cannot be the full story about concepts. On the one hand,

there is reason to think that some concepts—or something closely akin to

concepts—do not need to be situated in models at all but play a role more

directly connected to grouping stimuli into categories. Much of the litera-

ture on concepts in psychology is primarily about categorization, and it is

important to examine the relationship between the idea that concepts are

tools for categorization and the residential view. On the other hand, there

is reason to think that a single concept can play a role in more than one

model. At the least, we frequently use the same word in expressions of judg-

ments and inferences grounded in multiple models, and at first glance the

situation often looks not like a case of simple homonymy but like a single

concept straddling several models.

317 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

I think that both of these problems are real, and they point to a need

to go beyond the residential view of concepts without rejecting the idea

that much of the semantic content of concepts is derived from models in

which they play a role. There is, of course, a certain amount of terminologi-

cal choice involved in deciding what to call “a concept,” and what to call

by some other name—for example, whether the psychological units used

for classification in perception are the same sorts of entities as the units

used in semantically based reasoning and off-line simulation. But whatever

terminological choices we make, we need to respect the same data. And in

this case, I believe that the best approach is to view concepts as complicated

hybrid entities that must be understood in their relationship to more than

one kind of psychological system. A model-based semantics is still a part of

that story, but it is not the entire story.

16.4 Concepts without Models

I will explore three reasons to think that concepts can exist without being

embedded in mental models. First, in psychology, concepts are often treated

primarily as units of categorization. (And while it is often an assumption

left implicit, what is really central to the discussion is often categorization

in perception.) Categorization can take place without a mental model; and so

if concepts can be (just) tools for categorization, they need not be embed-

ded in models. Second, in some nonhuman animal species, we might have

reason to be skeptical about the presence of the kinds of models that are

relevant to inferential semantics, but still have reason to think that the ani-

mals have concepts (particularly in the sense of things used in perceptual

categorization). And third, concept learning does not seem to require the

mastery of an associated model. Indeed, the process of learning a model

often involves early stages in which we learn to recognize categories of

objects that will be relevant to the model without our yet having mastered

the model.

In discussions of concepts within psychology, we find a great deal of

focus on the role of concepts as tools of categorization, particularly among

proponents of prototype and exemplar theories. Eleanor Rosch, the pioneer

of the prototype theory of concepts, writes:

Two general and basic principles are proposed for the formation of categories. The

first has to do with the function of category systems and asserts that the task of

category systems is to provide maximum information with the least cognitive effort;

the second has to do with the structure of the information so provided and asserts

that the perceived world comes as structured information rather than as arbitrary or

318 Chapter 16

unpredictable attributes. The maximum information with least cognitive effort is

achieved if categories map the perceived world structure as closely as possible. (Rosch

1978/1999, 190; italics mine)

Rosch’s emphasis on “the perceived world” suggests that a core concern of

the theory may be more narrowly about categorization in perception. This

is even more clearly evident with exemplar theories, which treat concepts

as being (or involving) stored memory traces of exemplars of a category

(Smith and Medin 1981).

Perceptual categorization, or indeed categorization in general, is not the

only thing a theory of concepts should explain. But it is one important role

concepts play in our mental economy. Most theories of categorization in

psychology treat the categorization process as one that assigns a category

based on features. In classical theories, the features might be thought to pro-

vide necessary and sufficient conditions for the applicability of the concept.

Prototype and exemplar theories, by contrast, are probabilistic: a concept is

activated by some matching process involving either a set of prototypical

features or a set of exemplars stored in memory. The process may involve

a comparison of the stimulus to multiple prototypes or exemplars, and its

dynamics may be tuned to activate the concept with the best fit with the

stimulus. The kinds of inferential relationships that models are supposed to

underwrite need not figure in this, and it seems clear that mechanisms for

categorization could exist that do not require mental models.

Moreover, it seems reasonable to suppose that there are types of animal

minds that possess categorizing mechanisms that stand between percep-

tual inputs and behavioral control without these being embedded in mental

models of content domains. There are useful types of cognition that you

can obtain only once you have interposed something like a concept (or, if

you prefer to restrict that word to humans or other language users or other

conscious beings, a protoconcept or a feature aggregator) between the stimulus

end and the motor end of the cognitive architecture. Think of it this way:

the success of a motor response often depends little on what sensory chan-

nel an affordance or object is detected through, and very much on what

kind of affordance or object is detected, and the state it is in. Moreover, there

can be many stimuli that are cues to a single type of affordance (typed rela-

tionally) or object (typed “objectively”), and there might be many motor

schemas that are useful for responding to the affordance or object. It is

thus useful for an animal to have in its cognitive architecture a kind of

element that stands in between perception and motor control, as a kind of

central clearinghouse for the various sensory and motor schemas that need

321 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

Figure 16.1

Concepts as feature aggregators. Diagrams of two types of simple cognitive architec-

tures. In the first figure, perceptual feature detectors (for features like colored forms

and nectar pathways visible on flowers to birds or insects) directly drive motor con-

trol. In the second figure, a middle layer is interposed, which responds to many fea-

tures, either individually or in combination, and can drive multiple motor responses.

This architecture allows an organism to detect the same objects, properties, or affor-

dances from multiple distinct cues, and to treat them as equivalent for purposes of

behavioral response.

residential view would have far more radical consequences. If there are

multiple models of banking institutions—say, architectural models, models

used by patrons of how to make various kinds of financial transactions,

economic models used in finance—they would all have to employ distinct

concepts, all expressed by the English word ‘bank’. This might be attrac-

tive from the standpoint of a molecularist inferential semantics; the uses

associated with different models yield different types of inferences. But it

also seems rather counterintuitive, and it presents a problem of how we

know (or at least why we have the sense that) we are talking about the same

institutions when we are thinking about them through different models. It

cannot merely be that we use the same word, because a single word can be

used to talk about distinct classes of things, like a financial institution and

the side of a riverbed, and in those sorts of cases we have no similar tempta-

tion to suppose that there is only a single concept.

Consider some other examples. There are no doubt a number of distinct

models that deal with cows. People who herd cattle probably have mental

models of how cattle roam about singly and in groups and how to interact

with them to cajole them into going where the herder wishes them to go.

Cattle breeders have mental models of different heritable traits of cows and

how they can be combined through selective breeding. Wildlife ecologists

dealing with open ranges have ecological models involving cattle and their

impact on particular environments, and so on. They all use the word ‘cow’

to talk about the same class of things, and it takes no special mental gym-

nastics to recognize that it is the same class of things that is understood,

in different ways, through the different models. The natural conclusion to

draw would seem to be that there is a single concept,

COW, that appears in

many models.

A slightly more difficult case involves theory difference and theory

change. Classical and relativistic mechanics both employ the word ‘mass’,

though the constitutive implications of the word differ importantly in the

323 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

tracking particular individuals, kinds, properties, relations, and processes.

The second involves distinguishing two ways of typing concepts: by their

semantic properties and as psychological continuants in the mind of an

individual.

Intension and Ostension

First, the distinction between intensional and ostensive components. It is

easier to find a point of entry by considering our concepts of individu-

als rather than our concepts of kinds, properties, relations, or processes.

We think of individuals as having enduring properties and properties that

change over time. Being able to think about an individual person or object

at all requires the ability to think of it as one and the same thing despite the

constant changes in variable properties: Socrates is first sitting then stand-

ing, asleep then chatting in the Agora, bearded and then newly shaven.

The boundary between “enduring” and “changing” properties is a bit hazy,

though: we may think of a person’s physiognomy and personality as rela-

tively stable things, but both in fact change substantially throughout the

life cycle and can undergo rapid and dramatic changes as well. Just what

can change without forcing us to conclude that the individual we knew

is no longer present seems somewhat open-ended, a fact reflected in rival

theories of personal identity and of the identity conditions of objects, as

well as in the problems involved in deciding when an embryo becomes a

human person.

The simplest and perhaps the only explanation for this would seem to be

that concepts of individuals (whether persons or objects) involve multiple

components. Some of these involve attribution of properties, and it may be

that there is an important psychological difference in the way we represent

properties we regard as enduring (perhaps even assumed to be part of an

essence) and those that are evanescent. But in addition to these there seems

to have to be a component that is more ostensive—one that has the func-

tion of tracking a particular individual through changes. And the “changes”

we need to track through are not only real changes in the individual but

changes in our beliefs about that individual. I see Socrates and take him to

be a Spartan but then change my mind and decide he is an Athenian. I see

something on the path and take it to be a rock until it moves and I see it

from a different angle and conclude that it is some kind of animal. I do

not simply first think, “There is a Spartan,” and then deny that and think,

“There is an Athenian,” or first think, “There is a rock” and then “There is

an animal.” I am not simply registering (and changing my mind about) the

presence of property-instances; I am tracking one individual throughout, to

333 Cognitive Pluralism and Semantics

language-like cognition. Their semantic properties are determined not by

their nature as language-like units but by the fact that they are also constit-

uents of concepts. Language and language-like thinking have CLs as their

constituents, but because these are bound to CMs as conceptual structures,

language incorporates or ties into model-based semantics as well. This dis-

tinction between what is a constituent of language and what is incorporated

into it is quite useful, as it provides some insight into how there can be for-

mal languages without semantic properties (CLs that are not tied to models

or feature aggregators), and how we are capable of making syntactically

based inferences even without fully grasping the relevant concepts.

16.7 Possible Implications for Disputes about Concepts and Semantics

What I have proposed in the previous section should be viewed as some-

thing on the order of a schematic outline of a theory of conceptual seman-

tics. It is not quite so concrete as a theory, but it enumerates some of the

components that might need to go into a theory, and explores some basic

suggestions for how they might be related.

The proposal for looking forward involves a reframing of how we think

about philosophical debates in semantics. Debates about semantic theories

are too often framed as either-or debates between accounts that each focus

on different, but arguably equally legitimate, features and concerns: sense,

reference, truth, or inferential commitments; internalism versus exter-

nalism; intension versus extension; atomism versus holism. There have

been some attempts to move beyond this, such as the two-factor accounts

proposed by Field (1977) and Block (1986). My suggestion is to broaden

this approach to recognize the multiple factors that not only are a part of

semantic competence but would have to be present in any organism that

possesses the kinds of cognitive capacities that human beings possess, even

if that means that they cannot all be accommodated in a compact and tidy

account.

Conceptual atomists and direct-reference theorists have something right.

There is an element of a concept whose function is to track individuals,

kinds, properties, relations, or processes (depending on what kind of con-

cept it is): an ostensive element akin to what Husserl called the “pure x.”

Just as was the case with the triangulation of individuals through different

ways of thinking about them, so it is crucially important for us to be able

to have a way of thinking about “the same thing” through changes in our

understanding of it, and thus it seems quite necessary that concepts have

such an element. In my view, however, the ostensive tracking relationship